<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<!-- Copyright 2012-2019                                                   -->
<!-- Matthew Boelkins                                                      -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- This file is part of Active Calculus.                                 -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document -->
<!-- under the terms of the Creative Commons BY-SA license.  The work      -->
<!-- may be used for free by any party so long as attribution is given to  -->
<!-- the author(s), the work and its derivatives are used in the spirit of -->
<!-- "share and share alike".  All trademarks are the registered marks of  -->
<!-- their respective owners.                                              -->
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<worksheet label="ws-act-3-4-3">
  <activity xml:id="act-3-4-3" workspace="3cm">
    <statement>
      <p>
      Consider the region in the <m>x</m>-<m>y</m> plane that is bounded by the <m>x</m>-axis and the function <m>f(x) = 25-x^2</m>.
      Construct a rectangle whose base lies on the <m>x</m>-axis and is centered at the origin,
      and whose sides extend vertically until they intersect the curve <m>y = 25-x^2</m>.
      Which such rectangle has the maximum possible area?
      Which such rectangle has the greatest perimeter?
      Which has the greatest combined perimeter and area? (Challenge:
      answer the same questions in terms of positive parameters <m>a</m> and <m>b</m> for the function <m>f(x) = b-ax^2</m>.)
    </p>
    </statement>
    <hint>
      <p>
      Let <m>x</m> represent half the width of the rectangle's base.
      How does the rectangle's height depend on <m>x</m>?
    </p>
    </hint>
    <answer>
      <p>
      Maximum area:
      <m>A(\frac{5}{\sqrt{3}}) = \frac{500}{9}\sqrt{3} \approx 96.225</m>.
      Maximum perimeter: <m>P(1) = 52</m>.
      At <m>x = \frac{\sqrt{82}-1}{3}</m> the absolute maximum of combined perimeter and area occurs.
    </p>
    </answer>
    <solution>
      <p>
      Letting <m>x</m> represent half the width of the rectangle's base,
      it follows that the rectangle's height is <m>25-x^2</m>.
      Hence the area of the rectangle is
      <me>
        A(x) = 2x(25-x^2) = 50x - 2x^3
      </me>.
    </p>
      <p>
      Based on the region,
      the only possible values of <m>x</m> are for <m>0 \le x \le 5</m>;
      moreover, it is evident that for either <m>x = 0</m> or <m>x = 5</m>,
      the area of the corresponding rectangle is zero,
      which can't be where the maximum occurs.
      Differentiating,
      <me>
        A'(x) = 50 - 6x^2
      </me>,
      so we find the critical number of <m>A</m> by solving <m>6x^2 = 50</m>,
      which yields <m>x = \frac{5}{\sqrt{3}} \approx 2.8868</m>,
      which results in the maximum possible area of
      <me>
        A(\frac{5}{\sqrt{3}}) = \frac{500}{9}\sqrt{3} \approx 96.225
      </me>
      square units.
    </p>
      <p>
      To maximize perimeter, we note that the rectangle's perimeter is
      <me>
        P(x) = 2x + (25-x^2) + 2x + (25 - x^2) = -2x^2 + 4x + 50
      </me>.
    </p>
      <p>
      It is straightforward to show that the only critical number of the quadratic function <m>P</m> occurs when <m>x = 1</m> and that the corresponding absolute maximum value is <m>P(1) = 52</m>.
    </p>
      <p>
      Finally, to consider combined area and perimeter,
      examine the function <m>f(x) = A(x) + P(x)</m> on the interval <m>0 \le x \le 5</m>.
      You should find that the only relevant critical number is
      <m>x = \frac{\sqrt{82}-1}{3}</m> and that the absolute maximum of <m>f</m> occurs at that value.
    </p>
    </solution>
  </activity>
</worksheet>
