<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<activity xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="act-7-6-1">

      <p>Our first model will be based on the following assumption:</p>

      <blockquote>
      <em>The rate of change of the population is proportional to the
            population.  
          </em>
      </blockquote>

      <p>On the face of it, this seems pretty reasonable. When there is a
        relatively small number of people, there will be fewer births and
        deaths so the rate of change will be small. When there is a larger
        number of people, there will be more births and deaths so we expect
        a larger rate of change.</p>

      <p>If <m>P(t)</m> is the population <m>t</m> years after the year 2000, we may
      express this assumption as
      <me>
        \frac{dP}{dt} = kP
      </me>
      where <m>k</m> is a constant of proportionality.

      <ol label="a">
        <li><p>Use the data in the table to estimate the derivative <m>P'(0)</m>
              using a central difference.  Assume that <m>t=0</m> corresponds to the
              year 2000.</p></li>

        <li><p>What is the population <m>P(0)</m>?</p></li>

        <li><p>Use these two facts to estimate the constant of proportionality
              <m>k</m> in the differential equation.</p></li>

        <li><p>Now that we know the value of <m>k</m>, we have the initial
              value problem
            <me>
              \frac{dP}{dt} = kP, \ P(0) = 6.084.
            </me>
            Find the solution to this initial value problem.</p></li>

        <li><p>What does your solution predict for the population in the year
              2010?  Is this close to the actual population given in the table?</p></li>

        <li><p>When does your solution predict that the population will reach
              12 billion?</p></li>

        <li><p>What does your solution predict for the population in the year
              2500?</p></li>

        <li><p>Do you think this is a reasonable model for the earth's
              population?  Why or why not?  Explain your thinking using a couple
              of complete sentences.</p></li>
      </ol>
      </p>

      <hint>
        <p>

        <ol label="a">
          <li><p>Small hints for each of the prompts above.</p></li>
        </ol>
        </p>
      </hint>

      <answer>
        <p>

        <ol label="a">
          <li><p>Answers for each of the prompts above.</p></li>
        </ol>
        </p>
      </answer>

      <solution>
        <p>

        <ol label="a">
          <li><p>Solutions for each of the prompts above.</p></li>
        </ol>
        </p>
      </solution>
    </activity>


