<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<activity xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="act-2-7-1">

<p>
Consider the curve defined by the equation <m>x = y^5 - 5y^3 + 4y</m>, whose graph is pictured in <xref ref="F-2-7-Act1">Figure</xref>.
</p>
<figure xml:id="F-2-7-Act1" >
	<caption>The curve <m>x = y^5 - 5y^3 + 4y</m>.</caption>
	<image width="50%" source="images/2_7_Act1" />
</figure>

	<ol label="a">
		<li><p>Explain why it is not possible to express <m>y</m> as an explicit function of <m>x</m>.</p></li>
		<li><p>Use implicit differentiation to find a formula for <m>dy/dx</m>.</p></li>
		<li><p>Use your result from part (b) to find an equation of the line tangent to the graph of <m>x = y^5 -
		5y^3 + 4y</m> at the point <m>(0, 1)</m>.</p></li>
		<li><p>Use your result from part (b) to determine all of the points at
		which the graph of <m>x = y^5 - 5y^3 + 4y</m> has a vertical tangent
		line.</p></li>
	</ol>

<hint>
<p>

	<ol label="a">
		<li><p>Does the graph pass the vertical line test?</p></li>
		<li><p>Note, for instance, that <m>\frac{d}{dx}[y^5] = 5y^4</m>.</p></li>
		<li><p>Remember the meaning of <m>\left. \frac{dy}{dx} \right|_{(0,1)}</m>.</p></li>
		<li><p>What is the slope of a vertical line?</p></li>
	</ol>

</p>
</hint>

<answer>
<p>

	<ol label="a">
		<li><p>The graph of the curve fails the vertical line test.</p></li>
		<li><p>
		<m>
		  \frac{dy}{dx} = \frac{1}{5y^4 - 15y^2 + 4}.
		</m></p></li>
		<li><p><m>y = -\frac{1}{6}x + 1</m>.</p></li>
		<li><p><m>(1.418697,0.543912)</m>, <m>(-1.418697,-0.543912)</m>, <m>(-3.63143, 1.64443)</m>, and <m>(3.63143, -1.64443)</m>.</p></li>
	</ol>

</p>
</answer>

<solution>
<p>

	<ol label="a">
		<li><p>Because the graph of the curve fails the vertical line test, <m>y</m> cannot be a function of <m>x</m>.  This also confirms our intuition that there is not an algebraic means by which we can rearrange the equation <m>x = y^5 - 5y^3 + 4y</m> to write <m>y</m> in terms of <m>x</m>.</p></li>
		<li><p>We differentiate implicitly, taking the derivative of each side with respect to <m>x</m>,
		<me>
		  \frac{d}{dx}[x ]= \frac{d}{dx}[y^5 - 5y^3 + 4y],
		</me>
		and evaluate the elementary derivative on the left and use the sum rule on the right to find that
		<me>
		  1 = \frac{d}{dx}[y^5] - \frac{d}{dx}[5y^3] + \frac{d}{dx}[4y].
		</me>
		By the chain and constant multiple rules, viewing <m>y</m> as a function of <m>x</m>, we now have
		<me>
		  1 = 5y^4\frac{dy}{dx} - 15y^2\frac{dy}{dx} + 4\frac{dy}{dx}.
		</me>
		Factoring,
		<me>
		  1 = \frac{dy}{dx}(5y^4 - 15y^2 + 4),
		</me>
		and therefore
		<me>
		  \frac{dy}{dx} = \frac{1}{5y^4 - 15y^2 + 4}.
		</me></p></li>
		<li><p>To find an equation of the line tangent to the graph of <m>x = y^5 - 5y^3 + 4y</m> at the point <m>(0, 1)</m>, we only need the slope of the tangent line.  Hence we compute
		<me>
		  \left. \frac{dy}{dx} \right|_{(0,1)} = \frac{1}{5 \cdot 1^4 - 15 \cdot 1^2 + 4} = -\frac{1}{6}.
		</me>
		Therefore, the equation of the tangent line is
		<me>
		  y - 1 = -\frac{1}{6}(x-0)
		</me>
		or <m>y = -\frac{1}{6}x + 1</m>.</p></li>
		<li><p>Since a line is vertical whenever its slope is undefined, we seek all points <m>(x,y)</m> that make <m>\frac{dy}{dx}</m> undefined.  This will occur precisely when the denominator, <m>5y^4 - 15y^2 + 4</m>, is zero.  Using a graphing utility or computer algebra system to solve the equation <m>5y^4 - 15y^2 + 4 = 0</m>, we find that this happens at the four approximate <m>y</m>-values <m>y \approx \pm 0.543912, \pm 1.64443</m>.  For each such value, we use the original equation <m>x = y^5 - 5y^3 + 4y</m> to find the <m>x</m>-value of the point.  Doing so, we have established that there are four points at which the tangent line is vertical, and they are approximately <m>(1.418697,0.543912)</m>, <m>(-1.418697,-0.543912)</m>, <m>(-3.63143, 1.64443)</m>, and <m>(3.63143, -1.64443)</m>.</p></li>
	</ol>

</p>
</solution>
</activity>	

