<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<activity xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="act-6-2-2">
<statement>
<p>In each of the following questions, draw a careful, labeled sketch of the region described, as well as the resulting solid that results from revolving the region about the stated axis. In addition, draw a representative slice and state the volume of that slice, along with a definite integral whose value is the volume of the entire solid. It is not necessary to evaluate the integrals you find.

      <ol label="a.">
        <li><p>The region <m>S</m> bounded by the <m>y</m>-axis, the curve <m>y = \sqrt{x}</m>, and the line <m>y = 2</m>; revolve <m>S</m> about the <m>y</m>-axis.</p></li>

        <li><p>The region <m>S</m> bounded by the <m>x</m>-axis, the curve <m>y = \sqrt{x}</m>, and the line <m>x = 4</m>; revolve <m>S</m> about the <m>y</m>-axis.</p></li>

        <li><p>The finite region <m>S</m> in the first quadrant bounded by the curves <m>y = 2x</m> and <m>y = x^3</m>; revolve <m>S</m> about the <m>x</m>-axis.</p></li>

        <li><p>The finite region <m>S</m> in the first quadrant bounded by the curves <m>y = 2x</m> and <m>y = x^3</m>; revolve <m>S</m> about the <m>y</m>-axis.</p></li>

        <li><p>The finite region <m>S</m> bounded by the curves <m>x = (y-1)^2</m> and <m>y  = x-1</m>; revolve <m>S</m> about the <m>y</m>-axis</p></li>
      </ol>
      </p>

</statement>
      <hint>
        <p>

        <ol label="a.">
          <li><p>Consider slices perpendicular to the <m>y</m>-axis.</p></li>
          <li><p>Since we revolve around the <m>y</m>-axis, think about slices of thickness <m>\triangle y</m>.</p></li>
          <li><p>Note that <m>y = x^3</m> lies below <m>y = 2x</m> on the interval <m>[0,\sqrt{2}].</m></p></li>
          <li><p>The curve <m>y = x^3</m> can be equivalently expressed as <m>x = \sqrt[3]{y}.</m></p></li>
          <li><p>Find the intersection points by writing the second curve as <m>x = y+1</m> and solving <m>(y-1)^2 = y+1</m>.</p></li>
        </ol>
        </p>
      </hint>

      <answer>
        <p>

        <ol label="a.">
          <li><p>
          <m>V = \int_0^2 \pi y^4 \triangle \, dy.</m>
            </p></li>
            <li><p>
                <m>V = \int_0^2 \pi (16 - y^4) \, dy.</m>
            </p></li>
            <li><p>
                <m>V = int_0^{\sqrt{2}} \pi ( 4x^2 - x^6 ) \, dx.</m>
            </p></li>
            <li><p>
                <m>V = \int_0^{2\sqrt{2}} \pi( y^{2/3} - y^2/4 ) \, dy. </m>
            </p></li>
            <li><p>
              <m>V = \int_0^3 \pi( (y+1)^2 - (y-1)^4 ) \, dy. </m>
            </p></li>
        </ol>
        </p>
      </answer>

      <solution>
        <p>

        <ol label="a.">
          <li><p>Observe that horizontal slices with thickness <m>\triangle y</m> are all cylindrical disks, each with radius given by <m>r(y) = y^2</m> since they are given by the curve <m>y = \sqrt{x}</m>, which can be equivalently expressed as <m>x = y^2</m>.  The volume of each slice is thus
          <me>V_{\text{slice}} = \pi r(y)^2 \triangle y = \pi y^4 \triangle y.</me>
          The volume of the solid is thus given by the definite integral
          <me>V = \int_0^2 \pi y^4 \triangle \, dy.</me>
            </p></li>
            <li><p>
                Slicing perpendicular to the axis of rotation, we get slices of thickness <m>\triangle y</m> that are shaped like washers.  The outer radius, <m>R(y)</m>, is given by <m>R(y) = 4</m>; the innner radius is given by the function <m>y = \sqrt{x},</m> but expressed with <m>x</m> as a function of <m>y</m>, so <m>r(y) = y^2</m>.  It follows that a representative washer slice has volume
                <me>V_{\text{slice}} = \pi (R(y)^2 - r(y)^2) \triangle y = \pi (16 - y^4) \triangle y.</me>
                Further, since <m>y = \sqrt{x}</m> and <m>x = 4</m> intersect at the point <m>(4,2)</m>, we integrate from <m>y = 0</m> to <m>y = 2</m> and thus find that the total volume is
                <me>V = \int_0^2 \pi (16 - y^4) \, dy.</me>
            </p></li>
            <li><p>
                The curves <m>y=x^3</m> and <m>y=2x</m> intersect where <m>x^3 = 2x</m>, so where <m>x^3-2x = x(x^2 - 2) = 0</m>.  The two nonnegative values of <m>x</m> that make this equation true are <m>x=0</m> and <m>x=\sqrt{2}</m>, and thus the points <m>(0,0)</m> and <m>(\sqrt{2}, 2\sqrt{2})</m> form the boundaries of the region <m>S</m> that is being rotated about the <m>x</m>-axis.  Since we rotate about the horizontal axis, we slice perpendicular to that axis with slices of thickness <m>\triangle x</m>.   A representative slice is in the shape of a washer and has volume
                <me>V_{\text{slice}} = \pi (R(x)^2 - r(x)^2) \triangle x = \pi ( (2x)^2 - (x^3)^2 ) \triangle x,</me>
                and thus the total volume of the solid is
                <me>V = int_0^{\sqrt{2}} \pi ( 4x^2 - x^6 ) \, dx.</me>
            </p></li>
            <li><p>
                To use the same region <m>S</m> as in part (c), but now revolved about the <m>y</m>-axis, we shift to horizontal slices of thickness <m>\triangle y</m>, and thus need to express the curves as functions of <m>y</m>: the rightmost curve is <m>x = R(y) = \sqrt[3]{y}</m>, while the leftmost curve is <m>x = r(y) = \frac{1}{2}y.</m>  A representative slice is a washer whose volume is
                <me>V_{\text{slice}} = \pi (R(y)^2 - r(y)^2) \triangle y = \pi( (\sqrt[3]{y})^2 - (\frac{1}{2}y)^2) \triangle y.</me>
                It follows that the total volume of the solid is
                <me>V = \int_0^{2\sqrt{2}} \pi( y^{2/3} - y^2/4 ) \, dy. </me>
            </p></li>
            <li><p>
                For this pair of curves, we see they intersect where <m>x=(y-1)^2</m> and <m>x = (y+1)</m> are both true, and hence where <m>(y-1)^2 = y+1.</m>  Expanding, moving all terms to the left, and combining like terms, we see that <m>y^2 - 2y + 1 = y + 1</m>, so
              <m>y^2 - 3y = 0</m>.  It follows that <m>y(y-3) = 0</m> and therefore <m>y=3</m> or <m>y = 0.</m>  Plotting the region and revolving about the <m>y</m>-axis, we see that horizontal slices of thickness <m>\triangle y</m> are shaped like washers.  The outer radius is given by <m>R(y) = y+1</m>, while the inner radius is <m>r(y) = (y-1)^2</m>.  A representative slice thus has volume
              <me>V_{\text{slice}} = \pi (R(y)^2 - r(y)^2) \triangle y = \pi( (y+1)^2 - ((y-1)^2)^2 ) \triangle y.</me>
              The volume of the solid of revolution is therefore
              <me>V = \int_0^3 \pi( (y+1)^2 - (y-1)^4 ) \, dy. </me>
            </p></li>
        </ol>
        </p>
      </solution>


    </activity>