<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
  <activity xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="act-1-2-3">
     <title>A moving object with position given by a graph</title>
        <statement>
          <p>
          For the moving object whose position <m>s</m> at time <m>t</m> is given by the graph below, answer each of the following questions. Assume that <m>s</m> is measured in feet and <m>t</m> is measured in seconds.
          </p>
            <figure>
              <caption>Plot of the position function <m>y = s(t)</m> in <xref ref="act-1-2-3">Activity</xref>.</caption>
              <image width="50%" source="images/1_2_Act3" /> 
            </figure>
            <ol label="alpha">
              <li>Use the graph to estimate the average velocity of the object on each of the following intervals: <m>[0.5,1]</m>, <m>[1.5,2.5]</m>, <m>[0,5]</m>.  Draw each line whose slope represents the average velocity you seek.</li>
              <li>How could you use average velocities or slopes of lines to estimate the instantaneous velocity of the object at a fixed time?</li>
              <li>Use the graph to estimate the instantaneous velocity of the object when <m>t = 2</m>.  Should this instantaneous velocity at <m>t = 2</m> be greater or less than the average velocity on <m>[1.5,2.5]</m> that you computed in (a)?  Why?</li>
            </ol>
        </statement>
        <hint>
          <ol label="alpha">
            <li>Remember that average velocity on an interval computes the quotient of <q>change in <m>s</m> over change in <m>t</m>.</q>  This is the slope of the line between the corresponding two points on the graph of <m>s</m>.</li>
            <li>Think about shorter and shorter time intervals and drawing the lines whose slopes represent average velocity.</li>
            <li>Think about zooming in on the graph at <m>t = 2</m> and drawing a line that, up close, looks just like the curve <m>s(t)</m>.  What is the approximate slope of that line?</li>
          </ol> 
        </hint> 
        <answer>
          <ol label="alpha">
            <li> <m>AV_{[0.5,1]} = \frac{1-1}{1-0.5} = 0</m>, <m>AV_{[1.5,2.5]} = \frac{3-1}{2.5-1.5} = 2</m>, and <m>AV_{[0,5]} = \frac{5-0}{5-0} = 1</m>.</li>
            <li>Take shorter and shorter time intervals and draw the lines whose slopes represent average velocity.  If those lines' slopes are approaching a single number, that number represents the instantaneous velocity.</li>
            <li>The instantaneous velocity at <m>t = 2</m> is greater than the average velocity on <m>[1.5,2.5]</m>.</li>
          </ol> 
 
        </answer>
        <solution>
           <ol label="alpha">
            <li>The average velocity on <m>[0.5,1]</m> is the slope of the line joining the points <m>(0.5,s(0.5))</m> and <m>(1,s(1))</m>, which is <m>AV_{[0.5,1]} = \frac{1-1}{1-0.5} = 0</m>.  On <m>[1.5,2.5]</m>, we similarly find <m>AV_{[1.5,2.5]} = \frac{3-1}{2.5-1.5} = 2</m>, and on <m>[0,5]</m>, we have <m>AV_{[0,5]} = \frac{5-0}{5-0} = 1</m>.</li>
            <li>Take shorter and shorter time intervals and draw the lines whose slopes represent average velocity.  If those lines' slopes are approaching a single number, that number represents the instantaneous velocity.  For example, to estimate the instantaneous velocity at <m>t = 2</m>, we might consider average velocities on <m>[2,3]</m>, <m>[2,2.5]</m>, and <m>[2,2.25]</m>.</li>
            <li>If we draw the line through <m>(2,2)</m> and <m>(2.1,s(2.1))</m>, it looks like the line's slope is approximately 2.5: if we go over one grid-width, we appear to go up about 2.5.  The slope of this line is clearly greater than the slope of the line through <m>(1.5, s(1.5))</m> and <m>(2.5, s(2.5))</m>, which is 2. Hence the instantaneous velocity at <m>t = 2</m> is greater than the average velocity on <m>[1.5,2.5]</m>.</li>
          </ol> 
        </solution>
  </activity>



