<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<activity xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="act-6-4-3">

      <p>In each of the following problems, determine the total force exerted by water against the surface that is described.</p>

      <figure xml:id="F-6-4-Act3Trough" >
        <caption>A trough with triangular ends, as described in <xref ref="act-6-4-3">Activity</xref>, part (c).</caption>
        <image width="50%" source="images/6_4_Act2Trough" />
      </figure>

      <p><ol label="a">
        <li><p>Consider a rectangular dam that is 100 feet wide and 50 feet tall, and suppose that water presses against the dam all the way to the top.</p></li>

        <li><p>Consider a semicircular dam with a radius of 30 feet.  Suppose that the water rises to within 10 feet of the top of the dam.</p></li>

        <li><p>Consider a trough with triangular ends, as pictured in <xref ref="F-6-4-Act3Trough">Figure</xref>, where the tank is 10 feet long, the top is 5 feet wide, and the tank is 4 feet deep.  Say that the trough is full to within 1 foot of the top with water of weight density 62.4 pounds/ft<m>^3</m>.  How much force does the water exert against one of the triangular ends?</p></li>
      </ol></p>

      <hint>
        <p>

        <ol label="a">
          <li><p>Put the center of the top of the dam at the origin and let the positive <m>x</m>-axis point down.</p></li>
          <li><p>With the positive <m>x</m>-axis pointing down, the equation for the edge of the semi-circular dam is <m>y = \sqrt{900-x^2}</m>.</p></li>
          <li><p>The equation for the line that bounds the right side of the trough is <m>y = -\frac{5}{8}x + 2.5 </m>.</p></li>
        </ol>
        </p>
      </hint>

      <answer>
        <p>

        <ol label="a">
          <li><p>
            <m>
              F = \int_{x = 0}^{x=50} (6240 x) dx = 7~800~000 \text{ pounds } .
            </m>
          </p></li>
          <li><p>
            <m>
              F = \int_{x=4}^{x=30} 124.8 (x - 4)\sqrt{900 - x^2} dx = 800~244 \text{ pounds } .
            </m>
          </p></li>
          <li><p>
            <m>
              F = \int_{x=1}^{x=4} 62.4 (x - 1)(5 - 1.25x) dx = 351 \text{ pounds } .
            </m>
            </p></li>
        </ol>
        </p>
      </answer>

      <solution>
        <p>

        <ol label="a">
          <li><p>
          	We let the positive <m>x</m>-axis point down and let <m>x</m> be the distance from the top of the dam.  The area of a typical horizontal slice (in square feet) is
            <me>
              A_{\text{ slice } } = 100 \Delta x.
            </me>
            The pressure (in pounds per square foot) at depth <m>x</m> is given by <m>P_{\text{ slice } } = 62.5 x</m>.  So the force on a typical slice (in pounds) is
            <me>
              F_{\text{ slice } } = (62.4x)(100 \Delta x) = 6240 x \Delta x.
            </me>
            So the force of the water against the dam is
            <me>
              F = \int_{x = 0}^{x=50} (6240 x) dx = 7~800~000 \text{ pounds } .
            </me>
          </p></li>
          <li><p>
          	We let the positive <m>x</m>-axis point down and let <m>x</m> be the distance from the top of the dam.  We place the top of the dam along the <m>x</m>-axis with the center at the origin.  So the equation for the semicircle is
            <m>y = \sqrt{30^2 - x^2} = \sqrt{900 - x^2}</m>.
            The area of a typical horizontal slice (in square feet) is
            <me>
              A_{\text{ slice } } = 2y \Delta x = 2 \sqrt{900 - x^2} \Delta x.
            </me>
            At a given value of <m>x</m>, the depth of the water is <m>(x - 4)</m>.  So the pressure (in pounds per square foot) at  <m>x</m> is given by <m>P_{\text{ slice } } = 62.4 (x - 4)</m>.  So the force on a typical slice (in pounds) is
            <me>
              F_{\text{ slice } } = 62.4(x - 4) \left(2 \sqrt{900 - x^2} \Delta x \right) = 124.8 (x - 4)\sqrt{900 - x^2} \Delta x .
            </me>
            So the force of the water against the dam is
            <me>
              F = \int_{x=4}^{x=30} 124.8 (x - 4)\sqrt{900 - x^2} dx = 800~244 \text{ pounds } .
            </me>
          </p></li>
          <li><p>
            We let the positive <m>x</m>-axis point down and let <m>x</m> be the distance from the top of the dam.  We place the top of the trough along the <m>x</m>-axis with the center at the origin.  We need the equation for the straight line from the point <m>(0, 2.5)</m> to the point <m>(4, 0)</m>.  The equation for this line is <m>y = -\frac{5}{8}x + 2.5 = 2.5 - 0.625x</m>.
            The area of a typical horizontal slice (in square feet) is
            <me>
              A_{\text{ slice } } = 2y \Delta x = 2(2.5 - 0.625x) \Delta x = (5 - 1.25x)  \Delta x.
            </me>
            At a given value of <m>x</m>, the depth of the water is <m>(x - 1)</m>.  So the pressure (in pounds per square foot) at  <m>x</m> is given by <m>P_{\text{ slice } } = 62.4 (x - 1)</m>.  So the force on a typical slice (in pounds) is
            <me>
              F_{\text{ slice } } = 62.4(x - 1) \left( 5 - 1.25x \Delta x \right) = 62.4 (x - 1)(5 - 1.25x) \Delta x .
            </me>
            So the force of the water against the trough is
            <me>
              F = \int_{x=1}^{x=4} 62.4 (x - 1)(5 - 1.25x) dx = 351 \text{ pounds } .
            </me>
            </p></li>
        </ol>
        </p>
      </solution>
    </activity>
