<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<activity xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="act-3-1-2">
<statement>
<p>
Suppose that <m>g</m> is a function whose second derivative, <m>g''</m>, is given by the following graph.
</p>
<figure xml:id="F-3-1-Act2" >
    <caption>The graph of <m>y = g''(x)</m>.</caption>
    <image width="50%" source="images/3_1_Act2" />
</figure>

    <p><ol label="a.">
        <li><p>Find the <m>x</m>-coordinates of all points of inflection of <m>g</m>.</p></li>
        <li><p>Fully describe the concavity of <m>g</m> by making an appropriate sign chart.</p></li>
        <li><p>Suppose you are given that <m>g'(-1.67857351) = 0</m>.  Is there is a local maximum, local minimum, or neither (for the function <m>g</m>) at this critical number of <m>g</m>, or is it impossible to say?  Why?</p></li>
        <li><p>Assuming that <m>g''(x)</m> is a polynomial (and that all important behavior of <m>g''</m> is seen in the graph above), what degree polynomial do you think <m>g(x)</m> is?  Why?</p></li>
    </ol></p>
</statement>
<hint>
<p>

    <ol label="a.">
        <li><p>What must be true of <m>g''(x)</m> at a point of inflection?</p></li>
        <li><p>Use the given graph to decide where <m>g''</m> is positive and negative.</p></li>
        <li><p>What does the second derivative test say?</p></li>
        <li><p>Can you guess a formula for <m>g''(x)</m> based on its graph?</p></li>
    </ol>

</p>
</hint>

<answer>
<p>
    <ol label="a.">
        <li><p><m>x = -1</m> is an inflection point of <m>g</m>.</p></li>
        <li><p><m>g</m> is concave up for <m>x \lt  -1</m>, concave down for <m>-1 \lt  x \lt  2</m>, and concave down for <m>x \gt 2</m>.</p></li>
        <li><p><m>g</m> has a local minimum at <m>x = -1.67857351</m>.</p></li>
        <li><p><m>g</m> is a degree 5 polynomial.</p></li>
    </ol>

</p>
</answer>

<solution>
<p>

    <ol label="a.">
        <li><p>Based on the given graph of <m>g''</m>, the only point at which <m>g''</m> changes sign is <m>x = -1</m>, and hence this is an inflection point of <m>g</m>.</p></li>
        <li><p>Note that <m>g''(x) \gt 0</m> for <m>x \lt  -1</m>, <m>g''(x) \lt  0</m> for <m>-1 \lt  x \lt  2</m>, and <m>g''(x) \lt  0</m> for <m>x \gt 2</m>.  This tells us that <m>g</m> is concave up for <m>x \lt  -1</m>, concave down for <m>-1 \lt  x \lt  2</m>, and concave down for <m>x \gt 2</m>.</p></li>
        <li><p>Given that <m>g'(-1.67857351) = 0</m>, we know that <m>g</m> has a horizontal tangent line at this critical number.  In addition, from the given graph of <m>g''</m>, we see that <m>g''( -1.67857351) \gt 0</m> and observe that <m>g</m> is concave up at <m>x</m>-values near <m>-1.67857351</m>.  By the second derivative test, <m>g</m> has a local minimum at <m>x = -1.67857351</m>.</p></li>
        <li><p>From the given graph, since <m>g''</m> has a simple zero at <m>x = -1</m> and a repeated zero at <m>x = 2</m>, it appears that <m>g''</m> is a degree 3 polynomial.  If so, then <m>g'</m> is a degree 4 polynomial, and <m>g</m> is a degree 5 polynomial.</p></li>
    </ol>

</p>
</solution>
</activity>

