<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<activity xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="act-4-1-2">
<statement>
<p>A ball is tossed vertically in such a way that its velocity function is given by <m>v(t) = 32 - 32t</m>, where <m>t</m> is measured in seconds and <m>v</m> in feet per second. Assume that this function is valid for <m>0 \le t \le 2</m>.

      <ol label="a">
        <li><p>For what values of <m>t</m> is the velocity of the ball positive?  What does this tell you about the motion of the ball on this interval of time values?</p></li>

        <li><p>Find an antiderivative, <m>s</m>, of <m>v</m> that satisfies <m>s(0) = 0</m>.</p></li>

        <li><p>Compute the value of <m>s(1) - s(\frac{1}{2})</m>.  What is the meaning of the value you find?</p></li>

        <li><p>Using the graph of <m>y = v(t)</m> provided in <xref ref="F-4-1-Act2">Figure</xref>, find the exact area of the region under the velocity curve between <m>t = \frac{1}{2}</m> and <m>t = 1</m>.  What is the meaning of the value you find?</p></li>

        <li><p>Answer the same questions as in (c) and (d) but instead using the interval <m>[0,1]</m>.</p></li>

        <li><p>What is the value of <m>s(2) - s(0)</m>?  What does this result tell you about the flight of the ball?  How is this value connected to the provided graph of <m>y = v(t)</m>?  Explain.</p></li>
      </ol>
      </p>

      <figure xml:id="F-4-1-Act2" >
        <caption>The graph of <m>y = v(t)</m>.</caption>
        <image width="50%" source="images/4_1_Act2" />
      </figure>

</statement>
      <hint>
        <p>

        <ol label="a">
          <li><p>Where is velocity zero?</p></li>

          <li><p>Since <m>v</m> is linear, note that <m>s</m> must be quadratic.</p></li>

          <li><p>Observe that you are taking the difference between two values of the position function.</p></li>

          <li><p>The region whose area is sought is triangular.</p></li>

          <li><p>See (c) and (d) above.</p></li>

          <li><p>What does it mean for the change of the ball's position to be zero?</p></li>
        </ol>
        </p>
      </hint>

      <answer>
        <p>

        <ol label="a">
          <li><p>On <m>(0,1)</m>, <m>s</m> is increasing because velocity is positive.</p></li>

          <li><p><m>s(t) = 32t - 16t^2</m>.</p></li>

          <li><p><m>s(1) - s(\frac{1}{2}) = 4</m>.</p></li>

          <li><p><m>A = 4</m> feet is the total distance the ball traveled vertically on <m>[0,\frac{1}{2}]</m>.</p></li>

          <li><p><m>s(1) - s(0) = 16</m> is the vertical distance the ball traveled on the interval <m>[0,1]</m>.  Equivalently, the area under the velocity curve on <m>[0,1]</m> is <m>A = 16</m> feet.  </p></li>

          <li><p><m>s(2) - s(0) = 0</m>, so the ball has zero change in position on the interval <m>[0,2]</m>.</p></li>
        </ol>
        </p>
      </answer>

      <solution>
        <p>

        <ol label="a">
          <li><p>Note that <m>v(1) = 0</m> and for <m>0 \lt  t \lt  1</m>, <m>v(t) \gt 0</m>.  This means that on the interval <m>(0,1)</m>, the position function <m>s</m> is increasing because velocity is positive.</p></li>

          <li><p>We can check that the derivative of <m>s(t) = 32t - 16t^2</m> is <m>s'(t) = v(t) = 32 - 32t</m>, and that <m>s(0) = 0</m>, so this is the antiderivative of <m>v</m> that we desire.</p></li>

          <li><p>Now, <m>s(1) - s(\frac{1}{2}) = (32 - 16) - (16 - 4) = 4</m>, which is the change in position of the ball on the interval <m>[\frac{1}{2},1]</m>.  Equivalently, since <m>v</m> is positive through this interval, 4 feet is the vertical distance the ball traveled during this time.</p></li>

          <li><p>On the interval from <m>t = \frac{1}{2}</m> to <m>t = 1</m>, the corresponding area under the velocity curve is the area of the right triangular region whose width is <m>\frac{1}{2}</m> seconds and whose height is <m>v(\frac{1}{2}) = 16</m> feet/sec.  That area is therefore <m>A = \frac{1}{2} bh = \frac{1}{2} \cdot \frac{1}{2} \cdot 16 = 4</m> feet.  This is the total distance the ball traveled vertically on <m>[0,\frac{1}{2}]</m>.</p></li>

          <li><p><m>s(1) - s(0) = (32 - 16) - (0-0) = 16</m>, which is the vertical distance the ball traveled on the interval <m>[0,1]</m>.  The area under the velocity curve on <m>[0,1]</m> is the area of the triangle with height 32 (ft/sec) and base 1 (second), which is <m>A = \frac{1}{2} \cdot 1 \cdot 32 = 16</m> feet.  These two results are identical, in part due to the fact that we are using two different perspectives to compute the same quantity, which is distance traveled.</p></li>

          <li><p>Observe that <m>s(2) - s(0) = (32 - 32) - (0 - 0) = 0</m>.  This means that the ball has zero change in position on the interval <m>[0,2]</m>.  But we already established that on the interval <m>[0,1]</m>, the ball traveled 16 feet vertically; since the velocity becomes negative on the interval <m>1 \lt  t \lt  2</m>, there we know the ball's position is decreasing, so it is falling back to earth.  The resulting zero change in position means that at <m>t = 2</m> the ball has returned to the location from which it was tossed.  If we view the area between the velocity function and the <m>t</m>-axis as being negative wherever <m>v</m> is negative, then we see that the areas of the two triangles involved are opposites, which in some sense results in the <q>total area</q> being zero, matching the change in position.</p></li>
        </ol>
        </p>
      </solution>
    </activity>	

