<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
  <activity xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="act-1-3-3">
     <title>Population Growth</title>
        <statement>
        <p>
        A rapidly growing city in Arizona has its population <m>P</m> at time <m>t</m>, where <m>t</m> is the number of decades after the year 2010, modeled by the formula <m>P(t) = 25000 e^{t/5}</m>. Use this function to respond to the following questions.
        </p>

          <ol label="a">
            <li>Sketch an accurate graph of <m>P</m> for <m>t = 0</m> to <m>t = 5</m> on the axes provided in <xref ref="F-1-3-Act3">Figure</xref>.  Label the scale on the axes carefully.
            <figure xml:id="F-1-3-Act3" >
            <caption>Axes for plotting <m>y = P(t)</m> in <xref ref="act-1-3-3">Activity</xref>.</caption>
            <image width="50%" source="images/1_3_Act3" /> </figure>
            </li>
            <li>Compute the average rate of change of <m>P</m> between 2030 and 2050.  Include units on your answer and write one sentence to explain the meaning (in everyday language) of the value you found.</li>
            <li>Use the limit definition to write an expression for the instantaneous rate of change of <m>P</m> with respect to time, <m>t</m>, at the instant <m>a = 2</m>.  Explain why this limit is difficult to evaluate exactly.</li>
            <li>Estimate the limit in (c) for the instantaneous rate of change of <m>P</m> at the instant <m>a = 2</m> by using several small <m>h</m> values.  Once you have determined an accurate estimate of <m>P'(2)</m>, include units on your answer, and write one sentence (using everyday language) to explain the meaning of the value you found.</li>
            <li>On your graph above, sketch two lines:  one whose slope represents the average rate of change of <m>P</m> on <m>[2,4]</m>, the other whose slope represents the instantaneous rate of change of <m>P</m> at the instant <m>a=2</m>.</li>
            <li>In a carefully-worded sentence, describe the behavior of <m>P'(a)</m> as <m>a</m> increases in value.  What does this reflect about the behavior of the given function <m>P</m>?</li>
          </ol>
        </statement>
        <hint>
          <p><ol label="a">
            <li><m>P(t)</m> is the standard exponential function, scaled by <m>25000</m>.</li>
            <li>Use the formula for the average rate of change of a function.</li>
            <li>Because of the exponential nature of <m>P(t)</m>, we're not able to simplify <m>\frac{P(2+h)-P(2)}{h}</m> in a way that removes <m>h</m> from the denominator.</li>
            <li>Try using <m>h = 0.001, 0.0001, 0.00001</m> and <m>h = -0.001, -0.0001, -0.00001</m>.  Be careful not to round or use computing precision that is too limited.</li>
            <li>For the first line, think about the points <m>(2,P(2))</m> and <m>(4,P(4))</m>.</li>
            <li>Visualize the slope of the tangent line and how it changes as a point moves along the curve.</li>
          </ol></p>
        </hint>  
        <answer>
        <p><ol label="a">
          <li><image width="50%" source="images/1_3_Act3Soln" /> </li>
          <li><m>AV_{[2,4]} \approx 9171</m> people per decade is expected to be the average rate of change of the city's population over the two decades from 2030 to 2050.</li>
          <li>
          <me>
          P'(2) =  \lim_{h \to 0} \frac{P(2+h)-P(2)}{h} \approx 7458.5
          </me>
          which is measured in people per decade.</li>
          <li>See the graph provided in (a) above.  The magenta line has slope equal to the average rate of change of <m>P</m> on <m>[2,4]</m>, while the green line is the tangent line at <m>(2,P(2))</m> with slope <m>P'(2)</m>.</li>
          <li>It appears that the tangent line's slope at the point <m>(a,P(a))</m> will increase as <m>a</m> increases.</li>
         </ol></p>
        </answer>
        <solution>
        <p><ol label="a">
          <li><image width="50%" source="images/1_3_Act3Soln" /> </li>
          <li><m>AV_{[2,4]} = \frac{P(4)-P(2)}{4-2} = \frac{25000e^{4/5} - 25000e^{2/5}}{2} \approx 9171</m> people per decade is expected to be the average rate of change of the city's population over the two decades from 2030 to 2050.</li>
          <li>Note that
          <md>
            <mrow>P'(2) = \amp  \lim_{h \to 0} \frac{P(2+h)-P(2)}{h} = \lim_{h \to 0} \frac{25000 e^{(2+h)/5}-25000e^{2/5}}{h}</mrow>
            <mrow>      = \amp   \lim_{h \to 0} \frac{25000 e^{2/5} e^{h/5} -25000e^{2/5}}{h} =  \lim_{h \to 0} 25000e^{2/5}\left( \frac{e^{h/5} - 1}{h}\right)</mrow>
          </md>
         
          Because there is no way to remove a factor of <m>h</m> from the numerator, we cannot eliminate the <m>h</m> that is making the denominator go to zero, so it appears we need to be content estimating the limit with small values of <m>h</m>.</li>
          <li>Using <m>h = 0.00001</m>, we find <m>\frac{P(2+0.00001)-P(2)}{0.00001} \approx 7457</m>; using <m>h = -0.00001</m>, we find <m>\frac{P(2-0.00001)-P(2)}{-0.00001} \approx 7460</m>.  Averaging these two results, we find that
            
          <me>
          P'(2) =  \lim_{h \to 0} \frac{P(2+h)-P(2)}{h} \approx 7458.5
          </me>
           
          which is measured in people per decade.</li>
          <li>See the graph provided in (a) above.  The magenta line has slope equal to the average rate of change of <m>P</m> on <m>[2,4]</m>, while the green line is the tangent line at <m>(2,P(2))</m> with slope <m>P'(2)</m>.</li>
          <li>If we consider the point where <m>t = a</m> and let <m>a</m> start at 0 and then increase, it appears that the tangent line's slope at the point <m>(a,P(a))</m> will increase as <m>a</m> increases.</li>
         </ol></p>
        </solution>
  </activity>

