<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<activity xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="act-2-7-2">
<statement>
<p>
Consider the curve defined by the equation <m>y(y^2-1)(y-2) = x(x-1)(x-2)</m>, whose graph is pictured in <xref ref="F-2-7-Act2">Figure</xref>.
</p>
<figure xml:id="F-2-7-Act2" >
    <caption>The curve <m>y(y^2-1)(y-2) = x(x-1)(x-2)</m>.</caption>
    <image width="50%" source="images/2_7_Act2" />
</figure>
<p>
Through implicit differentiation, it can be shown that
<me>
  \frac{dy}{dx} = \frac{(x-1)(x-2) + x(x-2) + x(x-1)}{(y^2-1)(y-2) + 2y^2(y-2) + y(y^2-1)}.
</me>
</p>

<p>
Use this fact to answer each of the following questions.
    <ol label="a.">
        <li><p>Determine all points <m>(x,y)</m> at which the tangent line to the curve is horizontal.  (Use technology appropriately to find the needed zeros of the relevant polynomial function.)</p></li>
        <li><p>Determine all points <m>(x,y)</m> at which the tangent line is vertical.  (Use technology appropriately to find the needed zeros of the relevant polynomial function.)</p></li>
        <li><p>Find the equation of the tangent line to the curve at one of the points where <m>x = 1</m>.</p></li>
    </ol>

</p>
</statement>
<hint>
<p>

    <ol label="a.">
        <li><p>Note that the numerator of <m>\frac{dy}{dx}</m> is a quadratic function of <m>x</m>.</p></li>
        <li><p>The denominator of <m>\frac{dy}{dx}</m> is a cubic function of <m>y</m>.</p></li>
        <li><p>When <m>x = 1</m>, then <m>y</m> must satisfy the equation <m>y(y^2-1)(y-2) = 0</m>.</p></li>
    </ol>

</p>
</hint>

<answer>
<p>

    <ol label="a.">
        <li><p>Horizontal at <m>x \approx 0.42265</m>, thus
        <m>
          (0.42265, -1.05782); (0.42265, 0.229478);  (0.42265, 0.770522); (0.42265, 2.05782).
        </m>
        There are four more points where <m>x \approx 1.57735</m>.</p></li>
        <li><p>When <m>y = \frac{1}{2}, \frac{1 \pm \sqrt{5}}{2},</m>  so one point is <m>(2.21028, \frac{1}{2})</m>.</p></li>
        <li><p><m>y - 1 = \frac{1}{2}(x-1)</m>.</p></li>
    </ol>

</p>
</answer>

<solution>
<p>

    <ol label="a.">
        <li><p>To find where the tangent line to the curve is horizontal, we set <m>\frac{dy}{dx} = 0</m>, which requires that the numerator be zero, or in other words that
        <me>
          (x-1)(x-2) + x(x-2) + x(x-1) = 0.
        </me>
        Expanding and combining like terms, we find that <m>3x^2 - 6x + 2 = 0</m>, which occurs where <m>x = \frac{3\pm\sqrt{3}}{3} \approx 0.42265, 1.57735</m>. From the graph in <xref ref="F-2-7-Act2">Figure</xref>, we observe that at each such <m>x</m>-value, there are several corresponding <m>y</m>-values for which the tangent line will be horizontal.  For instance, when <m>x = 0.42265</m>, then <m>y</m> must satisfy the equation
        <me>
          y(y^2-1)(y-2) = 0.42265(0.42265-1)(0.42265-2) = 0.384900.
        </me>
        Because this is a quartic equation (degree 4) equation in <m>y</m>, we use computational technology to help us find the solutions.  Doing so, we find four approximate values for <m>y</m>, <m>y \approx -1.05782, 0.229478, 0.770522, 2.05782</m>, and thus our estimates for four points at which the tangent line is horizontal are
        <me>
          (0.42265, -1.05782); (0.42265, 0.229478);  (0.42265, 0.770522); (0.42265, 2.05782).
        </me>
        Similar work can be done to find the four points at which the tangent line is horizontal when <m>x \approx 1.57735</m>.</p></li>
        <li><p>The tangent line to the curve is vertical wherever <m>\frac{dy}{dx}</m> is undefined, which occurs precisely where
        <me>
          (y^2-1)(y-2) + 2y^2(y-2) + y(y^2-1) = 0.
        </me>
        Expanding and combining like terms, we see that we need to solve the cubic equation <m>4y^3 - 6y^2 - 2y + 2 = 0</m>; using a computer algebra system, we find that this occurs when <m>y = \frac{1}{2}, \frac{1 \pm \sqrt{5}}{2}.</m>  It now remains to find the <m>x</m>-coordinate that corresponds to each such <m>y</m>-value.  For instance, when <m>y = \frac{1}{2}</m>, <m>x</m> must satisfy
        <me>
          \frac{1}{2}(\frac{1}{4}-1)(\frac{1}{2}-2) = x(x-1)(x-2),
        </me>
        or in other words, <m>x^3 - 3x^2 + 2x = \frac{9}{16}.</m>  Here, too, we use technology to determine that there is only one such <m>x</m>, and <m>x \approx 2.21028</m>.  Similar work can be done to find the <m>x</m>-values that correspond to <m>y = \frac{1 \pm \sqrt{5}}{2}</m>.</p></li>
        <li><p>There are four points on the curve where <m>x = 1</m>, which correspond to the <m>y</m>-values that satisfy <m>y(y^2-1)(y-2) = 0</m>: <m>(1,0)</m>, <m>(1,1)</m>, <m>(1,-1)</m>, <m>(1,2)</m>.  We choose the point <m>(1,1)</m> and evaluate <m>\frac{dy}{dx}</m> at this point.  Doing so,
        <me>
          \left.\frac{dy}{dx} \right|_{(1,1)} = \frac{(1-1)(1-2) + 1(1-2) + 1(1-1)}{(1^2-1)(1-2) + 2\cdot 1^2(1-2) + 1(1^2-1)} = \frac{-1}{-2} = \frac{1}{2}.
        </me>
        Thus, the equation of the tangent line to the curve at <m>(1,1)</m> is <m>y - 1 = \frac{1}{2}(x-1)</m>.</p></li>
    </ol>

</p>
</solution>
</activity>
