<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<activity xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="act-4-2-2">
<statement>
<p>Suppose that an object moving along a straight line path has its velocity in feet per second at time <m>t</m> in seconds given by <m>v(t) = \frac{2}{9}(t-3)^2 + 2</m>.

      <ol label="a">
        <li><p>Carefully sketch the region whose exact area will tell you the value of the distance the object traveled on the time interval <m>2 \le t \le 5</m>.</p></li>

        <li><p>Estimate the distance traveled on <m>[2,5]</m> by computing <m>L_4</m>, <m>R_4</m>, and <m>M_4</m>.</p></li>

        <li><p>Does averaging <m>L_4</m> and <m>R_4</m> result in the same value as <m>M_4</m>?  If not, what do you think the average of <m>L_4</m> and <m>R_4</m> measures?</p></li>

        <li><p>For this question, think about an arbitrary function <m>f</m>, rather than the particular function <m>v</m> given above.  If <m>f</m> is positive and increasing on <m>[a,b]</m>, will <m>L_n</m> over-estimate or under-estimate the exact area under <m>f</m> on <m>[a,b]</m>?  Will <m>R_n</m> over- or under-estimate the exact area under <m>f</m> on <m>[a,b]</m>? Explain.</p></li>
      </ol>
      </p>

</statement>
      <hint>
        <p>

        <ol label="a">
          <li><p>Note that <m>y = v(t)</m> is a parabola with vertex <m>(3,2)</m>.</p></li>

          <li><p>Recall the formulas for <m>L_n</m>, <m>R_n</m>, and <m>M_n</m>.</p></li>

          <li><p>Think about what the average of <m>L_1</m> and <m>R_1</m> measures.</p></li>

          <li><p>Consider carefully the role of endpoints in generating <m>L_n</m> and <m>R_n</m>.</p></li>
        </ol>
        </p>
      </hint>

      <answer>
        <p>

        <ol label="a">
          <li><p>
              <image width="50%" source="images/4_2_Act2Soln" />
            </p></li>

          <li><p><m>L_4 = \frac{311}{48} \approx 6.47917</m>,
            <m>R_4 = \frac{335}{48} \approx 6.97917</m>, and
            <m>M_4 = \frac{637}{96} \approx 6.63542</m>.</p></li>

          <li><p>
              <me>
                \frac{L_4 + M_4}{2} = \frac{646}{96} \ne \frac{637}{96} = M_4.
              </me>
              </p></li>

          <li><p><m>L_n</m> is an under-estimate; <m>R_n</m> is an over-estimates.</p></li>
        </ol>
        </p>
      </answer>

      <solution>
        <p>

        <ol label="a">
          <li><p>The region whose exact area tells us the value of the distance the object traveled on the time interval <m>2 \le t \le 5</m> is shown below.
              <image width="50%" source="images/4_2_Act2Soln" />
            </p></li>

          <li><p><m>L_4 = \frac{311}{48} \approx 6.47917</m>,
            <m>R_4 = \frac{335}{48} \approx 6.97917</m>, and
            <m>M_4 = \frac{637}{96} \approx 6.63542</m>.</p></li>

          <li><p>The average of <m>L_4</m> and <m>R_4</m> is
              <me>
                \frac{L_4 + M_4}{2} = \frac{311+335}{96} = \frac{646}{96} \ne \frac{637}{96} = M_4.
              </me>
              This average actually measures what would result from using four trapezoids, rather than rectangles, to estimate the area on each subinterval.  One reason this is so is because the area of a trapezoid is the average of the bases times the width, and the <q>bases</q> are given by the function values at the left and right endpoints.</p></li>

          <li><p>If <m>f</m> is positive and increasing on <m>[a,b]</m>, <m>L_n</m> will under-estimate the exact area under <m>f</m> on <m>[a,b]</m>.  Because <m>f</m> is increasing, its value at the left endpoint of any subinterval will be lower than every other function value in the interval, and thus the rectangle with that height lies exclusively below the curve.  In a similar way, <m>R_n</m> over-estimates the exact area under <m>f</m> on <m>[a,b]</m>.</p></li>
        </ol>
        </p>
      </solution>
    </activity>