<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<activity xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="act-6-1-2">
<statement>
<p>In each of the following problems, our goal is to determine the area of the region described. For each region, (i) determine the intersection points of the curves, (ii) sketch the region whose area is being found, (iii) draw and label a representative slice, and (iv) state the area of the representative slice. Then, state a definite integral whose value is the exact area of the region, and evaluate the integral to find the numeric value of the region's area. <em>Note well:</em> At the step where you draw a representative slice, you need to make a choice about whether to slice vertically or horizontally.

      <ol label="a">
        <li><p>The finite region bounded by <m>x=y^2</m> and <m>x=6-2y^2</m>.</p></li>

        <li><p>The finite region bounded by <m>x=1-y^2</m> and <m>x = 2-2y^2</m>.</p></li>

        <li><p>The area bounded by the <m>x</m>-axis, <m>y=x^2</m>, and <m>y=2-x</m>.</p></li>

        <li><p>The finite regions between the curves <m>x=y^2-2y</m> and <m>y=x</m>.</p></li>
      </ol>
      </p>

</statement>
      <hint>
        <p>

        <ol label="a">
          <li><p>Find where the curves intersect and plot them.</p></li>
          <li><p>Observe that horizontal slices are appropriate, so we will integrate with respect to y.</p></li>
          <li><p>Note that the region is approximately triangular with the <m>x</m>-axis as the base, <m>y=x^2</m> as the left "side", and <m>y = 2-x</m> as the right side.</p></li>
          <li><p></p></li>
          <li><p>Plot the region and observe that horizontal slices are appropriate because of the shape of the region.</p></li>
        </ol>
        </p>
      </hint>

      <answer>
        <p>

        <ol label="a">
          <li><p>
          <m> A = \int_{y=-\sqrt{2}}^{y=\sqrt{2}} (6-2y^2 - y^2) \, dy = 8\sqrt{2} \approx 11.314.</m>    
          </p></li>            
          <li><p>
            <m>
            A = \int_{y=-1}^{y=1} (2-2y^2-(1-y^2)) \, dy = \frac{4}{3}.
            </m>
            </p></li>
            <li><p>
            <m>
                A=\int_{y=0}^{y=4-2\sqrt{3}} \left(\frac{2-y}{2} - \sqrt{y} \right) \, dy = \frac{11}{3}-2\sqrt{3} \approx 0.2026 
            </m>
            </p></li>
            <li><p>
            <m>
                A = \int_{0}^{3} (y - (y^2 - 2y)) \, dy = \frac{9}{2}.
            </m>    
            </p></li>
        </ol>
        </p>
      </answer>

      <solution>
        <p>

        <ol label="a">
          <li><p>The two curves intersect when <m>y^2=6-2y^2</m>, thus when <m>3y^2=6</m>, so at <m>y=\pm \sqrt{2}</m>.  Plotting the region, we see that for <m>y=-\sqrt{2}</m> to <m>y=\sqrt{2}</m>, <m>g(y) = 6-2y^2 \gt y^2 = f(y)</m>, and thus horizontal slices are appropriate for setting up the integral that represents the region's area.  The area is thus given by
          <me> A = \int_{y=-\sqrt{2}}^{y=\sqrt{2}} (6-2y^2 - y^2) \, dy = 8\sqrt{2} \approx 11.314.</me>    
          </p></li>
          <li><p>The two curves intersect when <m>1-y^2=2-2y^2</m>, and therefore <m>3y^2=3</m> so <m>y=\pm 1</m>.  Graphing the region, on <m>-1 \lt y \lt 1</m>, we see that <m>g(y) = 2-2y^2 \ge 1-y^2 = f(y).</m>  Using horizontal slices, it follows that the region's area is given by
            <me>
            A = \int_{y=-1}^{y=1} (2-2y^2-(1-y^2)) \, dy = int_{y=-1}^{y=1} (1-y^2) \, dy = \frac{4}{3}.
            </me>
            </p></li>
            <li><p>
            Standard algebra shows that the two curves meet at <m>(-1+\sqrt{3},4-2\sqrt{3})</m>.  A careful plot of the region shows that the two curves, together with the <m>x</m>-axis, form a roughly triangular region with the <m>x</m>-axis as the base, <m>y=x^2</m> as the left "side", and <m>y = 2-2x</m> as the right side.  Using horizontal slices, and writing each respective equation with <m>x</m> as a function of <m>y</m> (so <m>x=\sqrt{y}</m> and <m>x=\frac{2-y}{2}</m>), we find that the area of this region is
            <me>A=\int_{y=0}^{y=4-2\sqrt{3}} \left(\frac{2-y}{2} - \sqrt{y} \right) \, dy = \frac{11}{3}-2\sqrt{3} \approx 0.2026 </me>
            </p></li>
            <li><p>
            The two curves intersect at <m>(0,0)</m> and <m>(3,3)</m>.  For <m>0 \le y \le 3</m>, we observe that <m>g(y)=y \ge y^2-2y = f(y)</m>, so using horizontal slices and the corresponding definite integral, we find that the region's area is
            <me>
                A = \int_{0}^{3} (y - (y^2 - 2y)) \, dy = \int_{0}^{3} (3y - y^2) \, dy = \frac{9}{2}.
            </me>    
            </p></li>
        </ol>
        </p>
      </solution>
    </activity>
