<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<activity xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="act-1-5-3">
<statement>
<p>
Researchers at a major car company have found a function that relates gasoline consumption to speed for a particular model of car. In particular, they have determined that the consumption <m>C</m>, in {liters per kilometer}, at a given speed <m>s</m>, is given by a function <m>C = f(s)</m>, where <m>s</m> is the car's speed in <em>kilometers per hour</em>.
<ol label="a">
  <li><p>Data provided by the car company tells us that <m>f(80) = 0.015</m>, <m>f(90) = 0.02</m>, and <m>f(100) = 0.027</m>.  Use this information to estimate the instantaneous rate of change of fuel consumption with respect to speed at <m>s = 90</m>.  Be as accurate as possible, use proper notation, and include units on your answer.</p></li>
  <li><p>By writing a complete sentence, interpret the meaning (in the context of fuel consumption) of <q><m>f(80) = 0.015</m>.</q></p></li>
  <li><p>Write at least one complete sentence that interprets the meaning of the value of <m>f'(90)</m> that you estimated in (a).</p></li>
</ol>

</p>
</statement>
<hint>
  <p>

  <ol label="a">
    <li><p>Try a central difference.</p></li>
    <li><p>What is happening when the car is traveling at 80 km/hr?</p></li>
    <li><p>Remember that units on the derivative are <q>units of output per unit of input.</q></p></li>
  </ol>

  </p>
</hint>

<answer>
  <p>

  <ol label="a">
    <li><p><m>f'(90) = 0.0006</m> liters per kilometer per kilometer per hour.</p></li>
    <li><p>At 80 kilometers per hour, the car is using fuel at a rate of 0.015 liters per kilometer.</p></li>
    <li><p>When the car is traveling at 90 kilometers per hour, its rate of fuel consumption per kilometer is increasing at a rate of 0.0006 liters per kilometer per kilometer per hour.</p></li>
  </ol>

  </p>
</answer>

<solution>
  <p>

  <ol label="a">
    <li><p>Using a central difference, we have
    <me>
      f'(90) = \frac{f(100) - f(80}{100-80} = \frac{0.027 - 0.015}{20} = \frac{0.012}{20} = 0.0006
    </me>
    which tells us that <m>f'(90) = 0.0006</m> liters per kilometer per kilometer per hour.</p></li>
    <li><p>When the car is traveling at 80 kilometers per hour, it is using fuel at a rate of 0.015 liters per kilometer.  That is, at the given speed, for each additional kilometer the car travels, it uses an additional 0.015 liters of fuel.</p></li>
    <li><p>To say that <m>f'(90) = 0.0006</m> liters per kilometer per kilometer per hour means that when the car is traveling at 90 kilometers per hour, its rate of fuel consumption per kilometer is increasing at a rate of 0.0006 liters per kilometer per kilometer per hour.  If we increase our speed from 90 to 91 km/hr, we would expect our rate of fuel consumption to rise by 0.0006 liters for each additional kilometer driven.</p></li>
  </ol>

  </p>
</solution>
</activity>
