<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<activity xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="act-1-6-3">
<statement>
<p>
This activity builds on our experience and understanding of how to sketch the graph of <m>f'</m> given the graph of <m>f</m>.
</p>
<p>
In <xref ref="F-1-6-A2">Figure</xref>, given the respective graphs of two different functions <m>f</m>, sketch the corresponding graph of <m>f'</m> on the first axes below, and then sketch <m>f''</m> on the second set of axes. In addition, for each, write several careful sentences in the spirit of those in <xref ref="act-1-6-1">Activity</xref> that connect the behaviors of <m>f</m>, <m>f'</m>, and <m>f''</m>. For instance, write something such as
</p>
<blockquote>

<p>
<m>f'</m> is <fillin /> on the interval <fillin />, which is connected to the fact that <m>f</m> is <fillin /> on the same interval <fillin />, and <m>f''</m> is <fillin /> on the interval as well
</p>

</blockquote>
<p>
but of course with the blanks filled in. Throughout, view the scale of the grid for the graph of <m>f</m> as being <m>1 \times 1</m>, and assume the horizontal scale of the grid for the graph of <m>f'</m> is identical to that for <m>f</m>. If you need to adjust the vertical scale on the axes for the graph of <m>f'</m> or <m>f''</m>, you should label that accordingly.
</p>

<figure xml:id="F-1-6-A2" >
<caption>Two given functions <m>f</m>, with axes provided for plotting <m>f'</m> and <m>f''</m> below.</caption>
<image width="100%" source="images/1_6_Act2" />
</figure>

</statement>
<hint>
<p>
Remember that to plot <m>y = f'(x)</m>, it is helpful to first identify where <m>f'(x) = 0.</m>
</p>
</hint>

<answer>
<p>
<figure xml:id="F-1-6-A2-soln-ans" >
	<caption>Solution to <xref ref="act-1-6-3">Activity</xref>.</caption>
<image width="100%" source="images/1_6_Act2Soln" />
</figure>
</p>
</answer>

<solution>
<p>
The graphs of <m>f'</m> and <m>f''</m> are plotted in <xref ref="F-1-6-A2-soln">Figure</xref>.
<figure xml:id="F-1-6-A2-soln" >
  <caption>Solution to <xref ref="act-1-6-3">Activity</xref>.</caption>
<image width="100%" source="images/1_6_Act2Soln" />
</figure>
</p>
</solution>

</activity>

