<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<activity xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="act-3-2-2">

<p>
Consider the two-parameter family of functions of the form <m>h(x) = a(1-e^{-bx}),</m> where <m>a</m> and <m>b</m> are positive real numbers.
	<ol label="a">
		<li><p>Find the first derivative and the critical numbers of <m>h</m>.  Use these to construct a first derivative sign chart and determine for which values of <m>x</m> the function <m>h</m> is increasing and decreasing.</p></li>
		<li><p>Find the second derivative and build a second derivative sign chart.  For which values of <m>x</m> is a function in this family concave up?  concave down?</p></li>
		<li><p>What is the value of <m>\lim_{x \to \infty} a(1-e^{-bx})</m>? <m>\lim_{x \to -\infty} a(1-e^{-bx})</m>?</p></li>
		<li><p>How does changing the value of <m>b</m> affect the shape of the curve?</p></li>
		<li><p>Without using a graphing utility, sketch the graph of a typical member of this family. Write several sentences to describe the overall behavior of a typical function <m>h</m> and how this behavior depends on <m>a</m> and <m>b</m>.</p></li>
	</ol>

</p>
<hint>
<p>

	<ol label="a">
		<li><p>Expand to write <m>h(x) = a - ae^{-bx}</m> before differentiating.</p></li>
		<li><p>Remember that <m>e^{-bx}</m> is never zero and always positive, regardless of the value of <m>x</m>.</p></li>
		<li><p>Recall that <m>e^{-x} \to 0</m> as <m>x \to \infty</m> and <m>e^{-x} \to \infty</m> as <m>x \to -\infty</m>.</p></li>
		<li><p>Consider how <m>b</m> affects the value of <m>h'(x)</m>.</p></li>
		<li><p>Use your work in (a)-(d).</p></li>
	</ol>

</p>
</hint>

<answer>
<p>

	<ol label="a">
		<li><p><m>h</m> is an always increasing function.</p></li>
		<li><p><m>h</m> is always concave down.</p></li>
		<li><p>
		<m>
		  \lim_{x \to \infty} a(1-e^{-bx}) = a,
		</m>
		and
		<m>
		  \lim_{x \to \infty} a(1-e^{-bx}) = -\infty.
		</m></p></li>
		<li><p>If <m>b</m> is large and <m>x</m> is close to zero, <m>h'(x)</m> is relatively large near <m>x = 0</m>, and the curve's slope will quickly approach zero as <m>x</m> increases.  If <m>b</m> is small, the graph is less steep near <m>x = 0</m> and its slope goes to zero less quickly as <m>x</m> increases.</p></li>
		<li><p>
		    <image width="50%" source="images/3_2_Act2Soln" /></p></li>
	</ol>

</p>
</answer>

<solution>
<p>

	<ol label="a">
		<li><p>Since <m>h(x) = a - ae^{-bx}</m>, we have by the constant multiple and chain rules that
		<me>
		  h'(x) = -ae^{-bx}(-b) = abe^{-bx}.
		</me>
		Since <m>a</m> and <m>b</m> are positive constants and <m>e^{-bx} \gt 0</m> for all <m>x</m>, we see that <m>h'(x)</m> is never zero (nor undefined), and indeed <m>h'(x) \gt 0</m> for all <m>x</m>.  Hence <m>h</m> is an always increasing function.</p></li>
		<li><p>Because <m>h'(x) = abe^{-bx},</m> we have that <m>h''(x) = abe^{-bx}(-b) = -ab^2e^{-bx}</m>.  As with <m>h'</m>, we recognize that <m>a</m>, <m>b^2</m>, and <m>e^{-bx}</m> are always positive, and thus <m>h''(x) = -ab^2e^{-bx} \lt  0</m> for all values of <m>x</m>, making <m>h</m> always concave down.</p></li>
		<li><p>As <m>x \to \infty</m>, <m>e^{-bx} \to 0</m>.  Thus,
		<me>
		  \lim_{x \to \infty} a(1-e^{-bx}) = \lim_{x \to \infty} a - ae^{-bx} = a - 0 = a.
		</me>
		This shows that <m>h</m> has a horizontal asymptote at <m>y = a</m> as we move rightward on its graph.
		  
		  As <m>x \to -\infty</m>, <m>e^{-bx} \to \infty</m>.  Thus,
		<me>
		  \lim_{x \to \infty} a(1-e^{-bx}) = \lim_{x \to \infty} a - ae^{-bx} = -\infty.
		</me></p></li>
		<li><p>Noting that <m>h'(x) = abe^{-bx}</m>, we see that if we consider different values of <m>b</m>, the slope of the graph changes.  If <m>b</m> is large and <m>x</m> is close to zero, <m>h'(x) \approx ab</m> (since <m>e^0 = 1</m>), so <m>h'(x)</m> is relatively large near <m>x = 0</m>.  At the same time, for large <m>b</m>, <m>e^{-bx}</m> approaches zero quickly as <m>x</m> increases, so the curve's slope will quickly approach zero as <m>x</m> increases.  If <m>b</m> is small, the graph is less steep near <m>x = 0</m> and its slope goes to zero less quickly as <m>x</m> increases.</p></li>
		<li><p>Observing that <m>h(0) = 0</m> and <m>\lim_{x \to \infty} h(x) = a</m>, along with the facts that <m>h</m> is always increasing and always concave down, we see that a typical member of this family looks like the following graph.
		    <image width="50%" source="images/3_2_Act2Soln" /></p></li>
	</ol>

</p>
</solution>
</activity>	

