<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<activity xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="act-8-5-3">

      <statement>
        <p><ol label="a.">
          <li>
            <p>Plot the graphs of several of the Taylor polynomials centered at 0 (of order at least 5) for <m>e^x</m> and convince yourself that these Taylor polynomials converge to <m>e^x</m> for every value of <m>x</m>.</p>
          </li>

          <li>
            <p>Draw the graphs of several of the Taylor polynomials centered at 0 (of order at least 6) for <m>\cos(x)</m> and convince yourself that these Taylor polynomials converge to <m>\cos(x)</m> for every value of <m>x</m>. Write the Taylor series centered at 0 for <m>\cos(x)</m>.</p>
          </li>

          <li>
            <p>Draw the graphs of several of the Taylor polynomials centered at 0 for <m>\frac{1}{1-x}</m>. Based on your graphs, for what values of <m>x</m>  do these Taylor polynomials appear to converge to <m>\frac{1}{1-x}</m>? How is this situation different from what we observe with <m>e^x</m> and <m>\cos(x)</m>?  In addition, write the Taylor series centered at 0 for <m>\frac{1}{1-x}</m>.</p>
          </li>
        </ol></p>
      </statement>
      <hint>
        <p><ol label="a.">
          <li>
            <p>Small hints for each of the prompts above.</p>
          </li>
        </ol></p>
      </hint>
      <solution>
        <p><ol label="a.">
          <li>
            <p>The graphs of the 10th (magenta), 20th (blue), and 30th (green) Taylor polynomials centered at 0 for <m>e^x</m> are shown below along with the graph of <m>f(x)</m> in red:</p>
            <sidebyside widths="47%" margins="0%" >
              <image source="images/8_5_exp_graphs" />
            </sidebyside>

            <p>It appears that as we increase the order of the Taylor polynomials, they fit the graph of <m>f</m> better and better over larger intervals. So it looks like the Taylor polynomials converge to <m>e^x</m> for every value of <m>x</m>.</p>
          </li>

          <li>
            <p>The graphs of the 10th (magenta), 20th (blue), and 30th (green) Taylor polynomials centered at 0 for <m>\cos(x)</m> are shown below along with the graph of <m>f(x)</m> in red:</p>
            <sidebyside widths="47%" margins="0%" >
              <image source="images/8_5_cos_graphs" />
            </sidebyside>
            <p>It appears that as we increase the order of the Taylor polynomials, they fit the graph of <m>f</m> better and better over larger intervals. So it looks like the Taylor polynomials converge to <m>\cos(x)</m> for every value of <m>x</m>. Based on the <m>n</m>th order Taylor polynomials we found earlier for <m>\cos(x)</m>, the Taylor series for <m>f(x)</m> centered at 0 is
              <me>
                \sum_{k=0}^{\infty} \frac{x^{2k}}{(2k)!}
              </me>.
            </p>
          </li>

          <li>
            <p>The graphs of the 10th (magenta), 20th (blue), and 30th (green) Taylor polynomials centered at 0 for <m>\frac{1}{1-x}</m> are shown below along with the graph of <m>f(x)</m> in red:</p>
            <sidebyside widths="47%" margins="0%" >
              <image source="images/8_5_1over1minusx_graphs" />
            </sidebyside>
            <p>It appears that as we increase the order of the Taylor polynomials, they only fit the graph of <m>f</m> better and better over the interval <m>(-1,1)</m> and appear to diverge outside that interval. So it looks like the Taylor polynomials converge to <m>\frac{1}{1-x}</m> only on the interval <m>(-1,1)</m>.</p>

            <p>Based on the <m>n</m>th order Taylor polynomials we found earlier for <m>\frac{1}{1-x}</m>, the Taylor series for <m>f(x)</m> centered at 0 is
              <me>
                \sum_{k=0}^{\infty} x^k
              </me>.
            </p>
          </li>
        </ol></p>
      </solution>
    </activity>