<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<!-- Copyright 2012-2018                                                   -->
<!-- Matthew Boelkins                                                      -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- This file is part of Active Calculus.                                 -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document -->
<!-- under the terms of the Creative Commons BY-SA license.  The work      -->
<!-- may be used for free by any party so long as attribution is given to  -->
<!-- the author(s), the work and its derivatives are used in the spirit of -->
<!-- "share and share alike".  All trademarks are the registered marks of  -->
<!-- their respective owners.                                              -->
<!-- **********************************************************************-->

<activity xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="act-6-4-2">
  <statement>
    <p>
      In each of the following problems,
      determine the total work required to accomplish the described task.
      In parts (b) and (c),
      a key step is to find a formula for a function that describes the curve that forms the side boundary of the tank.
    </p>

    <figure xml:id="F-6-4-Act2Trough">
      <caption>A trough with triangular ends, as described in <xref ref="act-6-4-2">Activity</xref>, part (c).</caption>
      <image width="50%" source="images/6_4_Act2Trough" />
    </figure>

    <p>
      <ol label="a.">
        <li>
          <p>
            Consider a vertical cylindrical tank of radius 2 meters and depth 6 meters.
            Suppose the tank is filled with 4 meters of water of mass density 1000 kg/m<m>^3</m>,
            and the top 1 meter of water is pumped over the top of the tank.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li>
          <p>
            Consider a hemispherical tank with a radius of 10 feet.
            Suppose that the tank is full to a depth of 7 feet with water of weight density 62.4 pounds/ft<m>^3</m>,
            and the top 5 feet of water are pumped out of the tank to a tanker truck whose height is 5 feet above the top of the tank.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li>
          <p>
            Consider a trough with triangular ends,
            as pictured in <xref ref="F-6-4-Act2Trough">Figure</xref>,
            where the tank is 10 feet long,
            the top is 5 feet wide,
      and the tank is 4 feet deep.
            Say that the trough is full to within 1 foot of the top with water of weight density 62.4 pounds/ft<m>^3</m>,
            and a pump is used to empty the tank until the water remaining in the tank is 1 foot deep.
          </p>
        </li>
      </ol>
    </p>
  </statement>
  <hint>
    <p>
      <ol label="a.">
        <li>
          <p>
            Note that slices of water at constant depth are all cylinders and all have the same radius.
            Also,
      remember to convert mass to weight when computing force.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li>
          <p>
            Recall that the top half of a circle of radius 10 centered at the origin has equation <m>y = \sqrt{100-x^2}</m>.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li>
          <p>
            The equation of the line that determines the right side of the front face of the tank is <m>y=\frac{5}{2} - \frac{5}{8}x</m>.
            Note that a slice of water at constant depth is a rectangular slab whose width is <m>2y</m>.
          </p>
        </li>
      </ol>
    </p>
  </hint>
  <answer>
    <p>
      <ol label="a.">
        <li>
          <p>
            <me>
              W = \int_{0}^{1} 9.8 \cdot 4000\pi \cdot x \, dx = 19600 \pi \, \text{newton-meters}
            </me>.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li>
          <p>
            <me>
              W = \int_{3}^{8} 62.4 \pi (100-x^2)(x+5) \, dx \approx 673593 \, \text{foot-pounds}
            </me>.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li>
          <p>
            <me>
              W = \int_{1}^{3} 62.4 (50 - \frac{25}{2}x) x \, dx = 5720 \, \text{foot-pounds}
            </me>.
          </p>
        </li>
      </ol>
    </p>
  </answer>
  <solution>
    <p>
      <ol label="a.">
        <li>
          <p>
            A typical slice is a thin cylinder of radius 2 and thickness <m>\Delta x</m>.
            The volume of such a cylinder is
            <m>V_{\text{slice}} = \pi (2)^2 \Delta x</m>,
            and its weight is thus <m>F_{\text{slice}} = 1000 \cdot 9.8 \cdot V_{\text{slice}} = 4000 \pi \Delta x</m>.
            Finally,
            the distance such a slice travels to the top of the tank is <m>d_{\text{slice}} = x</m>.
            If we only pump out the top 1 m of water,
            it follows that the total work is
            <me>
              W = \int_{0}^{1} 9.8 \cdot 4000\pi \cdot x \, dx = 19600 \pi \, \text{newton-meters}
            </me>.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li>
          <p>
            Viewing the tank as a solid of revolution,
            the tank is generated by the function <m>R(x) = \sqrt{100-x^2}</m>,
            and a typical slice has volume <m>V_{\text{slice}} = \pi (\sqrt{100-x^2})^2 \Delta x</m>.
            The force to move such a slice is its weight,
            <m>F_{\text{slice}} = 62.4 \cdot V_{\text{slice}} = 62.4 \pi (100-x^2) \Delta x</m>.
            Each slice has to move <m>x</m> feet to clear the top of the tank,
            and then an additional 5 feet up to the truck,
            so the distance each slice moves is <m>d_{\text{slice}} = x + 5</m>.
            Finally, since the tank is full to a depth of 7 feet,
            and we wish to pump out the top 5 feet,
            <m>x</m> ranges from <m>x=3</m>
            (the top of the water)
            to <m>x=8</m> (the point at which there are 2 feet remaining in the tank).
            Hence, the total work done is
            <me>
              W = \int_{3}^{8} 62.4 \pi (100-x^2)(x+5) \, dx \approx 673593 \, \text{foot-pounds}
            </me>.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li>
          <p>
            The line that bounds the right edge of the triangular face of the tank lying in the first quadrant is <m>y=\frac{5}{2} - \frac{5}{8}x</m>.
            If we take a slice of water that lies at depth <m>x</m>,
            note that the slice is rectangular with thickness <m>\Delta x</m>,
            length 10
            (the tank is 10 feet long),
            and width <m>2(\frac{5}{2} - \frac{5}{8}x)</m>.
            Thus, the volume of a typical slice is
            <me>
              V_{\text{slice}} = 10 \cdot 2(\frac{5}{2} - \frac{5}{8}x) \cdot \Delta x = (50 - \frac{25}{2}x) \Delta x
            </me>,
            and the force that has to be exerted to move such a slice is
            <me>
              F_{\text{slice}} = 62.4 \cdot V_{\text{slice}} = 62.4 (50 - \frac{25}{2}x) \Delta x
            </me>.
            The distance a typical slice moves when pumped to the top of the tank is <m>d_{\text{slice}} = x</m>,
            and since the tank is full to a depth of 3 feet (within 1 foot of the top) and we are going to empty the tank until 1 foot of water remains in it,
            we see that we need to integrate from <m>x=1</m> to <m>x=3</m>, so
            <me>
              W = \int_{1}^{3} 62.4 (50 - \frac{25}{2}x) x \, dx = 5720 \, \text{foot-pounds}
            </me>.
          </p>
        </li>
      </ol>
    </p>
  </solution>
</activity>

