<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<exercises xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="ez-3-5">

  <exercise xml:id="ez-3-5-WW1">
    <webwork source="Library/Rochester/setDerivatives8RelatedRates/csuf_dr_8_1.pg" />
  </exercise> 

  <exercise xml:id="ez-3-5-WW2">
    <webwork source="LLibrary/270/setDerivatives8RelatedRates/s2_8_21.pg" />
  </exercise> 

  <exercise xml:id="ez-3-5-WW3">
    <webwork source="Library/270/setDerivatives8RelatedRates/s2_8_7.pg" />
  </exercise> 

  <exercise xml:id="ez-3-5-WW4">
    <webwork source="Library/Rochester/setDerivatives8RelatedRates/c2s8p3.pg" />
  </exercise> 

<exercise>
<statement>
<p>
A sailboat is sitting at rest near its dock. A rope attached to the bow of the boat is drawn in over a pulley that stands on a post on the end of the dock that is 5 feet higher than the bow. If the rope is being pulled in at a rate of 2 feet per second, how fast is the boat approaching the dock when the length of rope from bow to pulley is 13 feet?
</p>
</statement>
  <answer>
    <p>Exercise Answer</p>
  </answer>
  <solution>
    <p>Exercise Solution</p>
  </solution>
</exercise>

<exercise xml:id="ez-3-5-pool">
<statement>
<p>
A swimming pool is 60 feet long and 25 feet wide. Its depth varies uniformly from 3 feet at the shallow end to 15 feet at the deep end, as shown in the <xref ref="F-3-5-Ez3">Figure</xref>.
</p>
<figure xml:id="F-3-5-Ez3" >
<caption>The swimming pool described in <xref ref="ez-3-5-pool">Exercise</xref>.</caption>
<image width="50%" source="images/3_5_Ez3" />
</figure>
<p>
Suppose the pool has been emptied and is now being filled with water at a rate of 800 cubic feet per minute. At what rate is the depth of water (measured at the deepest point of the pool) increasing when it is 5 feet deep at that end? Over time, describe how the depth of the water will increase: at an increasing rate, at a decreasing rate, or at a constant rate. Explain.
</p>
</statement>
  <answer>
    <p>Exercise Answer</p>
  </answer>
  <solution>
    <p>Exercise Solution</p>
  </solution>
</exercise>

<exercise>
<statement>
<p>
A baseball diamond is a square with sides 90 feet long. Suppose a baseball player is advancing from second to third base at the rate of 24 feet per second, and an umpire is standing on home plate. Let <m>\theta</m> be the angle between the third baseline and the line of sight from the umpire to the runner. How fast is <m>\theta</m> changing when the runner is 30 feet from third base?
</p>
</statement>
  <answer>
    <p>Exercise Answer</p>
  </answer>
  <solution>
    <p>Exercise Solution</p>
  </solution>
</exercise>

<exercise>
<statement>
<p>
Sand is being dumped off a conveyor belt onto a pile in such a way that the pile forms in the shape of a cone whose radius is always equal to its height. Assuming that the sand is being dumped at a rate of 10 cubic feet per minute, how fast is the height of the pile changing when there are 1000 cubic feet on the pile?
</p>
</statement>
  <answer>
    <p>Exercise Answer</p>
  </answer>
  <solution>
    <p>Exercise Solution</p>
  </solution>
</exercise>


</exercises>

