<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<!-- Copyright 2012-2017                                                   -->
<!-- Matthew Boelkins                                                      -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- This file is part of Active Calculus.                                 -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document -->
<!-- under the terms of the Creative Commons BY-NC-SA license.  The work   -->
<!-- may be used for free by any party so long as attribution is given to  -->
<!-- the author(s), the work and its derivatives are used in the spirit of -->
<!-- "share and share alike"; no party may sell this work or any of its    -->
<!-- derivatives for profit.  All trademarks are the registered marks of   -->
<!-- their respective owners.                                              -->
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<exercises xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="ez-3-4">

  <exercise xml:id="ez-3-4-WW1">
    <webwork source="Library/UVA-Stew5e/setUVA-Stew5e-C04S07-Optimization/4-7-08.pg" />
  </exercise>

  <exercise xml:id="ez-3-4-WW2">
    <webwork source="Library/UVA-Stew5e/setUVA-Stew5e-C04S07-Optimization/4-7-12.pg" />
  </exercise>

  <exercise xml:id="ez-3-4-WW3">
    <webwork source="Library/Rochester/setDerivatives10_5Optim/S04.07.Optimization.PTP01.pg" />
  </exercise>

  <exercise xml:id="ez-3-4-WW4">
    <webwork source="Library/Rochester/setDerivatives10_5Optim/S04.07.Optimization.PTP04.pg" />
  </exercise>

  <exercise xml:id="ez-3-4-WW5">
    <webwork source="Library/Rochester/setDerivatives10_5Optim/S04.07.Optimization.PTP05.pg" />
  </exercise>

<exercise>
<statement>
<p>
A rectangular box with a square bottom and closed top is to be made from two materials. The material for the side costs <dollar />1.50 per square foot and the material for the bottom costs <dollar />3.00 per square foot. If you are willing to spend <dollar />15 on the box, what is the largest volume it can contain? Justify your answer completely using calculus.
</p>
</statement>
  <answer>
    <p>Exercise Answer</p>
  </answer>
  <solution>
    <p>Exercise Solution</p>
  </solution>
</exercise>

<exercise>
<statement>
<p>
A farmer wants to start raising cows, horses, goats, and sheep, and desires to have a rectangular pasture for the animals to graze in. However, no two different kinds of animals can graze together. In order to minimize the amount of fencing she will need, she has decided to enclose a large rectangular area and then divide it into four equally sized pens by adding three segments of fence inside the large rectangle that are parallel to two existing sides. She has decided to purchase 7500 ft of fencing. What is the maximum possible area that each of the four pens will enclose?
</p>
</statement>
  <answer>
    <p>Exercise Answer</p>
  </answer>
  <solution>
    <p>Exercise Solution</p>
  </solution>
</exercise>

<exercise>
<statement>
<p>
Two vertical poles of heights 60 ft and 80 ft stand on level ground, with their bases 100 ft apart. A cable that is stretched from the top of one pole to some point on the ground between the poles, and then to the top of the other pole. What is the minimum possible length of cable required? Justify your answer completely using calculus.
</p>
</statement>
  <answer>
    <p>Exercise Answer</p>
  </answer>
  <solution>
    <p>Exercise Solution</p>
  </solution>
</exercise>

<exercise>
<statement>
<p>
A company is designing propane tanks that are cylindrical with hemispherical ends. Assume that the company wants tanks that will hold 1000 cubic feet of gas, and that the ends are more expensive to make, costing <dollar />5 per square foot, while the cylindrical barrel between the ends costs <dollar />2 per square foot. Use calculus to determine the minimum cost to construct such a tank.
</p>
</statement>
  <answer>
    <p>Exercise Answer</p>
  </answer>
  <solution>
    <p>Exercise Solution</p>
  </solution>
</exercise>

</exercises>

