<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<exercises xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="ez-4-1">

  <exercise xml:id="ez-4-1-WW1">
    <webwork source="Library/Michigan/Chap5Sec1/Q01.pg" />
  </exercise>

  <exercise xml:id="ez-4-1-WW2">
    <webwork source="Library/Michigan/Chap5Sec1/Q09.pg" />
  </exercise>

  <exercise xml:id="ez-4-1-WW3">
    <webwork source="Library/Michigan/Chap5Sec1/Q21.pg" />
  </exercise>

  <exercise xml:id="ez-4-1-WW4">
    <webwork source="Library/Michigan/Chap5Sec1/Q25.pg" />
  </exercise>

  <exercise xml:id="ez-4-1-WW5">
    <webwork source="Library/Michigan/Chap5Sec2/Q15.pg" />
  </exercise>

  <exercise xml:id="ez-4-1-WW6">
    <webwork source="Library/Rochester/setIntegrals3Definite/osu_in_3_1a_mo.pg" />
  </exercise>


     <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>Along the eastern shore of Lake Michigan from Lake Macatawa (near Holland) to Grand Haven, there is a bike bath that runs almost directly north-south. For the purposes of this problem, assume the road is completely straight, and that the function <m>s(t)</m> tracks the position of the biker along this path in miles north of Pigeon Lake, which lies roughly halfway between the ends of the bike path.</p>

          <p>Suppose that the biker's velocity function is given by the graph in <xref ref="F-4-1-Ez1">Figure</xref> on the time interval <m>0 \le t \le 4</m> (where <m>t</m> is measured in hours), and that <m>s(0) = 1</m>.</p>

          <figure xml:id="F-4-1-Ez1" >
            <caption>The graph of the biker's velocity, <m>y = v(t)</m>, at left.  At right, axes to plot an approximate sketch of <m>y = s(t)</m>.</caption>
            <image width="100%" source="images/4_1_Ez1" />
          </figure>

          <p><ol label="a.">
            <li><p>Approximately how far north of Pigeon Lake was the cyclist when she was the greatest distance away from Pigeon Lake?  At what time did this occur?</p></li>

            <li><p>What is the cyclist's total change in position on the time interval <m>0 \le t \le 2</m>?  At <m>t = 2</m>, was she north or south of Pigeon Lake?</p></li>

            <li><p>What is the total distance the biker traveled on <m>0 \le t \le 4</m>?  At the end of the ride, how close was she to the point at which she started?</p></li>

            <li><p>Sketch an approximate graph of <m>y = s(t)</m>, the position function of the cyclist, on the interval <m>0 \le t \le 4</m>.  Label at least four important points on the graph of <m>s</m>.</p></li>
          </ol></p>
        </statement>
  <answer>
    <p>Exercise Answer</p>
  </answer>
  <solution>
    <p>Exercise Solution</p>
  </solution>
      </exercise>

      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>A toy rocket is launched vertically from the ground on a day with no wind. The rocket's vertical velocity at time <m>t</m> (in seconds) is given by <m>v(t)= 500-32t</m> feet/sec.

          <ol label="a.">
            <li><p>At what time after the rocket is launched does the rocket's velocity equal zero?  Call this time value <m>a</m>.  What happens to the rocket at <m>t = a</m>?</p></li>

            <li><p>Find the value of the total area enclosed by <m>y = v(t)</m> and the <m>t</m>-axis on the interval <m>0 \le t \le a</m>.  What does this area represent in terms of the physical setting of the problem?</p></li>

            <li><p>Find an antiderivative <m>s</m> of the function <m>v</m>.  That is, find a function <m>s</m> such that <m>s'(t) = v(t)</m>.</p></li>

            <li><p>Compute the value of <m>s(a) - s(0)</m>.  What does this number represent in terms of the physical setting of the problem?</p></li>

            <li><p>Compute <m>s(5) - s(1)</m>.  What does this number tell you about the rocket's flight?</p></li>
          </ol>
          </p>
        </statement>
  <answer>
    <p>Exercise Answer</p>
  </answer>
  <solution>
    <p>Exercise Solution</p>
  </solution>
      </exercise>

      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>An object moving along a horizontal axis has its instantaneous velocity at time <m>t</m> in seconds given by the function <m>v</m> pictured in <xref ref="F-4-1-Ez3">Figure</xref>, where <m>v</m> is measured in feet/sec.</p>

          <figure xml:id="F-4-1-Ez3" >
            <caption>The graph of <m>y = v(t)</m>, the velocity function of a moving object.</caption>
            <image width="50%" source="images/4_1_Ez3" />
          </figure>

          <p>Assume that the curves that make up the parts of the graph of <m>y=v(t)</m> are either portions of straight lines or portions of circles.

          <ol label="a.">
            <li><p>Determine the exact total distance the object traveled on <m>0 \le t \le 2</m>.</p></li>

            <li><p>What is the value and meaning of <m>s(5) - s(2)</m>, where <m>y = s(t)</m> is the position function of the moving object?</p></li>

            <li><p>On which time interval did the object travel the greatest distance: <m>[0,2]</m>, <m>[2,4]</m>, or <m>[5,7]</m>?</p></li>

            <li><p>On which time interval(s) is the position function <m>s</m> increasing?  At which point(s) does <m>s</m> achieve a relative maximum?</p></li>
          </ol>
          </p>
        </statement>
  <answer>
    <p>Exercise Answer</p>
  </answer>
  <solution>
    <p>Exercise Solution</p>
  </solution>
      </exercise>

      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>Filters at a water treatment plant become dirtier over time and thus become less effective; they are replaced every 30 days. During one 30-day period, the rate at which pollution passes through the filters into a nearby lake (in units of particulate matter per day) is measured every 6 days and is given in the following table. The time <m>t</m> is measured in days since the filters were replaced.</p>
        <table>
          <caption>Pollution data for the water filters.</caption>
          <tabular top="minor" bottom="minor">
            <row>
              <cell>Day, <m>t</m></cell>
              <cell>0</cell>
              <cell>6</cell>
              <cell>12</cell>
              <cell>18</cell>
              <cell>24</cell>
              <cell>30</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Rate of pollution in units per day, <m>p(t)</m></cell>
              <cell>7</cell>
              <cell>8</cell>
              <cell>10</cell>
              <cell>13</cell>
              <cell>18</cell>
              <cell>35</cell>
            </row>
          </tabular>
        </table>

          <p><ol label="a.">
            <li><p>Plot the given data on a set of axes with time on the horizontal axis and the rate of pollution on the vertical axis.</p></li>

            <li><p>Explain why the amount of pollution that entered the lake during this 30-day period would be given exactly by the area bounded by <m>y = p(t)</m> and the <m>t</m>-axis on the time interval <m>[0,30]</m>.</p></li>

            <li><p>Estimate the total amount of pollution entering the lake during this 30-day period.  Carefully explain how you determined your estimate.</p></li>
          </ol></p>
        </statement>
  <answer>
    <p>Exercise Answer</p>
  </answer>
  <solution>
    <p>Exercise Solution</p>
  </solution>

      </exercise>


</exercises>

