<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<!-- Copyright 2012-2017                                                   -->
<!-- Matthew Boelkins                                                      -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- This file is part of Active Calculus.                                 -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document -->
<!-- under the terms of the Creative Commons BY-NC-SA license.  The work   -->
<!-- may be used for free by any party so long as attribution is given to  -->
<!-- the author(s), the work and its derivatives are used in the spirit of -->
<!-- "share and share alike"; no party may sell this work or any of its    -->
<!-- derivatives for profit.  All trademarks are the registered marks of   -->
<!-- their respective owners.                                              -->
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<exercises xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="ez-6-4">

  <exercise xml:id="ez-6-4-WW1">
    <title>Work to empty a conical tank</title>
    <webwork source="Library/ma123DB/set1/s6_4_17.pg" />
  </exercise>

  <exercise xml:id="ez-6-4-WW2">
    <title>Work to empty a cylindrical tank</title>
    <webwork source="Library/Michigan/Chap8Sec5/Q15.pg" />
  </exercise>

  <exercise xml:id="ez-6-4-WW3">
    <title>Work to empty a rectangular pool</title>
    <webwork source="Library/Michigan/Chap8Sec5/Q11.pg" />
  </exercise>

  <exercise xml:id="ez-6-4-WW4">
    <title>Work to empty a cylindrical tank to differing heights</title>
    <webwork source="Library/Michigan/5e/Chap8Sec5/Q15.pg" />
  </exercise>

  <exercise xml:id="ez-6-4-WW5">
    <title>Force due to hydrostatic pressure</title>
    <webwork source="Library/Michigan/Chap8Sec5/Q23.pg" />
  </exercise>

<!--  WeBWorK exercise not compatible with PTX  -->
<!--   <exercise xml:id="ez-6-4-WW6">
    <webwork source="Library/Michigan/Chap8Sec5/Q27.pg" />
  </exercise> -->

      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>Consider the curve <m>f(x) = 3 \cos(\frac{x^3}{4})</m> and the portion of its graph that lies in the first quadrant between the <m>y</m>-axis and the first positive value of <m>x</m> for which <m>f(x) = 0</m>. Let <m>R</m> denote the region bounded by this portion of <m>f</m>, the <m>x</m>-axis, and the <m>y</m>-axis. Assume that <m>x</m> and <m>y</m> are each measured in feet.

          <ol label="a.">
            <li><p>Picture the coordinate axes rotated 90 degrees clockwise so that the positive <m>x</m>-axis points straight down, and the positive <m>y</m>-axis points to the right.  Suppose that <m>R</m> is rotated about the <m>x</m> axis to form a solid of revolution, and we consider this solid as a storage tank.  Suppose that the resulting tank is filled to a depth of 1.5 feet with water weighing 62.4 pounds per cubic foot.  Find the amount of work required to lower the water in the tank until it is 0.5 feet deep, by pumping the water to the top of the tank.</p></li>

            <li><p>Again picture the coordinate axes rotated 90 degrees clockwise so that the positive <m>x</m>-axis points straight down, and the positive <m>y</m>-axis points to the right.  Suppose that <m>R</m>, together with its reflection across the <m>x</m>-axis, forms one end of a storage tank that is 10 feet long.  Suppose that the resulting tank is filled completely with water weighing 62.4 pounds per cubic foot.  Find a formula for a function that tells the amount of work required to lower the water by <m>h</m> feet.</p></li>

            <li><p>Suppose that the tank described in (b) is completely filled with water.  Find the total force due to hydrostatic pressure exerted by the water on one end of the tank.</p></li>
          </ol>
          </p>
        </statement>
        <answer>
          <p>Exercise Answer</p>
        </answer>
        <solution>
          <p>Exercise Solution</p>
        </solution>
      </exercise>

      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>A cylindrical tank, buried on its side, has radius 3 feet and length 10 feet. It is filled completely with water whose weight density is 62.4 lbs/ft<m>^3</m>, and the top of the tank is two feet underground.

          <ol label="a.">
            <li><p>Set up, but do not evaluate, an integral expression that represents the amount of work required to empty the top half of the water in the tank to a truck whose tank lies 4.5 feet above ground.</p></li>

            <li><p>With the tank now only half-full, set up, but do not evaluate an integral expression that represents the total force due to hydrostatic pressure against one end of the tank.</p></li>
          </ol>
          </p>
        </statement>

        <answer>
          <p>Exercise Answer</p>
        </answer>
        <solution>
          <p>Exercise Solution</p>
        </solution>

      </exercise>

</exercises>

