<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<exercises xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="ez-6-2">

  <exercise xml:id="ez-6-2-WW1">
    <webwork source="Library/Michigan/Chap8Sec2/Q05.pg" />
  </exercise>

  <exercise xml:id="ez-6-2-WW2">
    <webwork source="Library/Michigan/Chap8Sec2/Q22.pg" />
  </exercise>

  <exercise xml:id="ez-6-2-WW3">
    <webwork source="Library/Michigan/Chap8Sec2/Q23.pg" />
  </exercise>

  <exercise xml:id="ez-6-2-WW4">
    <webwork source="Library/Michigan/Chap8Sec2/Q24.pg" />
  </exercise>

  <exercise xml:id="ez-6-2-WW5">
    <webwork source="Library/Utah/AP_Calculus_I/set11_Applications_of_Integration/p12-8.pg" />
  </exercise>

  <exercise xml:id="ez-6-2-WW7">
    <webwork source="Library/ASU-topics/setCalc2/tracogna5.pg" />
  </exercise>

      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>Consider the curve <m>f(x) = 3 \cos(\frac{x^3}{4})</m> and the portion of its graph that lies in the first quadrant between the <m>y</m>-axis and the first positive value of <m>x</m> for which <m>f(x) = 0</m>. Let <m>R</m> denote the region bounded by this portion of <m>f</m>, the <m>x</m>-axis, and the <m>y</m>-axis.

          <ol label="a.">
            <li><p>Set up a definite integral whose value is the exact arc length of <m>f</m> that lies along the upper boundary of <m>R</m>.  Use technology appropriately to evaluate the integral you find.</p></li>

            <li><p>Set up a definite integral whose value is the exact area of <m>R</m>.  Use technology appropriately to evaluate the integral you find.</p></li>

            <li><p>Suppose that the region <m>R</m> is revolved around the <m>x</m>-axis.  Set up a definite integral whose value is the exact volume of the solid of revolution that is generated.   Use technology appropriately to evaluate the integral you find.</p></li>

            <li><p>Suppose instead that <m>R</m> is revolved around the <m>y</m>-axis.  If possible, set up an integral expression whose value is the exact volume of the solid of revolution and evaluate the integral using appropriate technology.  If not possible, explain why.</p></li>
          </ol>
          </p>
        </statement>
        <answer>
          <p>Exercise Answer</p>
        </answer>
        <solution>
          <p>Exercise Solution</p>
        </solution>
      </exercise>
      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>Consider the curves given by <m>y = \sin(x)</m> and <m>y = \cos(x)</m>. For each of the following problems, you should include a sketch of the region/solid being considered, as well as a labeled representative slice.

          <ol label="a.">
            <li><p>Sketch the region <m>R</m> bounded by the <m>y</m>-axis and the curves <m>y = \sin(x)</m> and <m>y = \cos(x)</m> up to the first positive value of <m>x</m> at which they intersect. What is the exact intersection point of the curves?</p></li>

            <li><p>Set up a definite integral whose value is the exact area of <m>R</m>.</p></li>

            <li><p>Set up a definite integral whose value is the exact volume of the solid  of revolution generated by revolving <m>R</m> about the <m>x</m>-axis.</p></li>

            <li><p>Set up a definite integral whose value is the exact volume of the solid  of revolution generated by revolving <m>R</m> about the <m>y</m>-axis.</p></li>

            <li><p>Set up a definite integral whose value is the exact volume of the solid  of revolution generated by revolving <m>R</m> about the line <m>y = 2</m>.</p></li>

            <li><p>Set up a definite integral whose value is the exact volume of the solid  of revolution generated by revolving <m>R</m> about the <m>x = -1</m>.</p></li>
          </ol>
          </p>
        </statement>
        <answer>
          <p>Exercise Answer</p>
        </answer>
        <solution>
          <p>Exercise Solution</p>
        </solution>
      </exercise>
      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>Consider the finite region <m>R</m> that is bounded by the curves <m>y = 1+\frac{1}{2}(x-2)^2</m>, <m>y=\frac{1}{2}x^2</m>, and <m>x = 0</m>.

          <ol label="a.">
            <li><p>Determine a definite integral whose value is the area of the region enclosed by the two curves.</p></li>

            <li><p>Find an expression involving one or more definite integrals whose value is the volume of the solid of revolution generated by revolving the region <m>R</m> about the line <m>y = -1</m>.</p></li>

            <li><p>Determine an expression involving one or more definite integrals whose value is the volume of the solid of revolution generated by revolving the region <m>R</m> about the <m>y</m>-axis.</p></li>

            <li><p>Find an expression involving one or more definite integrals whose value is the perimeter of the region <m>R</m>.</p></li>
          </ol>
          </p>
        </statement>
        <answer>
          <p>Exercise Answer</p>
        </answer>
        <solution>
          <p>Exercise Solution</p>
        </solution>
      </exercise>

</exercises>

