<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<!-- Copyright 2012-2017                                                   -->
<!-- Matthew Boelkins                                                      -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- This file is part of Active Calculus.                                 -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document -->
<!-- under the terms of the Creative Commons BY-NC-SA license.  The work   -->
<!-- may be used for free by any party so long as attribution is given to  -->
<!-- the author(s), the work and its derivatives are used in the spirit of -->
<!-- "share and share alike"; no party may sell this work or any of its    -->
<!-- derivatives for profit.  All trademarks are the registered marks of   -->
<!-- their respective owners.                                              -->
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<exercises xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="ez-7-3">


  <exercise xml:id="ez-7-3-WW1">
    <title>A few steps of Euler's method</title>
    <webwork source="Library/Michigan/Chap11Sec3/Q01.pg" />
  </exercise>

  <exercise xml:id="ez-7-3-WW2">
    <title>Using Euler's method for a solution of <m>y'=4y</m></title>
    <webwork source="Library/Michigan/Chap11Sec3/Q03.pg" />
  </exercise>

  <exercise xml:id="ez-7-3-WW3">
    <title>Using Euler's method with different time steps</title>
    <webwork source="Library/Michigan/Chap11Sec3/Q09.pg" />
  </exercise>


      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>Newton's Law of Cooling says that the rate at which an
          object, such as a cup of coffee, cools is proportional to the
          difference in the object's temperature and room temperature. If
          <m>T(t)</m> is the object's temperature and <m>T_r</m> is room temperature,
          this law is expressed at
          <me>
            \frac{dT}{dt} = -k(T-T_r),
          </me>
          where <m>k</m> is a constant of proportionality. In this problem,
          temperature is
          measured in degrees Fahrenheit and time in minutes.

          <ol label="a.">
            <li><p>Two calculus students, Alice and Bob, enter a 70<m>^\circ</m>
                    classroom at the same time.  Each has a cup of coffee that is
                    100<m>^\circ</m>.  The differential equation for Alice has a constant
                    of proportionality <m>k=0.5</m>, while the constant of proportionality
                    for Bob is <m>k=0.1</m>.

                    What is the initial rate of change for Alice's coffee?
                    What is the initial rate of change for Bob's coffee?</p></li>

            <li><p>What feature of Alice's and Bob's cups of coffee could explain
                    this difference?</p></li>

            <li><p>As the heating unit turns on and off in the room, the
                    temperature in the room is
                <me>
                  T_r=70+10\sin t.
                </me>
                Implement Euler's
                    method with a step size of <m>\Delta t = 0.1</m> to approximate the
                    temperature of Alice's coffee over the time interval <m>0\leq t\leq
                    50</m>.  This will most easily be performed using a spreadsheet such
                    as <em>Excel</em>.  Graph the temperature of her coffee and room
                    temperature over this interval.</p></li>

            <li><p>In the same way, implement Euler's method to approximate the
                    temperature of Bob's
                    coffee over the same time interval.  Graph the temperature of his
                    coffee and room temperature over the interval.</p></li>

            <li><p>Explain the similarities and differences that you see in the
                    behavior of Alice's and Bob's cups of coffee.</p></li>
          </ol>
          </p>
        </statement>
  <answer>
    <p>Exercise Answer</p>
  </answer>
  <solution>
    <p>Exercise Solution</p>
  </solution>
      </exercise>

      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>We have seen that the error in approximating the solution to
            an initial value problem is proportional to <m>\Delta t</m>. That is,
            if <m>E_{\Delta t}</m> is the Euler's method approximation to the
            solution to an initial value problem at <m>\overline{t}</m>, then
            <me>
              y(\overline{t})-E_{\Delta t} \approx K\Delta t
            </me>
            for some constant of proportionality <m>K</m>.</p>

          <p>In this problem, we will see how to use this fact to improve our
          estimates, using an idea called <em>accelerated convergence</em>.

          <ol label="a.">
            <li><p>We will create a new approximation by assuming the error is
                    <em>exactly</em> proportional to <m>\Delta t</m>, according to the formula
                <me>
                  y(\overline{t})-E_{\Delta t} =K\Delta t.
                </me>
                Using our earlier results from the initial value problem <m>dy/dt = y</m> and
                    <m>y(0)=1</m> with <m>\Delta t = 0.2</m> and <m>\Delta t = 0.1</m>, we have
                <md>
                  <mrow>y(1) - 2.4883 =\mathstrut \amp  0.2K</mrow>
                  <mrow>y(1) - 2.5937 =\mathstrut \amp  0.1K.</mrow>
                </md>
                This is a system of two linear equations in the unknowns <m>y(1)</m>
                    and <m>K</m>.  Solve this system to find a new approximation for
                    <m>y(1)</m>.  (You may remember that the exact value is <m>y(1) = e =
                    2.71828\ldots.</m>)</p></li>

            <li><p>Use the other data, <m>E_{0.05} = 2.6533</m> and <m>E_{0.025} = 2.6851</m>
                    to do similar work as in (a) to obtain another approximation.  Which gives the better
                    approximation?  Why do you think this is?</p></li>

            <li><p>Let's now study the initial value problem
                <me>
                  \frac{dy}{dt} = t-y, \ y(0) = 0.
                </me>
                Approximate <m>y(0.3)</m> by applying Euler's method to find
                    approximations <m>E_{0.1}</m> and <m>E_{0.05}</m>.  Now use the idea of
                    accelerated convergence to obtain a better approximation.  (For the sake of comparison, you want to  note that the actual value is <m>y(0.3) =
                    0.0408</m>.)</p></li>
          </ol>
          </p>
        </statement>
  <answer>
    <p>Exercise Answer</p>
  </answer>
  <solution>
    <p>Exercise Solution</p>
  </solution>
      </exercise>

      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>In this problem, we'll modify Euler's method to obtain better
            approximations to solutions of initial value problems. This
            method is called the <em>Improved Euler's method.</em></p>

          <p>In Euler's method, we walk across an interval of width <m>\Delta t</m>
            using the slope obtained from the differential equation at the
            left endpoint of the interval. Of course, the slope of the
            solution will most likely change over this interval. We can
            improve our approximation by trying to incorporate the change in
            the slope over the interval.</p>

          <p>Let's again consider the initial value problem <m>dy/dt = y</m> and
            <m>y(0) = 1</m>, which we will approximate using steps of width <m>\Delta
                t = 0.2</m>. Our first interval is therefore <m>0\leq t \leq 0.2</m>. At
            <m>t=0</m>, the differential equation tells us that the slope is 1, and
            the approximation we obtain from Euler's method is that
            <m>y(0.2)\approx y_1= 1+ 1(0.2)= 1.2</m>.</p>

          <p>This gives us some idea for how the slope has changed over the
            interval <m>0\leq t\leq 0.2</m>. We know the slope at <m>t=0</m> is 1,
            while the slope at <m>t=0.2</m> is 1.2, trusting in the Euler's method
            approximation. We will therefore refine our estimate of the
            initial slope to be the average of these two slopes; that is, we
            will estimate the slope to be <m>(1+1.2)/2 = 1.1</m>. This gives the
            new approximation <m>y(1) = y_1 = 1 + 1.1(0.2) = 1.22</m>.</p>

          <p>The first few steps look like what is found in <xref ref="T-7-3-ez-3">Table</xref>.</p>
          <table xml:id="T-7-3-ez-3">
            <caption>The first several steps of the improved Euler's method</caption>
          <tabular top="minor">
            <row bottom="minor">
              <cell><m>t_i</m></cell>
              <cell><m>y_i</m></cell>
              <cell>Slope at <m>(t_{i+1},y_{i+1})</m></cell>
              <cell>Average slope</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell><m>0.0</m></cell>
              <cell><m>1.0000</m></cell>
              <cell><m>1.2000</m></cell>
              <cell><m>1.1000</m></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell><m>0.2</m></cell>
              <cell><m>1.2200</m></cell>
              <cell><m>1.4640</m></cell>
              <cell><m>1.3420</m></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell><m>0.4</m></cell>
              <cell><m>1.4884</m></cell>
              <cell><m>1.7861</m></cell>
              <cell><m>1.6372</m></cell>
            </row>
            <row bottom="minor">
              <cell><m>\vdots</m></cell>
              <cell><m>\vdots</m></cell>
              <cell><m>\vdots</m></cell>
              <cell><m>\vdots</m></cell>
            </row>
          </tabular>
        </table>

          <p><ol label="a.">
            <li><p>Continue with this method to obtain an approximation for <m>y(1) =
                    e</m>.</p></li>

            <li><p>Repeat this method with <m>\Delta t = 0.1</m> to obtain a better
                    approximation for <m>y(1)</m>.</p></li>

            <li><p>We saw that the error in Euler's method is proportional to
                    <m>\Delta t</m>.  Using your results from parts (a) and (b), what power
                    of <m>\Delta t</m> appears to be proportional to the error in the
                    Improved Euler's Method?</p></li>
          </ol></p>
        </statement>

  <answer>
    <p>Exercise Answer</p>
  </answer>
  <solution>
    <p>Exercise Solution</p>
  </solution>

      </exercise>

</exercises>

