<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<exercises xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="ez-7-2">

  <exercise xml:id="ez-7-2-WW1">
    <webwork source="Library/UMN/calculusStewartET/s_9_2_1.pg" />
  </exercise>

  <exercise xml:id="ez-7-2-WW2">
    <webwork source="Library/Michigan/Chap11Sec2/Q01.pg" />
  </exercise>

  <exercise xml:id="ez-7-2-WW3">
    <webwork source="Library/Rochester/setDiffEQ2DirectionFields/ur_de_2_3.pg" />
  </exercise>

<!--  WeBWorK exercise not compatible with PTX  -->
<!--   <exercise xml:id="ez-7-2-WW4">
    <webwork source="Library/Rochester/setDiffEQ6AutonomousStability/ur_de_6_1.pg" />
  </exercise> -->

  <exercise xml:id="ez-7-2-WW5">
    <webwork source="Library/Rochester/setDiffEQ6AutonomousStability/ur_de_6_4.pg" />
  </exercise>

<exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>Consider the differential equation
          <me>
            \frac{dy}{dt} = t-y.
          </me>
          </p>

          <sidebyside widths="47% 47%" margins="0%">

          <p><ol label="a.">
            <li><p>Sketch a slope field on the plot below:
              </p></li>

            <li><p>Sketch the solutions whose initial values are <m>y(0)= -4, -3, \ldots, 4</m>.</p></li>

            <li><p>What do your sketches suggest is the solution whose initial
                    value is <m>y(0) = -1</m>?  Verify that this is indeed the solution to
                    this initial value problem.</p></li>

            <li><p>By considering the differential equation and the graphs you
                    have sketched, what is the relationship between <m>t</m> and <m>y</m> at a
                    point where a solution has a local minimum?</p></li>
          </ol></p>
          <image source="images/7_2_ex_1" />
        </sidebyside>

        </statement>
  <answer>
    <p>Exercise Answer</p>
  </answer>
  <solution>
    <p>Exercise Solution</p>
  </solution>
      </exercise>

      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>Consider the situation from problem 2 of <xref ref="sec-7-1-diff-eq-intro">Section</xref>: Suppose
            that the population of a particular species is
            described by the function <m>P(t)</m>, where <m>P</m> is expressed in
            millions. Suppose further that the population's rate of change is
            governed by the differential equation
            <me>
              \frac{dP}{dt} = f(P)
            </me>
            where <m>f(P)</m> is the function graphed below.</p>
            <sidebyside width="47%" margin="0%">
              <image source="images/7_1_threshold" />
            </sidebyside>

          <p><ol label="a.">
            <li><p>Sketch a slope field for this differential equation.  You do
                    not have enough information to determine the actual slopes, but
                    you should have enough information to determine where slopes are positive, negative, zero, large, or small, and hence determine the qualitative
                    behavior of solutions.</p></li>

            <li><p>Sketch some solutions to this differential equation when the
                    initial population <m>P(0) \gt 0</m>.</p></li>

            <li><p>Identify any equilibrium solutions to the differential equation and classify them as stable
                    or unstable.</p></li>

            <li><p>If <m>P(0) \gt 1</m>, what is the eventual fate of the species?</p></li>

            <li><p>if <m>P(0) \lt 1</m>, what is the eventual fate of the species?</p></li>

            <li><p>Remember that we referred to this model for population growth
                    as <q>growth with a threshold.</q>  Explain why this characterization makes sense by considering
                    solutions whose inital value is close to 1.</p></li>
          </ol></p>
        </statement>
  <answer>
    <p>Exercise Answer</p>
  </answer>
  <solution>
    <p>Exercise Solution</p>
  </solution>
      </exercise>

      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>The population of a species of fish in a lake is <m>P(t)</m> where
          <m>P</m> is measured in thousands of fish and <m>t</m> is measured in
          months. The growth of the population is described by the
          differential equation
          <me>
            \frac{dP}{dt} = f(P) = P(6-P).
          </me>

          <ol label="a.">
            <li><p>Sketch a graph of <m>f(P) = P(6-P)</m> and use it to determine the
                    equilibrium solutions and whether they are stable or unstable.
                    Write a complete sentence that describes the long-term behavior of
                    the fish population.</p></li>

            <li><p>Suppose now that the owners of the lake allow fishers to
                    remove 1000 fish from the lake every month (remember that <m>P(t)</m>
                    is measured in <em>thousands</em> of fish).  Modify the differential
                    equation to take this into account.  Sketch the new graph of
                    <m>dP/dt</m> versus <m>P</m>.  Determine the new equilibrium solutions and
                    decide whether they are stable or unstable.</p></li>

            <li><p>Given the situation in part (b), give a description of
                    the long-term behavior of the fish population.</p></li>

            <li><p>Suppose that fishermen remove <m>h</m> thousand fish per month.
                    How is the differential equation modified?</p></li>

            <li><p>What is the largest
                    number of fish that can be removed per month without eliminating the fish
                    population?  If fish are removed at this maximum rate, what is the
                    eventual population of fish?</p></li>
          </ol>
          </p>
        </statement>
  <answer>
    <p>Exercise Answer</p>
  </answer>
  <solution>
    <p>Exercise Solution</p>
  </solution>

      </exercise>

      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>Let <m>y(t)</m> be the number of thousands of mice that live on a
          farm; assume time <m>t</m> is measured in years.<fn>This problem is based on an ecological analysis
              presented in a research paper by C.S. Hollings:  The Components of
              Predation as Revealed by a Study of Small Mammal Predation of the
              European Pine Sawfly, <em>Canadian Entomology</em> <em>91</em>: 283-320.</fn>

          <ol label="a.">
            <li><p>The population of the mice grows at a yearly rate that is twenty times
                    the number of mice.  Express this as a differential equation.</p></li>

            <li><p>At some point, the farmer brings <m>C</m> cats to the farm.  The
                    number of mice that the cats can eat in a year is
                <me>
                  M(y) = C\frac{y}{2+y}
                </me>
                thousand mice per year.  Explain how this modifies the
                    differential equation that you found in part a).</p></li>

            <li><p>Sketch a graph of the function <m>M(y)</m> for a single cat <m>C=1</m> and
                    explain its features by looking, for instance, at the behavior of
                    <m>M(y)</m> when <m>y</m> is small and when <m>y</m> is large.</p></li>

            <li><p>Suppose that <m>C=1</m>.  Find the equilibrium solutions and
                    determine whether they are stable or unstable.  Use this to
                    explain the long-term behavior of the mice population depending on
                    the initial population of the mice.</p></li>

            <li><p>Suppose that <m>C=60</m>.  Find the equilibrium solutions and
                    determine whether they are stable or unstable.  Use this to
                    explain the long-term behavior of the mice population depending on
                    the initial population of the mice.</p></li>

            <li><p>What is the smallest number of cats you would need to keep the mice population from growing arbitrarily large?</p></li>
          </ol>
          </p>
        </statement>
      </exercise>


</exercises>

