<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<!-- Copyright 2012-2017                                                   -->
<!-- Matthew Boelkins                                                      -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- This file is part of Active Calculus.                                 -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document -->
<!-- under the terms of the Creative Commons BY-NC-SA license.  The work   -->
<!-- may be used for free by any party so long as attribution is given to  -->
<!-- the author(s), the work and its derivatives are used in the spirit of -->
<!-- "share and share alike"; no party may sell this work or any of its    -->
<!-- derivatives for profit.  All trademarks are the registered marks of   -->
<!-- their respective owners.                                              -->
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<exercises xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="ez-7-5">

  <exercise xml:id="ez-7-5-WW1">
    <title>Mixing problem</title>
    <webwork source="Library/Rochester/setDiffEQ5ModelingWith1stOrder/ns7_4_31a.pg" />
  </exercise>

  <exercise xml:id="ez-7-5-WW2">
    <title>Mixing problem</title>
    <webwork source="Library/Rochester/setDiffEQ5ModelingWith1stOrder/ns7_4_31c.pg" />
  </exercise>

  <exercise xml:id="ez-7-5-WW3">
    <title>Population growth problem</title>
    <webwork source="Library/Rochester/setDiffEQ5ModelingWith1stOrder/ns7_5_3.pg" />
  </exercise>

  <exercise xml:id="ez-7-5-WW4">
    <title>Radioactive decay problem</title>
    <webwork source="Library/Rochester/setDiffEQ5ModelingWith1stOrder/ns7_5_10.pg" />
  </exercise>

  <exercise xml:id="ez-7-5-WW5">
    <title>Investment problem</title>
    <webwork source="Library/Rochester/setDiffEQ5ModelingWith1stOrder/ur_de_5_1.pg" />
  </exercise>

      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>Congratulations, you just won the lottery! In one option
          presented to you, you will be paid one million dollars a year for
          the next 25 years. You can deposit this money in an account that
          will earn 5<percent /> each year.

          <ol label="a.">
            <li><p>Set up a differential equation that describes the rate of
                    change in the amount of money in the account.  Two factors cause
                    the amount to grow<mdash />first, you are depositing one millon dollars
                    per year and second, you are earning 5<percent /> interest.</p></li>

            <li><p>If there is no amount of money in the account when you open
                    it, how much money will you have in the account after 25 years?</p></li>

            <li><p>The second option presented to you is to take a lump sum of 10
                    million dollars, which you will deposit into a similar account.  How
                    much money will you have in that account after 25 years?</p></li>

            <li><p>Do you prefer the first or second option?  Explain your thinking.</p></li>

            <li><p>At what time does the amount of money in the account under the
                    first option overtake the amount of money in the account under the
                    second option?</p></li>
          </ol>
          </p>
        </statement>
  <answer>
    <p>Exercise Answer</p>
  </answer>
  <solution>
    <p>Exercise Solution</p>
  </solution>
      </exercise>

      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>When a skydiver jumps from a plane, gravity causes
          her downward velocity to increase at the rate of <m>g\approx 9.8</m>
          meters per second squared. At the same time, wind resistance
          causes her velocity to decrease at a rate proportional to the
          velocity.

          <ol label="a.">
            <li><p>Using <m>k</m> to represent the constant of proportionality,
                      write a differential equation that describes the rate of change
                      of the skydiver's velocity.</p></li>

            <li><p>Find any equilibrium solutions and decide whether they are
                        stable or unstable.  Your result should depend on <m>k</m>.</p></li>

            <li><p>Suppose that the initial velocity is zero.  Find the
                        velocity <m>v(t)</m>.</p></li>

            <li><p>A typical terminal velocity for a skydiver falling face
                        down is 54 meters per second.  What is the value of <m>k</m> for
                        this skydiver?</p></li>

            <li><p>How long does it take to reach 50<percent /> of the terminal
                        velocity?</p></li>
          </ol>
          </p>
        </statement>
  <answer>
    <p>Exercise Answer</p>
  </answer>
  <solution>
    <p>Exercise Solution</p>
  </solution>
      </exercise>

      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>During the first few years of life, the rate at which a baby
          gains weight is proportional to the reciprocal of its weight.

          <ol label="a.">
            <li><p>Express this fact as a differential equation.</p></li>

            <li><p>Suppose that a baby weighs 8 pounds at birth and 9 pounds
                        one month later.  How much will he weigh at one year?</p></li>

            <li><p>Do you think this is a realistic model for a long time?</p></li>
          </ol>
          </p>
        </statement>
  <answer>
    <p>Exercise Answer</p>
  </answer>
  <solution>
    <p>Exercise Solution</p>
  </solution>
      </exercise>

      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>Suppose that you have a water tank that holds 100 gallons of water.
            A briny solution, which contains 20 grams of salt per gallon, enters
            the tank at the rate of 3 gallons per minute.</p>

          <p>At the same time, the solution is well mixed, and water is pumped
          out of the tank at the rate of 3 gallons per minute.

          <ol label="a.">
            <li><p>Since 3 gallons enters the tank every minute and 3 gallons
                  leaves every minute, what can you conclude about the volume of water
                  in the tank.</p></li>

            <li><p>How many grams of salt enters the tank every minute?</p></li>

            <li><p>Suppose that <m>S(t)</m> denotes the number of grams of salt in the
                  tank in minute <m>t</m>.  How many grams are there in each gallon in
                  minute <m>t</m>?</p></li>

            <li><p>Since water leaves the tank at 3 gallons per minute, how many
                  grams of salt leave the tank each minute?</p></li>

            <li><p>Write a differential equation that expresses the total rate of
                  change of <m>S</m>.</p></li>

            <li><p>Identify any equilibrium solutions and determine whether they
                  are stable or unstable.</p></li>

            <li><p>Suppose that there is initially no salt in the tank.  Find the
                  amount of salt <m>S(t)</m> in minute <m>t</m>.</p></li>

            <li><p>What happens to <m>S(t)</m> after a very long time?  Explain how you
                  could have predicted this only knowing how much salt there is in
                  each gallon of the
                  briny solution that enters the tank.</p></li>
          </ol>
          </p>
        </statement>
  <answer>
    <p>Exercise Answer</p>
  </answer>
  <solution>
    <p>Exercise Solution</p>
  </solution>
      </exercise>

</exercises>

