<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<exercises xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="ez-8-4">

  <exercise xml:id="ez-8-4-WW1">
    <webwork source="Library/Michigan/Chap9Sec4/Q57.pg" />
  </exercise>

<!-- Uses EV2 and incompatible with PTX -->
<!--   <exercise xml:id="ez-8-4-WW2">
    <webwork source="Library/Rochester/setSeries3Convergent/ur_sr_3_1.pg" />
  </exercise> -->

  <exercise xml:id="ez-8-4-WW3">
    <webwork source="Library/Rochester/setSeries3Convergent/ur_sr_3_8.pg" />
  </exercise>

  <exercise xml:id="ez-8-4-WW4">
    <webwork source="Library/Rochester/setSeries3Convergent/ur_sr_3_9.pg" />
  </exercise>

  <exercise xml:id="ez-8-4-WW5">
    <webwork source="Library/Rochester/setSeries3Convergent/ur_sr_3_10.pg" />
  </exercise>

      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>Conditionally convergent series converge very slowly. As an example, consider the famous formula<fn>We will derive this formula in upcoming work.</fn>
            <men xml:id="Ex-8-4-pi" >
              \frac{\pi}{4} = 1 - \frac{1}{3} + \frac{1}{5} - \frac{1}{7} + \cdots = \sum_{k=0}^{\infty} (-1)^{k} \frac{1}{2k+1}
            </men>.
          </p>

          <p>In theory, the partial sums of this series could be used to approximate <m>\pi</m>.</p>

          <p><ol label="a.">
            <li>
              <p>Show that the series in <xref ref="Ex-8-4-pi" /> converges conditionally.</p>
            </li>

            <li>
              <p>Let <m>S_n</m> be the <m>n</m>th partial sum of the series in <xref ref="Ex-8-4-pi" />. Calculate the error in approximating <m>\frac{\pi}{4}</m> with <m>S_{100}</m> and explain why this is not a very good approximation.</p>
            </li>

            <li>
              <p>Determine the number of terms it would take in the series <xref ref="Ex-8-4-pi" /> to approximate <m>\frac{\pi}{4}</m> to 10 decimal places. (The fact that it takes such a large number of terms to obtain even a modest degree of accuracy is why we say that conditionally convergent series converge very slowly.)
              </p>
            </li>
          </ol>
          </p>
        </statement>
        <solution>
          <p>In this case we have
            <me>
              |S_n - \sum_{k=0}^{\infty} (-1)^{k} \frac{1}{2k+1}| \lt  a_{n+1} = \frac{1}{2n+1}
            </me>.
          </p>

          <p>To have <m>a_{n+1} \lt  10^{-10}</m> would require
            <md>
              <mrow>\frac{1}{2n+1} \amp \lt  10^{-10}</mrow>
              <mrow>2n+1 \amp \gt 10^{10}</mrow>
              <mrow>n \amp \gt \frac{10^{10}-1}{2}</mrow>
              <mrow>n \amp \gt 4{,}999{,}999{,}999.5</mrow>
            </md>.
          </p>
        </solution>
      </exercise>

      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>We have shown that if <m>\sum (-1)^{k+1} a_k</m> is a convergent alternating series, then the sum <m>S</m> of the series lies between any two consecutive partial sums <m>S_n</m>. This suggests that the average <m>\frac{S_n+S_{n+1}}{2}</m>
          is a better approximation to <m>S</m> than is <m>S_n</m>.

          <ol label="a.">
            <li>
              <p>Show that <m>\frac{S_n+S_{n+1}}{2} = S_n + \frac{1}{2}(-1)^{n+2} a_{n+1}</m>.</p>
            </li>

            <li>
              <p>Use this revised approximation in (a) with <m>n = 20</m> to approximate <m>\ln(2)</m> given that
                <me>
                  \ln(2) = \sum_{k=1}^{\infty} (-1)^{k+1} \frac{1}{k}
                </me>.
              Compare this to the approximation using just <m>S_{20}</m>. For your convenience, <m>S_{20} = \frac{155685007}{232792560}</m>.</p>
            </li>
          </ol></p>
        </statement>
        <solution>
          <p><ol label="a.">
            <li>
              <p>Since <m>S_{n+1} = S_n + (-1)^{n+2}a_{n+1}</m> we have
                <md>
                  <mrow>\frac{S_n+S_{n+1}}{2} \amp = \frac{S_n+S_{n} + (-1)^{n+2}a_{n+1}}{2}</mrow>
                  <mrow>\amp = \frac{2S_{n} + (-1)^{n+2}a_{n+1}}{2}</mrow>
                  <mrow>\amp = S_n + \frac{1}{2}(-1)^{n+2}a_{n+1}</mrow>
                </md>.
              </p>
            </li>
          </ol></p>
        </solution>
      </exercise>

      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>In this exercise, we examine one of the conditions of the Alternating Series Test. Consider the alternating series
            <me>
              1 - 1 + \frac{1}{2} - \frac{1}{4} + \frac{1}{3} - \frac{1}{9} + \frac{1}{4} - \frac{1}{16} + \cdots
            </me>,
          where the terms are selected alternately from the sequences <m>\left\{\frac{1}{n}\right\}</m> and <m>\left\{-\frac{1}{n^2}\right\}</m>.</p>

          <p><ol label="a.">
            <li>
              <p>Explain why the <m>n</m>th term of the given series converges to 0 as <m>n</m> goes to infinity.</p>
            </li>

            <li>
              <p>Rewrite the given series by grouping terms in the following manner:
                <me>
                  (1 - 1) + \left(\frac{1}{2} - \frac{1}{4}\right) + \left(\frac{1}{3} - \frac{1}{9}\right) + \left(\frac{1}{4} - \frac{1}{16}\right) + \cdots
                </me>.
              Use this regrouping to determine if the series converges or diverges.</p>
            </li>

            <li>
              <p>Explain why the condition that the sequence <m>\{a_n\}</m> <em>decreases</em> to a limit of 0 is included in the Alternating Series Test.</p>
            </li>
          </ol></p>
        </statement>
        <solution>
          <p><ol label="a.">
            <li>
              <p>Since both sequences <m>\left\{\frac{1}{n}\right\}</m> and <m>\left\{-\frac{1}{n^2}\right\}</m> converge to 0 as <m>n</m> goes to infinity, we see that the sequence of <m>n</m>th terms of our series converge to 0 as <m>n</m> goes to infinity.</p>
            </li>
            <li>
              <p>Notice that <m>\frac{1}{k} - \frac{1}{k^2} = \frac{k-1}{k^2}</m>. So our series can be rewritten as
                <me>
                  \sum_{k=1}^{\infty} \frac{k-1}{k^2}
                </me>.
              </p>

              <p>Since
                <me>
                  \lim_{k \to \infty} \frac{ \frac{k-1}{k^2} }{ \frac{1}{k} } = \lim_{k \to \infty} \frac{k^2-k}{k^2} = 1
                </me>,
              the Limit Comparison Test shows that the series <m>\sum_{k=1}^{\infty} \frac{k-1}{k^2}</m> behaves like the harmonic series <m>\sum_{k=1}^{\infty} \frac{1}{k}</m>. Since the harmonic series diverges, it follows that the series <m>\sum_{k=1}^{\infty} \frac{k-1}{k^2}</m> diverges as well.</p>
            </li>
          </ol></p>
        </solution>
      </exercise>
      
      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>Conditionally convergent series exhibit interesting and unexpected behavior. In this exercise we examine the conditionally convergent alternating harmonic series <m>\sum_{k=1}^{\infty} \frac{(-1)^{k+1}}{k}</m> and discover that addition is not commutative for conditionally convergent series. We will also encounter Riemann's Theorem concerning rearrangements of conditionally convergent series. Before we begin, we remind ourselves that
            <me>
              \sum_{k=1}^{\infty} \frac{(-1)^{k+1}}{k} = \ln(2)
            </me>,
          a fact which will be verified in a later section.</p>

          <p><ol label="a.">
            <li>
              <p>First we make a quick analysis of the positive and negative terms of the alternating harmonic series.</p>

              <p><ol label="i">
                <li>
                  <p>Show that the series <m>\sum_{k=1}^{\infty} \frac{1}{2k}</m> diverges.</p>
                </li>

                <li>
                  <p>Show that the series <m>\sum_{k=1}^{\infty} \frac{1}{2k+1}</m> diverges.</p>
                </li>

                <li>
                  <p>Based on the results of the previous parts of this exercise, what can we say about the sums <m>\sum_{k=C}^{\infty} \frac{1}{2k}</m> and <m>\sum_{k=C}^{\infty} \frac{1}{2k+1}</m> for any positive integer <m>C</m>? Be specific in your explanation.</p>
                </li>
              </ol></p>
            </li>

            <li>
              <p>Recall addition of real numbers is commutative; that is
                <me>
                  a + b = b + a
                </me>
              for any real numbers <m>a</m> and <m>b</m>. This property is valid for any sum of finitely many terms, but does this property extend when we add infinitely many terms together?</p>

              <p>The answer is no, and something even more odd happens. Riemann's Theorem (after the nineteenth-century mathematician Georg Friedrich Bernhard Riemann) states that a conditionally convergent series can be rearranged to converge to <em>any</em> prescribed sum. More specifically, this means that if we choose any real number <m>S</m>, we can rearrange the terms of the alternating harmonic series <m>\sum_{k=1}^{\infty} \frac{(-1)^{k+1}}{k}</m> so that the sum is <m>S</m>. To understand how Riemann's Theorem works, let's assume for the moment that the number <m>S</m> we want our rearrangement to converge to is positive. Our job is to find a way to order the sum of terms of the alternating harmonic series to converge to <m>S</m>.</p>

              <p><ol label="i">
                <li>
                  <p>Explain how we know that, regardless of the value of <m>S</m>, we can find a partial sum <m>P_1</m>
                    <me>
                      P_1 = \sum_{k=1}^{n_1} \frac{1}{2k+1} = 1 + \frac{1}{3} + \frac{1}{5} + \cdots + \frac{1}{2n_1+1}
                    </me>
                  of the positive terms of the alternating harmonic series that equals or exceeds <m>S</m>. Let
                    <me>
                      S_1 = P_1
                    </me>.
                  </p>
                </li>

                <li>
                  <p>Explain how we know that, regardless of the value of <m>S_1</m>, we can find a partial sum <m>N_1</m>
                    <me>
                      N_1 = -\sum_{k=1}^{m_1} \frac{1}{2k} = -\frac{1}{2} - \frac{1}{4} - \frac{1}{6} - \cdots - \frac{1}{2m_1}
                    </me>
                  so that
                    <me>
                      S_2 = S_1 + N_1 \leq S
                    </me>.
                  </p>
                </li>

                <li>
                  <p>Explain how we know that, regardless of the value of <m>S_2</m>, we can find a partial sum <m>P_2</m>
                    <me>
                      P_2 = \sum_{k=n_1+1}^{n_2} \frac{1}{2k+1} = \frac{1}{2(n_1+1)+1} + \frac{1}{2(n_1+2)+1} + \cdots + \frac{1}{2n_2+1}
                    </me>
                  of the remaining positive terms of the alternating harmonic series so that
                    <me>
                      S_3 = S_2 + P_2 \geq S
                    </me>.
                  </p>
                </li>

                <li>
                  <p>Explain how we know that, regardless of the value of <m>S_3</m>, we can find a partial sum
                    <me>
                      N_2 = -\sum_{k=m_1+1}^{m_2} \frac{1}{2k} = -\frac{1}{2(m_1+1)} - \frac{1}{2(m_1+2)} - \cdots - \frac{1}{2m_2}
                    </me>
                  of the remaining negative terms of the alternating harmonic series so that
                    <me>
                      S_4 = S_3 + N_2 \leq S
                    </me>.
                  </p>
                </li>

                <li>
                  <p>Explain why we can continue this process indefinitely and find a sequence <m>\{S_n\}</m> whose terms are partial sums of a rearrangement of the terms in the alternating harmonic series so that <m>\lim_{n \to \infty} S_n = S</m>.</p>
                </li>
              </ol></p>
            </li>
          </ol></p>
        </statement>
      </exercise>
    </exercises>
