<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<exploration xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="PA-5-3">

      <p>In <xref ref="sec-2-5-chain">Section</xref>, we learned the Chain Rule and how it can be applied to find the derivative of a composite function. In particular, if <m>u</m> is a differentiable function of <m>x</m>, and <m>f</m> is a differentiable function of <m>u(x)</m>, then
        <me>
          \frac{d}{dx} \left[ f(u(x))  \right] = f'(u(x)) \cdot u'(x).
        </me>
      </p>

      <p>In words, we say that the derivative of a composite function <m>c(x) = f(u(x))</m>, where <m>f</m> is considered the <q>outer</q> function and <m>u</m> the <q>inner</q> function, is <q>the derivative of the outer function, evaluated at the inner function, times the derivative of the inner function.</q></p>

      <p><ol label="a">
      <li><p>For each of the following functions, use the Chain Rule to find the function's derivative.  Be sure to label each derivative by name (e.g., the derivative of <m>g(x)</m> should be labeled <m>g'(x)</m>).</p>

      <p><ol label="i">
        <li>
          <p><m>g(x) = e^{3x}</m></p></li>

        <li>
          <p><m>h(x) = \sin(5x+1)</m></p></li>

        <li>
          <p><m>p(x) = \arctan(2x)</m></p></li>

        <li>
          <p><m>q(x) = (2-7x)^4</m></p></li>

        <li>
          <p><m>r(x) = 3^{4-11x}</m></p></li>
      </ol></p>
      </li>

      <li><p>For each of the following functions, use your work in (a) to help you determine the general antiderivative<fn>Recall that the general antiderivative of a function includes <q><m>+C</m></q> to reflect the entire family of functions that share the same derivative.</fn> of the function.  Label each antiderivative by name (e.g., the antiderivative of <m>m</m> should be called <m>M</m>).  In addition, check your work by computing the derivative of each proposed antiderivative.

      <ol label="i">
        <li>
          <p><m>m(x) = e^{3x}</m></p></li>

        <li>
          <p><m>n(x) = \cos(5x+1)</m></p></li>

        <li>
          <p><m>s(x) = \frac{1}{1+4x^2}</m></p></li>

        <li>
          <p><m>v(x) = (2-7x)^3</m></p></li>

        <li>
          <p><m>w(x) = 3^{4-11x}</m></p></li>
      </ol>
      </p></li>

      <li><p>Based on your experience in parts (a) and (b), conjecture an antiderivative for each of the following functions.  Test your conjectures by computing the derivative of each proposed antiderivative.

      <ol label="i">
        <li>
          <p><m>a(x) = \cos(\pi x)</m></p></li>

        <li>
          <p><m>b(x) = (4x+7)^{11}</m></p></li>

        <li>
          <p><m>c(x) = xe^{x^2}</m></p></li>
      </ol>
      </p></li>
      </ol></p>
    </exploration>

