<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<exploration xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="PA-7-5">

      <p>Any time that the rate of change of a quantity is related to the amount of a quantity, a differential equation naturally arises. In the following two problems, we see two such scenarios; for each, we want to develop a differential equation whose solution is the quantity of interest.

      <ol label="a">
        <li><p>Suppose you have a bank account in which money grows at an
          annual rate of 3<percent />.

        <ul>
          <li>
            <title>(i)</title>
            <p>If you have <dollar />10,000 in the account, at what rate is your
                    money growing?</p></li>

          <li>
            <title>(ii)</title>
            <p>Suppose that you are also withdrawing money from the account
                    at <dollar />1,000 per year.  What is the rate of change in the amount
                    of money in the account?  What are the units on this rate of change?</p></li>
        </ul>
        </p></li>

        <li><p>Suppose that a water tank holds 100 gallons and that a salty
          solution, which contains 20 grams of salt in every gallon, enters the
          tank at 2 gallons per minute.

        <ul>
          <li>
            <title>(i)</title>
            <p>How much salt enters the tank each minute?</p></li>

          <li>
            <title>(ii)</title>
            <p>Suppose that initially there are 300 grams of salt in the tank.  How
                    much salt is in each gallon at this point in time?</p></li>

          <li>
            <title>(iii)</title>
            <p>Finally, suppose that evenly mixed solution is pumped out of the tank at the
                    rate of 2 gallons per minute.  How much salt leaves the tank
                    each minute?</p></li>

          <li>
            <title>(iv)</title>
            <p>What is the total rate of change in the amount of salt in
                    the tank?</p></li>
        </ul>
        </p></li>
      </ol>
      </p>
    </exploration>


