<webwork-tex seed="123567890">
<statement>
			%mbx script removed problem header
 The table below shows the number of calories used per minute as a function of an individual's body weight for three sports:
\leavevmode\\\relax 
\begin{center} 

\par\smallskip\begin{center}\begin{tabular}{|c|c|c|c|c|c|c|} \hline

Activity &amp;100 lb &amp;120 lb &amp;150 lb &amp;170 lb &amp;200 lb &amp;220 lb \\ \hline 

Walking &amp;2.7 &amp;3.2 &amp;4 &amp;4.6 &amp;5.4 &amp;5.9 \\ \hline 

Bicycling &amp;5.4 &amp;6.5 &amp;8.1 &amp;9.2 &amp;10.8 &amp;11.9 \\ \hline 

Swimming &amp;5.8 &amp;6.9 &amp;8.7 &amp;9.8 &amp;11.6 &amp;12.7 \\ \hline 


\end {tabular}\end{center}\par\smallskip

\end{center} 
\par 
a) Determine the number of calories that a 200 lb person uses in one half-hour of walking . \mbox{\parbox[t]{10ex}{\hrulefill}}  calories

\par 
b) Who uses more calories, a 170 lb person swimming for one hour, or a
         220 lb person bicycling for a half-hour?

\begin{itemize}
\item{A. The 170 lb person swimming for one hour}
\item{B. The 220 lb person bicycling for a half-hour}
\item{C. They both use the same amount of calories}

\end{itemize}

\par 
c) Does the number of calories of a person walking increase or decrease as weight increases?

\begin{itemize}
\item{A. Increase}
\item{B. Decrease}

\end{itemize}


\par \par {\bf Solution: }\par 
{\bf  SOLUTION }
\par 
a) The table gives the amount of calories used per minute.  So in order to find the total number of calories used in a half-hour, use the table to find the number of calories used by a 200 lb who walks for a half-hour, and then multiply by 30 minutes.  Using the table we know a 200 lb person walking uses 5.4 calories per minute; therefore,
\[\mbox{ Total calories used } = ( 5.4 )(30) = 162 \mbox{ calories}\]
\leavevmode\\\relax 
b) Using the same calculation as in (a), it follows that a 170 lb person swimming uses 9.8 calories per minute.  Thus a 170 lb person swimming for one hour uses a total of \(( 9.8 )(60) = 588\) calories.  On the other hand, a 220 lb person bicycling uses 11.9 calories per minute.  Thus a 220 lb person bicycling for a half-hour uses a total of \(( 11.9 )(30) = 357\) calories.  By comparing the values 588 and 357 we obtain the answer.
\par 
c) Since the values in the table are increasing along the row of values corresponding to a person who is walking, the number of calories of a person walking increases as weight increases.

\par 
</webwork-tex>