<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<!-- Copyright 2012-2018                                                   -->
<!-- Matthew Boelkins                                                      -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- This file is part of Active Calculus.                                 -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document -->
<!-- under the terms of the Creative Commons BY-SA license.  The work      -->
<!-- may be used for free by any party so long as attribution is given to  -->
<!-- the author(s), the work and its derivatives are used in the spirit of -->
<!-- "share and share alike".  All trademarks are the registered marks of  -->
<!-- their respective owners.                                              -->
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<section permid="sec-elem-rules" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec-2-1-elem-rules">
  <title>Elementary derivative rules</title>
  <objectives permid="ob">
    <ul permid="ul">
      <li permid="l_j">
        <p permid="p">
          What are alternate notations for the derivative?
        </p>
      </li>

      <li permid="l_s">
        <p permid="p">
          How can we use the algebraic structure of a function <m>f(x)</m> to compute a formula for <m>f'(x)</m>?
        </p>
      </li>

      <li permid="l_b">
        <p permid="p">
          What is the derivative of a power function of the form <m>f(x) = x^n</m>?
          What is the derivative of an exponential function of form <m>f(x) = a^x</m>?
        </p>
      </li>

      <li permid="l_k">
        <p permid="p">
          If we know the derivative of <m>y = f(x)</m>,
          what is the derivative of <m>y = k f(x)</m>,
          where <m>k</m> is a constant?
        </p>
      </li>

      <li permid="l_t">
        <p permid="p">
          If we know the derivatives of <m>y = f(x)</m> and <m>y = g(x)</m>,
          how do we compute the derivative of <m>y = f(x) + g(x)</m>?
        </p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </objectives>

  <introduction>
    <p permid="p1">
      In <xref ref="C-1">Chapter</xref>,
      we developed the concept of the derivative of a function.
      We now know that the derivative <m>f'</m> of a function <m>f</m> measures the instantaneous rate of change of <m>f</m> with respect to <m>x</m>.
      The derivative also tells us the slope of the tangent line to <m>y=f(x)</m> at any given value of <m>x</m>.
      So far, we have focused on interpreting the derivative graphically or,
      in the context of a physical setting,
      as a meaningful rate of change.
      To calculate the value of the derivative at a specific point,
      we have relied on the limit definition of the derivative,
      <me>
        f'(x) = \lim_{h \to 0} \frac{f(x+h)-f(x)}{h}
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p permid="p2">
      In this chapter,
      we investigate how the limit definition of the derivative      
      leads to interesting patterns and rules that enable us to find a formula for <m>f'(x)</m> quickly,
      <em>without</em>
      using the limit definition directly.
      For example,
      we would like to apply shortcuts to differentiate a function such as <m>g(x) = 4x^7 - \sin(x) + 3e^x</m>
    </p>

    <xi:include href="./previews/PA-2-1.xml" />
  </introduction>

  <subsection permid="ssec-some-key-notation">
    <title>Some Key Notation</title>
    <p permid="p1">
      In addition to our usual <m>f'</m> notation,
      there are other ways to denote the derivative of a function,
      as well as the instruction to take the derivative.
      If we are thinking about the relationship between <m>y</m> and <m>x</m>,
      we sometimes denote the derivative of <m>y</m> with respect to <m>x</m> by the symbol
      <me>
        \frac{dy}{dx}
      </me>
      which we read <q>dee-y dee-x.</q>
      For example, if <m>y = x^2</m>,
      we'll write that the derivative is <m>\frac{dy}{dx} = 2x</m>.
      This notation comes from the fact that the derivative is related to the slope of a line,
      and slope is measured by <m>\frac{\Delta y}{\Delta x}</m>.
      Note that while we read <m>\frac{\Delta y}{\Delta x}</m> as
      <q>change in <m>y</m> over change in <m>x</m>,</q> we view
      <m>\frac{dy}{dx}</m> as a single symbol,
      not a quotient of two quantities.
    </p>

    <p permid="p2">
      We use a variant of this notation as the instruction to take the derivative.
      In particular,
      <me>
        \frac{d}{dx}\left[ \Box \right]
      </me>
      means <q>take the derivative of the quantity in <m>\Box</m> with respect to <m>x</m>.</q>
      For example, we may write <m>\frac{d}{dx}[x^2] = 2x</m>.
    </p>

    <p permid="p3">
      It is important to note that the independent variable can be different from <m>x</m>.
      If we have <m>f(z) = z^2</m>,
      we then write <m>f'(z) = 2z</m>.
      Similarly, if <m>y = t^2</m>,
      we say <m>\frac{dy}{dt} = 2t</m>.
      And it is also true that <m>\frac{d}{dq}[q^2] = 2q</m>.
      This notation may also be used for second derivatives:
      <m>f''(z) = \frac{d}{dz}\left[\frac{df}{dz}\right] = \frac{d^2 f}{dz^2}</m>.
    </p>

    <p permid="p4">
      In what follows,
      we'll build a repertoire of functions for which we can quickly compute the derivative.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection permid="ssec-constant-power-exponential-functions">
    <title>Constant, Power, and Exponential Functions</title>
    <p permid="p1">
      So far, we know the derivative formula for two important classes of functions:
      constant functions and power functions.
      If
      <m>f(x) = c</m> is a constant function,
      its graph is a horizontal line with slope zero at every point.
      Thus, <m>\frac{d}{dx}[c] = 0</m>.
      We summarize this with the following rule.
    </p>

    <assemblage permid="const-fxns" xml:id="const-fxns">
      <title>Constant Functions</title>
      <p permid="p">
            <idx><h>derivative</h><h>constant function</h></idx>
        For any real number <m>c</m>,
        if <m>f(x) = c</m>, then <m>f'(x) = 0</m>.
      </p>
    </assemblage>

    <example permid="ex1">
      <statement>
        <p permid="p">
          If <m>f(x) = 7</m>, then <m>f'(x) = 0</m>.
          Similarly, <m>\frac{d}{dx} [\sqrt{3}] = 0</m>.
        </p>
      </statement>
    </example>

    <p permid="p2">
      In your work in <xref ref="PA-2-1">Preview Activity</xref>,
      you conjectured that for any positive integer <m>n</m>,
      if <m>f(x) = x^n</m>, then <m>f'(x) = nx^{n-1}</m>.
      This rule can be formally proved for any positive integer <m>n</m>,
      and also for any nonzero real number
      (positive or negative).
    </p>

    <assemblage permid="power-fxns" xml:id="power-fxns">
      <title>Power Functions</title>
      <p permid="p">
            <idx><h>derivative</h><h>power function</h></idx>
        For any nonzero real number <m>n</m>,
        if <m>f(x) = x^n</m>, then <m>f'(x) = nx^{n-1}</m>.
      </p>
    </assemblage>

    <example permid="ex2">
      <statement>
        <p permid="p">
          Using the rule for power functions,
          we can compute the following derivatives.
          If <m>g(z) = z^{-3}</m>, then <m>g'(z) = -3z^{-4}</m>.
          Similarly, if <m>h(t) = t^{7/5}</m>,
          then <m>\frac{dh}{dt} = \frac{7}{5}t^{2/5}</m>,
          and <m>\frac{d}{dq} [q^{\pi}] = \pi q^{\pi - 1}</m>.
        </p>
      </statement>
    </example>

    <p permid="p3">
      It will be instructive to have a derivative formula for one more type of basic function.
      For now, we simply state this rule without explanation or justification;
      we will explore why this rule is true in one of the exercises.
      And we will encounter graphical reasoning for why the rule is plausible in <xref ref="PA-2-2">Preview Activity</xref>.
    </p>

    <assemblage permid="exp-fxns" xml:id="exp-fxns">
      <title>Exponential Functions</title>
      <p permid="p">
            <idx><h>derivative</h><h>exponential function</h></idx>
        For any positive real number <m>a</m>,
        if <m>f(x) = a^x</m>, then <m>f'(x) = a^x \ln(a)</m>.
      </p>
    </assemblage>

    <example permid="ex3">
      <statement>
        <p permid="p">
          If <m>f(x) = 2^x</m>,
          then <m>f'(x) = 2^x \ln(2)</m>.
          Similarly, for <m>p(t) = 10^t</m>,
          <m>p'(t) = 10^t \ln(10)</m>.
          It is especially important to note that when <m>a = e</m>,
          where <m>e</m> is the base of the natural logarithm function,
          we have that
          <me>
            \frac{d}{dx} [e^x] = e^x \ln(e) = e^x
          </me>
          since <m>\ln(e) = 1</m>.
          This is an extremely important property of the function <m>e^x</m>:
          its derivative function is itself!
        </p>
      </statement>
    </example>

    <p permid="p4">
      Note carefully the distinction between power functions and exponential functions:
      in power functions, the variable is in the base, as in <m>x^2</m>,
      while in exponential functions,
      the variable is in the power, as in <m>2^x</m>.
      As we can see from the rules,
      this makes a big difference in the form of the derivative.
    </p>

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-2-1-1.xml" />
  </subsection>

  <subsection permid="ssec-constant-multiples-sums-functions">
    <title>Constant Multiples and Sums of Functions</title>
    <p permid="p1">
      Next we will learn how to compute the derivative of a function constructed as an algebraic combination of basic functions.
      For instance,
      we'd like to be able to take the derivative of a polynomial function such as
      <me>
        p(t) = 3t^5 - 7t^4 + t^2 - 9
      </me>,
      which is a sum of constant multiples of powers of <m>t</m>.
      To that end, we develop two new rules:
      the Constant Multiple Rule and the Sum Rule.
    </p>

    <p permid="p2">
      How is the derivative of <m>y = kf(x)</m> related to the derivative of <m>y = f(x)</m>?
      Recall that when we multiply a function by a constant <m>k</m>,
      we vertically stretch the graph by a factor of <m>|k|</m>
      (and reflect the graph across <m>y = 0</m> if <m>k \lt 0</m>).
      This vertical stretch affects the slope of the graph,
      so the slope of the function
      <m>y = kf(x)</m> is <m>k</m> times as steep as the slope of <m>y = f(x)</m>.
      Thus, when we multiply a function by a factor of <m>k</m>,
      we change the value of its derivative by a factor of <m>k</m> as well.<fn>
      The Constant Multiple Rule can be formally proved as a consequence of properties of limits,
      using the limit definition of the derivative.
      </fn>,
    </p>

    <assemblage permid="const-mult-rule" xml:id="const-mult-rule">
      <title>The Constant Multiple Rule</title>
      <p permid="p">
            <idx><h>constant multiple rule</h></idx>
        For any real number <m>k</m>,
        if <m>f(x)</m> is a differentiable function with derivative <m>f'(x)</m>,
        then <m>\frac{d}{dx}[k f(x)] = k f'(x)</m>.
      </p>
    </assemblage>

    <p permid="p3">
      In words, this rule says that <q>the derivative of a constant times a function is the constant times the derivative of the function.</q>
    </p>

    <example permid="ex1">
      <statement>
        <p permid="p">
          If <m>g(t) = 3 \cdot 5^t</m>,
          we have <m>g'(t) = 3 \cdot 5^t \ln(5)</m>.
          Similarly, <m>\frac{d}{dz} [5z^{-2}] = 5 (-2z^{-3})</m>.
        </p>
      </statement>
    </example>

    <p permid="p4">
      Next we examine a sum of two functions.
      If we have <m>y = f(x)</m> and <m>y = g(x)</m>,
      we can compute a new function
      <m>y = (f+g)(x)</m> by adding the outputs of the two functions:
      <m>(f+g)(x) = f(x) + g(x)</m>.
      Not only is the value of the new function the sum of the values of the two known functions,
      but the slope of the new function is the sum of the slopes of the known functions.
      Therefore<fn>
      Like the Constant Multiple Rule,
      the Sum Rule can be formally proved as a consequence of properties of limits,
      using the limit definition of the derivative.
      </fn>,
      we arrive at the following Sum Rule for derivatives:
    </p>

    <assemblage permid="sum-rule" xml:id="sum-rule">
      <title>The Sum Rule</title>
      <p permid="p">
            <idx><h>sum rule</h></idx>
        If <m>f(x)</m> and <m>g(x)</m> are differentiable functions with derivatives <m>f'(x)</m> and <m>g'(x)</m> respectively,
        then <m>\frac{d}{dx}[f(x) + g(x)] = f'(x) + g'(x)</m>.
      </p>
    </assemblage>

    <p permid="p5">
      In words, the Sum Rule tells us that
      <q>the derivative of a sum is the sum of the derivatives.</q>
      It also tells us that a sum of two differentiable functions is also differentiable.
      Furthermore, because we can view the difference function
      <m>y = (f-g)(x) = f(x) - g(x)</m> as <m>y = f(x) + (-1 \cdot g(x))</m>,
      the Sum Rule and Constant Multiple Rules together tell us that <m>\frac{d}{dx}[f(x) + (-1 \cdot g(x))] = f'(x) - g'(x)</m>,
      or that <q>the derivative of a difference is the difference of the derivatives.</q>
      We can now compute derivatives of sums and differences of elementary functions.
    </p>

    <example permid="ex2">
      <statement>
        <p permid="p">
          Using the sum rule, <m>\frac{d}{dw} (2^w + w^2) = 2^w \ln(2) + 2w</m>.
          Using both the sum and constant multiple rules,
          if <m>h(q) = 3q^6 - 4q^{-3}</m>,
          then <m>h'(q) = 3 (6q^5) - 4(-3q^{-4}) = 18q^5 + 12q^{-4}</m>.
        </p>
      </statement>
    </example>

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-2-1-2.xml" />

    <p permid="p6">
      In the same way that we have shortcut rules to help us find derivatives,
      we introduce some language that is simpler and shorter.
      Often, rather than say <q>take the derivative of <m>f</m>,</q>
      we'll instead say simply <q>differentiate <m>f</m>.</q>
      Similarly,
      if the derivative exists at a point,
      we say <q><m>f</m> is differentiable at that point,</q>
      or that <m>f</m> can be differentiated.
    </p>

    <p permid="p7">
      As we work with the algebraic structure of functions,
      it is important to develop a big picture view of what we are doing.
      Here, we make several general observations based on the rules we have so far.

      <ul permid="ul">
        <li permid="l_j">
          The derivative of any polynomial function will be another polynomial function,
          and that the degree of the derivative is one less than the degree of the original function.
          For instance, if <m>p(t) = 7t^5 - 4t^3 + 8t</m>,
          <m>p</m> is a degree 5 polynomial, and its derivative,
          <m>p'(t) = 35t^4 - 12t^2 + 8</m>, is a degree 4 polynomial.
        </li>

        <li permid="l_s">
          The derivative of any exponential function is another exponential function:
          for example, if <m>g(z) = 7 \cdot 2^z</m>,
          then <m>g'(z) = 7 \cdot 2^z \ln(2)</m>,
          which is also exponential.
        </li>

        <li permid="l_b">
          We should not lose sight of the fact that all of the meaning of the derivative that we developed in <xref ref="C-1">Chapter</xref> still holds.
          The derivative measures the instantaneous rate of change of the original function,
          as well as the slope of the tangent line at any selected point on the curve.
        </li>
      </ul>
    </p>

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-2-1-3.xml" />
  </subsection>

  <subsection permid="ssec-summary">
    <title>Summary</title>
    <p permid="p">
      <ul permid="ul">
        <li permid="l_j">
          <p permid="p">
            Given a differentiable function <m>y = f(x)</m>,
            we can express the derivative of <m>f</m> in several different notations:
            <m>f'(x)</m>, <m>\frac{df}{dx}</m>,
            <m>\frac{dy}{dx}</m>, and <m>\frac{d}{dx}[f(x)]</m>.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="l_s">
          <p permid="p">
            The limit definition of the derivative leads to patterns among certain families of functions that enable us to compute derivative formulas without resorting directly to the limit definition.
            For example,
            if <m>f</m> is a power function of the form <m>f(x) = x^n</m>,
            then <m>f'(x) = nx^{n-1}</m> for any real number <m>n</m> other than 0.
            This is called the Rule for Power Functions.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="l_b">
          <p permid="p">
            We have stated a rule for derivatives of exponential functions in the same spirit as the rule for power functions:
            for any positive real number <m>a</m>,
            if <m>f(x) = a^x</m>, then <m>f'(x) = a^x \ln(a)</m>.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="l_k">
          <p permid="p">
            If we are given a constant multiple of a function whose derivative we know,
            or a sum of functions whose derivatives we know,
            the Constant Multiple and Sum Rules make it straightforward to compute the derivative of the overall function.
            More formally,
            if <m>f(x)</m> and <m>g(x)</m> are differentiable with derivatives <m>f'(x)</m> and <m>g'(x)</m> and <m>a</m> and <m>b</m> are constants, then
            <me>
              \frac{d}{dx} \left[af(x) + bg(x)\right] = af'(x) + bg'(x)
            </me>.
          </p>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <xi:include href="./exercises/ez-2-1.xml" />
</section>

