<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<!-- Copyright 2012-2018                                                   -->
<!-- Matthew Boelkins                                                      -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- This file is part of Active Calculus.                                 -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document -->
<!-- under the terms of the Creative Commons BY-SA license.  The work      -->
<!-- may be used for free by any party so long as attribution is given to  -->
<!-- the author(s), the work and its derivatives are used in the spirit of -->
<!-- "share and share alike".  All trademarks are the registered marks of  -->
<!-- their respective owners.                                              -->
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<section permid="sec-vel" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec-1-1-vel">
  <title>How do we measure velocity?</title>
  <objectives permid="ob">
    <ul permid="ul">
      <li permid="l_j">
        <p permid="p">
          How is the average velocity of a moving object connected to the values of its position function?
        </p>
      </li>

      <li permid="l_s">
        <p permid="p">
          How do we interpret the average velocity of an object geometrically on the graph of its position function?
        </p>
      </li>

      <li permid="l_b">
        <p permid="p">
          How is the notion of instantaneous velocity connected to average velocity?
        </p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </objectives>

  <introduction>
    <p permid="p1">
      Calculus can be viewed broadly as the study of change.
      A natural and important question to ask about any changing quantity is
      <q>how fast is the quantity changing?</q>
    </p>

    <p permid="p2">
      We begin with a simple problem:
      a ball is tossed straight up in the air.
      How the ball is moving?
      Questions like this one are central to our study of differential calculus.
    </p>

    <xi:include href="./previews/PA-1-1.xml" />
  </introduction>

  <subsection permid="ssec-position-average-velocity">
    <title>Position and average velocity</title>
    <p permid="p1">
      Any moving object has a <em>position</em>
          <idx><h>position</h></idx>
      that can be considered a function of <em>time</em>.
      When the motion is along a straight line,
      the position is given by a single variable,
      which we denote by <m>s(t)</m>.
      For example,
      <m>s(t)</m> might give the mile marker of a car traveling on a straight highway at time <m>t</m> in hours.
      Similarly, the function <m>s</m> described in <xref ref="PA-1-1">Preview Activity</xref> is a position function,
      where position is measured vertically relative to the ground.
    </p>

    <p permid="p2">
      On any time interval, a moving object also has an
      <em>average velocity</em>.
      For example,
      to compute a car's average velocity we divide the number of miles traveled by the time elapsed,
      which gives the velocity in <em>miles per hour</em>.
      Similarly, the value of <m>AV_{[0.5,1]}</m> in <xref ref="PA-1-1">Preview Activity</xref>
      gave the average velocity of the ball on the time interval <m>[0.5,1]</m>,
      measured in feet per second.
    </p>

    <p permid="p3">
      In general, we make the following definition:
    </p>

    <assemblage permid="asm-average-velocity">
      <title>Average Velocity</title>
      <p permid="p">
        For an object moving in a straight line with position function <m>s(t)</m>, the 
            <idx><h>average velocity</h></idx>
        <em>average velocity of the object on the interval from <m>t = a</m> to <m>t = b</m></em>,
        denoted <m>AV_{[a,b]}</m>, is given by the formula
        <me>
          AV_{[a,b]} = \frac{s(b)-s(a)}{b-a}
        </me>.
      </p>
    </assemblage>

    <p permid="p4">
      Note well: the units on <m>AV_{[a,b]}</m> are
      <q>units of <m>s</m> per unit of <m>t</m>,</q>
      such as <q>miles per hour</q> or
      <q>feet per second.</q>
    </p>

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-1-1-1.xml" />
  </subsection>

  <subsection permid="ssec-instantaneous-velocity">
    <title>Instantaneous Velocity</title>
    <p permid="p1">
      Whether we are driving a car,
      riding a bike, or throwing a ball,
      we have an intuitive sense that a moving object has a velocity at any given moment -- a number that measures how fast the object is moving <em>right now</em>.
      For instance,
      a car's speedometer tells the driver the car's velocity at any given instant.
      In fact, the velocity on a speedometer is really an average velocity that is computed over a very small time interval.
      If we let the time interval over which average velocity is computed become shorter and shorter,
      we can progress from average velocity to
      <em>instantaneous</em> velocity.
    </p>

    <p permid="p2">
      Informally, we define the <em>instantaneous velocity</em>
          <idx><h>instantaneous velocity</h></idx>
      of a moving object at time <m>t = a</m> to be the value that the average velocity approaches as we take smaller and smaller intervals of time containing <m>t = a</m>.
      We will develop a more formal definition of instantaneous velocity soon,
      and this definition will be the foundation of much of our work in calculus.
      For now, it is fine to think of instantaneous velocity as follows:
      take average velocities on smaller and smaller time intervals around a specific point.
      If those average velocities approach a single number,
      then that number will be the instantaneous velocity at that point.
    </p>

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-1-1-2.xml" />

    <p permid="p3">
      <!-- As we saw in in <xref ref="act-1-1-1">Activity</xref>,
      it follows that ...
      (will cross-referencing work for activities?)
      -->
      At this point we have started to see a close connection between average velocity and instantaneous velocity.
      Each is connected not only to the physical behavior of the moving object but also to the geometric behavior of the graph of the position function.
      We are interested in computing average velocities on the interval <m>[a,b]</m> for smaller and smaller intervals.
      In order to make the link between average and instantaneous velocity more formal,
      think of the value <m>b</m> as <m>b = a + h</m>,
      where <m>h</m> is a small (non-zero) number that is allowed to vary.
      Then the average velocity of the object on the interval <m>[a,a+h]</m> is
      <me>
        AV_{[a,a+h]} = \frac{s(a+h)-s(a)}{h}
      </me>,
      with the denominator being simply <m>h</m> because <m>(a+h) - a = h</m>.
      Note that when <m>h \lt  0</m>,
      <m>AV_{[a,a+h]}</m> measures the average velocity on the interval <m>[a+h,a]</m>.
    </p>

    <p permid="p4">
      To find the instantaneous velocity at <m>t = a</m>,
      we investigate what happens as the value of <m>h</m> approaches zero.
    </p>

    <example permid="ex-computing-instantaneous-velocity-for-a-falling-ball">
      <title>Computing instantaneous velocity for a falling ball</title>
      <statement>
        <p permid="p1">
          The position function for a falling ball is given by <m>s(t) = 16 - 16t^2</m>
          (where <m>s</m> is measured in feet and <m>t</m> in seconds).
        </p>

        <p permid="p2">
          <ol permid="ol" label="a">
            <li permid="l_j">
              Find an expression for the average velocity of the ball on a time interval of the form <m>[0.5, 0.5+h]</m> where
              <m>-0.5 \lt h \lt 0.5</m> and <m>h \ne 0</m>.
            </li>

            <li permid="l_s">
              Use this expression to compute the average velocity on
              <m>[0.5,0.75]</m> and <m>[0.4,0.5]</m>.
            </li>

            <li permid="l_b">
              Make a conjecture about the instantaneous velocity at <m>t = 0.5</m>.
            </li>
          </ol>
        </p>
      </statement>
      <solution permid="s">
        <p permid="p">
          <ol permid="ol" label="a">
            <li permid="l_j">
              We make the assumptions that
              <m>-0.5 \lt  h \lt  0.5</m> and <m>h \ne 0</m> because <m>h</m> cannot be zero
              (otherwise there is no interval on which to compute average velocity)
              and because the function only makes sense on the time interval <m>0 \le t \le 1</m>,
              as this is the duration of time during which the ball is falling.
              We want to compute and simplify
              <me>
                AV_{[0.5, 0.5+h]} = \frac{s(0.5+h) - s(0.5)}{(0.5+h) - 0.5}
              </me>.
              We start by finding <m>s(0.5+h)</m>.
              To do so, we follow the rule that defines the function <m>s</m>.
              <md>
                <mrow>s(0.5+h) \amp  =  16 - 16(0.5 + h)^2</mrow>
                <mrow>\amp  =  16 - 16(0.25 + h + h^2)</mrow>
                <mrow>\amp  =  16 - 4 - 16h - 16h^2</mrow>
                <mrow>\amp  =  12 - 16h - 16h^2</mrow>
              </md>.
              Now, returning to our computation of the average velocity,
              we find that
              <md>
                <mrow>AV_{[0.5, 0.5+h]} \amp  =  \frac{s(0.5+h) - s(0.5)}{(0.5+h) - 0.5}</mrow>
                <mrow>\amp  =  \frac{(12 - 16h - 16h^2) - (16 - 16(0.5)^2)}{0.5 + h - 0.5}</mrow>
                <mrow>\amp  =  \frac{12 - 16h - 16h^2 - 12}{h}</mrow>
                <mrow>\amp  =  \frac{-16h - 16h^2}{h}</mrow>
              </md>.
              At this point, we note two things:
              first, the expression for average velocity clearly depends on <m>h</m>,
              which it must,
              since as <m>h</m> changes the average velocity will change.
              Further, we note that since <m>h</m> can never equal zero,
              we may remove the common factor of <m>h</m> from the numerator and denominator.
              It follows that
              <me>
                AV_{[0.5, 0.5+h]} = -16 - 16h
              </me>.
            </li>

            <li permid="l_s">
              From this expression we can compute the average for any small positive or negative value of <m>h</m>.
              For instance, to obtain the average velocity on
              <m>[0.5,0.75]</m>, we let <m>h = 0.25</m>,
              and the average velocity is <m>-16 - 16(0.25) = -20</m> ft/sec.
              To get the average velocity on <m>[0.4, 0.5]</m>,
              we let <m>h = -0.1</m>, and compute the average velocity as
              <me>
                -16 - 16(-0.1) = -14.4\ \text{ft/sec}
              </me>.
            </li>

            <li permid="l_b">
              We can even explore what happens to
              <m>AV_{[0.5, 0.5+h]}</m> as <m>h</m> gets closer and closer to zero.
              As <m>h</m> approaches zero,
              <m>-16h</m> will also approach zero,
              so it appears that the instantaneous velocity of the ball at <m>t = 0.5</m> should be <m>-16</m> ft/sec.
            </li>
          </ol>
        </p>
      </solution>
    </example>

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-1-1-3.xml" />
  </subsection>

  <subsection permid="ssec-summary">
    <title>Summary</title>
    <!-- The first list item is split from the others; fine in practice as long as the list is not used as a knowl. -->
    <p permid="p">
      <ul permid="ul">
        <li permid="l_j">
          For an object moving in a straight line with position function <m>s(t)</m>, the
              <idx><h>average velocity</h></idx>
          <em>average velocity of the object on the interval from <m>t = a</m> to <m>t = b</m></em>,
          denoted <m>AV_{[a,b]}</m>, is given by the formula
          <me>
            AV_{[a,b]} = \frac{s(b)-s(a)}{b-a}
          </me>.
        </li>

        <li permid="l_s">
          <p permid="p">
            The average velocity on <m>[a,b]</m> can be viewed geometrically as the slope of the line between the points <m>(a,s(a))</m> and
            <m>(b,s(b))</m> on the graph of <m>y = s(t)</m>,
            as shown in <xref ref="F-1-1-Summary">Figure</xref>.
          </p>

          <figure xml:id="F-1-1-Summary">
            <caption>The graph of position function <m>s</m> together with the line through <m>(a,s(a))</m> and <m>(b,s(b))</m> whose slope is <m>m = \frac{s(b)-s(a)}{b-a}</m>. The line's slope is the average rate of change of <m>s</m> on the interval <m>[a,b]</m>.</caption>
            <image width="50%" source="images/1_1_Summary" />
          </figure>

        </li>

        <li permid="l_b">
          Given a moving object whose position at time <m>t</m> is given by a function <m>s</m>,
          the average velocity of the object on the time interval <m>[a,b]</m> is given by <m>AV_{[a,b]} = \frac{s(b) - s(a)}{b-a}</m>.
          Viewing the interval <m>[a,b]</m> as having the form <m>[a,a+h]</m>,
          we equivalently compute average velocity by the formula <m>AV_{[a,a+h]} = \frac{s(a+h) - s(a)}{h}</m>.
        </li>

        <li permid="l_k">
          The instantaneous velocity of a moving object at a fixed time is estimated by considering average velocities on shorter and shorter time intervals that contain the instant of interest.
        </li>
      </ul>
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <xi:include href="./exercises/ez-1-1.xml" />
</section>

