<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!--********************************************************************
Copyright 2015 Robert A. Beezer

This file is part of MathBook XML.

MathBook XML is free software: you can redistribute it and/or modify
it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by
the Free Software Foundation, either version 2 or version 3 of the
License (at your option).

MathBook XML is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
GNU General Public License for more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
along with MathBook XML.  If not, see <http://www.gnu.org/licenses/>.
*********************************************************************-->
<!-- This file was originally part of the book     -->
<!-- (as copied on 2015/07/12)                     -->
<!--                                               -->
<!--   Abstract Algebra: Theory and Applications   -->
<!--                                               -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 1997-2014  Thomas W. Judson     -->

<frontmatter xml:id="frontmatter" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">

    <titlepage>

        <author>
            <personname>Matthew Boelkins</personname>
            <department>Department of Mathematics</department>
            <institution>Grand Valley State University</institution>
            <email>boelkinm@gvsu.edu</email>
        </author>

        <author>
            <personname>David Austin</personname>
            <department>Department of Mathematics</department>
            <institution>Grand Valley State University</institution>
            <email>austind@gvsu.edu</email>
        </author>

        <author>
            <personname>Steven Schlicker</personname>
            <department>Department of Mathematics</department>
            <institution>Grand Valley State University</institution>
            <email>schlicks@gvsu.edu</email>
        </author>

        <date><today /></date>

    </titlepage>

    <colophon>

        <copyright>
            <year>2012<ndash />2016</year>
            <holder>Matthew Boelkins</holder>
            <minilicense>GFDL License</minilicense>
            <shortlicense>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.2 or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts.  A copy of the license is included in the appendix entitled <q>GNU Free Documentation License.</q>  All trademarks<trademark /> are the registered<registered /> marks of their respective owners.</shortlicense>
        </copyright>

    </colophon>

    <!-- A section of its own in HTML, migrates to copyright-page in LaTeX -->
    <!-- Titles are optional, presumably none for single author,           -->
    <!-- or for every author, even if we test a mix here                   -->
    <!--
    <biography>
        <p>Matt Boelkins ... .</p>
        <p>David Austin ... .</p>
        <p>Steve Schlicker ... .</p>
    </biography>
    -->

    <!-- The following items must be placed in the desired/required order -->
    <!-- This will be checked by a Document Type Definition eventually -->
    <!-- Order: dedication, acknowledgements, forewords, prefaces -->

    <!-- Each paragraph gets centered and has some vertical separatation -->
    <!-- A line element may be used here with a single paragraph   -->
 
<!--   
    <dedication>
        <p>
            <line>To students of algebra everywhere</line>
            <line>they are the reason</line>
        </p>
        <p>And to those who teach them</p>
    </dedication>
-->

    <preface>

        <p>
        Several fundamental ideas in calculus are more than 2000 years old. As a formal subdiscipline of mathematics, calculus was first introduced and developed in the late 1600s, with key independent contributions from Sir Isaac Newton and Gottfried Wilhelm Leibniz. Mathematicians agree that the subject has been understood rigorously since the work of Augustin Louis Cauchy and Karl Weierstrass in the mid 1800s when the field of modern analysis was developed, in part to make sense of the infinitely small quantities on which calculus rests. Hence, as a body of knowledge calculus has been completely understood by experts for at least 150 years. The discipline is one of our great human intellectual achievements: among many spectacular ideas, calculus models how objects fall under the forces of gravity and wind resistance, explains how to compute areas and volumes of interesting shapes, enables us to work rigorously with infinitely small and infinitely large quantities, and connects the varying rates at which quantities change to the total change in the quantities themselves.
        </p>

        <p>
        While each author of a calculus textbook certainly offers her own creative perspective on the subject, it is hardly the case that many of the ideas she presents are new. Indeed, the mathematics community broadly agrees on what the main ideas of calculus are, as well as their justification and their importance; the core parts of nearly all calculus textbooks are very similar. As such, it is our opinion that in the 21st century <mdash /> an age where the internet permits seamless and immediate transmission of information <mdash /> no one should be required to purchase a calculus text to read, to use for a class, or to find a coherent collection of problems to solve. Calculus belongs to humankind, not any individual author or publishing company. Thus, a main purpose of this work is to present a new calculus text that is <em>free</em>. In addition, instructors who are looking for a calculus text should have the opportunity to download the source files and make modifications that they see fit; thus this text is <em>open-source</em>. Since August 2013, <em>Active Calculus</em> has been endorsed by the American Institute of Mathematics and its Open Textbook Initiative: \href{http://aimath.org/textbooks/}{<c>http://aimath.org/textbooks/</c>}.
        </p>

        <p>
        Because the text is free, any professor or student may use the electronic version of the text for no charge.  For reading on laptops or mobile devices, the best electronic version to use is the HTML one, which may be retrieved from <url>TBD</url>. A full .pdf copy of the text may be obtained by download from <url>http://gvsu.edu/s/xr</url>, where there is also a link to a print-on-demand option for purchasing a bound, softcover version for about <dollar />20.  Other ancillary materials, such as WeBWorK .def files, an activities-only workbook, and sample computer laboratory activities are available upon direct request to the author. Furthermore, because the text is open-source, any instructor may acquire the full set of source files, again by request to the author at <email>boelkinm@gvsu.edu</email>.

        This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License. The graphic
        </p>
        <image width="25%" source="images/CClicense" />
        <p>
        that appears in other locations in the text shows that the work is licensed with the Creative Commons, that the work may be used for free by any party so long as attribution is given to the author(s), that the work and its derivatives are used in the spirit of <q>share and share alike,</q> and that no party may sell this work or any of its derivatives for profit, with the following exception: <em>it is entirely acceptable for university bookstores to sell bound photocopied copies of the activities workbook to students at their standard markup above the copying expense.</em> Full details may be found by visiting <url>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</url>  or sending a letter to Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street, Suite 900, Mountain View, California, 94041, USA.
        </p>

    </preface>

    <preface>
        <title>Active Calculus: our goals</title>
        <p>
        In <em>Active Calculus</em>, we endeavor to actively engage students in learning the subject through an activity-driven approach in which the vast majority of the examples are completed by students. Where many texts present a general theory of calculus followed by substantial collections of worked examples, we instead pose problems or situations, consider possibilities, and then ask students to investigate and explore. Following key activities or examples, the presentation normally includes some overall perspective and a brief synopsis of general trends or properties, followed by formal statements of rules or theorems. While we often offer plausibility arguments for such results, rarely do we include formal proofs. It is not the intent of this text for the instructor or author to <em>demonstrate</em> to students that the ideas of calculus are coherent and true, but rather for students to <em>encounter</em> these ideas in a supportive, leading manner that enables them to begin to understand for themselves why calculus is both coherent and true. This approach is consistent with the <url href="http://launchings.blogspot.com/2011/07/the-worst-way-to-teach.html">growing body of scholarship</url> that calls for students to be interactively engaged in class.
        </p>

        <p>
        Moreover, this approach is consistent with the following goals:
        <ul>
        <li><p>To have students engage in an active, inquiry-driven approach, where learners strive to construct solutions and approaches to ideas on their own, with appropriate support through questions posed, hints, and guidance from the instructor and text.</p></li>
        <li><p>To build in students intuition for why the main ideas in calculus are natural and true.  Often, we do this through consideration of the instantaneous position and velocity of a moving object, a scenario that is common and familiar.</p></li>
        <li><p>To challenge students to acquire deep, personal understanding of calculus through reading the text and completing preview activities on their own, through working on activities in small groups in class, and through doing substantial exercises outside of class time.</p></li>
        <li><p>To strengthen students' written and oral communicating skills by having them write about and explain aloud the key ideas of calculus.</p></li>
        </ul>

        </p>
    </preface>

    <preface>
        <title>Features of the Text</title>
        <p>
        Instructors and students alike will find several consistent features in the presentation, including:
        <ul>
        <li><p><em>Motivating Questions.</em>  At the start of each section, we list 2-3 <em>motivating questions</em> that provide motivation for why the following material is of interest to us.  One goal of each section is to answer each of the motivating questions.</p></li>
        <li><p><em>Preview Activities.</em> Each section of the text begins with a short introduction, followed by a <em>preview activity</em>.  This brief reading and the preview activity are designed to foreshadow the upcoming ideas in the remainder of the section; both the reading and preview activity are intended to be accessible to students <em>in advance</em> of class, and indeed to be completed by students before a day on which a particular section is to be considered.</p></li>
        <li><p><em>Activities.</em>  A typical section in the text has three <em>activities</em>.  These are designed to engage students in an inquiry-based style that encourages them to construct solutions to key examples on their own, working individually or in small groups.</p></li>
        <li><p><em>Exercises.</em>  There are dozens of calculus texts with (collectively) tens of thousands of exercises.  Rather than repeat standard and routine exercises in this text, we recommend the use of WeBWorK with its access to the National Problem Library and around 20,000 calculus problems.  In this text, there are approximately four challenging exercises per section.  Almost every such exercise has multiple parts, requires the student to connect several key ideas, and expects that the student will do at least a modest amount of writing to answer the questions and explain their findings.  For instructors interested in a more conventional source of exercises, consider the freely available <em>APEX Calculus</em> text by Greg Hartmann et al, available from <url>http://www.apexcalculus.com/</url>.</p></li>
        <li><p><em>Graphics.</em>  As much as possible, we strive to demonstrate key fundamental ideas visually, and to encourage students to do the same.  Throughout the text, we use full-color<fn>To keep cost low, the graphics in the print-on-demand version are in black and white.  When the text itself refers to color in images, one needs to view the .html or .pdf electronically.</fn> graphics to exemplify and magnify key ideas, and to use this graphical perspective alongside both numerical and algebraic representations of calculus.</p></li>
        <li><p><em>Links to interactive graphics.</em>  Many of the ideas of calculus are best understood dynamically; java applets offer an often ideal format for investigations and demonstrations.  Relying primarily on the work of David Austin of Grand Valley State University and Marc Renault of Shippensburg University, each of whom has developed a large library of applets for calculus, we frequently point the reader (through active links in the electronic versions of the text) to applets that are relevant for key ideas under consideration.</p></li>
        <li><p><em>Summary of Key Ideas.</em>  Each section concludes with a summary of the key ideas encountered in the preceding section; this summary normally reflects responses to the motivating questions that began the section.</p></li>
        </ul>

        </p>
    </preface>

    <preface>
        <title>How to Use this Text</title>
        <p>
        This text may be used as a stand-alone textbook for a standard first semester college calculus course or as a supplement to a more traditional text. <xref ref="C-1">Chapters</xref>- <xref ref="C-4"></xref> address the typical topics for differential calculus, while <xref ref="C-5">Chapters</xref>- <xref ref="C-8"></xref> provide the standard topics of integral calculus, including a chapter on differential equations (<xref ref="C-7">Chapter</xref>) and on infinite series (<xref ref="C-8">Chapter</xref>).
        </p>

        <ul>
            <li><p><em>Electronically</em>.  Because students and instructors alike have access to the book in electronic format, there are several advantages to the text over a traditional print text. One is that the text may be projected on a screen in the classroom (or even better, on a whiteboard) and the instructor may reference ideas in the text directly, add comments or notation or features to graphs, and indeed write right on the text itself. Students can do likewise, choosing to print only whatever portions of the text are needed for them. In addition, the electronic versions of the text includes live html links to java applets, so student and instructor alike may follow those links to additional resources that lie outside the text itself. Finally, students can have access to a copy of the text anywhere they have a computer.
            </p></li>    

            <li><p><em>Activities Workbook</em>.  Each section of the text has a preview activity and at least three in-class activities embedded in the discussion. As it is the expectation that students will complete all of these activities, it is ideal for them to have room to work on them adjacent to the problem statements themselves. As a separate document, we have compiled a workbook of activities that includes only the individual activity prompts, along with space provided for students to write their responses. This workbook is the one printing expense that students will almost certainly have to undertake, and is available upon request.
            </p></li>
            
            <li><p><em>Community of Users</em>.  Because this text is free and open-source, we hope that as people use the text, they will contribute corrections, suggestions, and new material. The best way to communicate such feedback is by email to Matt Boelkins at <email>boelkinm@gvsu.edu</email>. We also have a blog at <url>http://opencalculus.wordpress.com</url>, at which we  post feedback, new developments, and other points of discussion.
            </p></li>
        </ul>

    </preface>

    <acknowledgement>

        <p>*** Thank you ***. </p>

        <ul>
            <li><p>Contributor, Institution</p></li>
        </ul>

        <p>I would also like to thank ... .</p>

        <!-- Added NSF support statement.  TWJ 8/9/2012 -->
        <p>Special thanks to Rob Beezer.</p>

        <attribution>
            <line>Matt Boelkins</line>
            <line>Allendale, MI 2016</line>
        </attribution>

    </acknowledgement>

</frontmatter>
