<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<!-- Copyright 2012-2019                                                   -->
<!-- Matthew Boelkins                                                      -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- This file is part of Active Calculus.                                 -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document -->
<!-- under the terms of the Creative Commons BY-SA license.  The work      -->
<!-- may be used for free by any party so long as attribution is given to  -->
<!-- the author(s), the work and its derivatives are used in the spirit of -->
<!-- "share and share alike".  All trademarks are the registered marks of  -->
<!-- their respective owners.                                              -->
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<frontmatter xml:id="frontmatter" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" permid="yaN">
  <xi:include href="./titlepage.xml" />
  <xi:include href="./colophon.xml" />

  <acknowledgement>
    <p permid="MOm">
      This text began as my sabbatical project in the winter semester of 2012,
      during which I wrote most of the material for the first four chapters.
      For the sabbatical leave, I am indebted to Grand Valley State University for its support of the project,
      as well as to my colleagues in the Department of Mathematics and the College of Liberal Arts and Sciences for their endorsement of the project.
      I'm also grateful to the American Institute of Mathematics
      for their <url href="https://aimath.org/textbooks/">support of free and open textbooks in general</url>,
      and their support of this one in particular.
    </p>

    <p permid="sVv">
      The beautiful full-color .eps graphics in the text are only possible because of David Austin of GVSU and Bill Casselman of the University of British Columbia.
      Building on their longstanding efforts to develop tools for high quality mathematical graphics, David wrote a library of Python routines that employ <url href="http://gvsu.edu/s/bi">Bill's PiScript program</url>; 
      David's routines are so easy to use that even I could generate graphics like the professionals that he and Bill are.
      I am deeply grateful to them both.
    </p>

    <p permid="ZcE">
      The current .html version of the text is possible only because of the amazing work of Rob Beezer and his development of the original <url href="https://mathbook.pugetsound.edu">Mathbook XML</url>,
      now known as <pretext />.
      My ability to take advantage of Rob's work is due to the support of the American Institute of Mathematics,
      which funded me to attend a weeklong workshop in Mathbook XML in San Jose, CA, in April 2016, as well as 
      the support of the ongoing
      <url href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!forum/pretext-support">user group</url>.
      David Farmer's conversion script saved me hundreds of hours of work by taking my original <latex /> source and converting it to <pretext />; David remains a major source of ongoing support and advocacy.
      Alex Jordan of Portland Community College has also been a tremendous help,
      and it is through Alex's fantastic work that live
      <webwork /> exercises are not only possible,
      but also included from the 2017 version forward.
      Mitch Keller of Morningside College agreed in early 2018 to serve as the book's production editor; his 
      technical expertise has contributed to many aspects of the book,
      including the presence of answers to
      activities and non-
      <webwork /> exercises and other supporting material for instructors.
    </p>

    <p permid="FjN">
      For the 2018 edition, Kathy Yoshiwara of the AIM Editorial Board read the entire text and contributed 
      editorial suggestions for every section.
      In short, she made the prose cleaner,
      more direct, and simply better.
      I'm deeply thankful for her time, effort, and insights.
    </p>

    <p permid="lqW">
      Over my more than 20 years at GVSU, many of my colleagues have shared with me ideas and 
      resources for teaching calculus.
      I am particularly indebted to David Austin, Will Dickinson, Paul Fishback, Jon Hodge,
      and Steve Schlicker for their contributions that improved my teaching of and thinking about calculus,
      including materials that I have modified and used over many different semesters with students.
      Parts of these ideas can be found throughout this text.
      In addition, Will Dickinson and Steve Schlicker provided me access to a large number of their electronic notes and activities from teaching of differential and integral calculus,
      and those ideas and materials have similarly impacted my work and writing in positive ways,
      with some of their problems and approaches finding parallel presentation here.
    </p>

    <p permid="Ryf">
      In the summer of 2012, David and Steve each agreed to write a chapter to support the completion 
      of the material on integral calculus. 
      David is the lead author of <xref ref="C-7">Chapter</xref>
      and Steve the lead author of <xref ref="C-8">Chapter</xref>.
      Along with our colleague Ted Sundstrom, Steve has also contributed a large number of problem and 
      activity solutions and answers.
      I'm deeply grateful for how the work of these friends and colleagues
      has made the text so much better.
    </p>

    <p permid="xFo">
      Shelly Smith of GVSU and Matt DeLong of Marian University both provided extensive comments on the first few chapters of early drafts,
      feedback that was immensely helpful in improving the text.
      As more and more people use the text, I am grateful to everyone who reads,
      edits, and uses this book,
      and hence contributes to its improvement through ongoing discussion.
    </p>

    <p permid="dMx">
      Finally, I am grateful for all that my students have taught me over the years.
      Their responses and feedback have helped to shape me as a teacher,
      and I appreciate their willingness to wholeheartedly engage in the activities and approaches I've tried in class,
      to let me know how those affect their learning,
      and to help me learn and grow as an instructor.
      Early on, they also provided useful editorial feedback on this text.
    </p>

    <p permid="JTG">
      Any and all remaining errors or inconsistencies are mine.
      I will gladly take <url href="http://gvsu.edu/s/0vK">reader and user feedback</url> 
      to correct them, along with other suggestions to improve the text.
    </p>
    <!--<attribution>
    <line>Matt Boelkins</line>
    <line>Allendale, MI</line>
    <line>July 2017</line>
    <line>
    <email>boelkinm@gvsu.edu</email>
    </line>
    </attribution>-->
  </acknowledgement>

  <preface permid="ehW">
    <title>Contributors</title>
    <p permid="DuA">
      A large and growing number of people have generously contributed to the development or improvement of the text.
      Contributing authors David Austin and Steven Schlicker have each written drafts of at least one full chapter of the text.
      Production editor Mitchel Keller has been an indispensable source of technological support and editorial counsel.
    </p>

    <p permid="jBJ">
      The following contributing editors have offered feedback that includes information about typographical errors or suggestions to improve the exposition.
    </p>

    <contributors>
      <contributor>
        <personname>David Austin</personname>
        <institution>GVSU</institution>
      </contributor>

      <contributor>
        <personname>Rene Ardila</personname>
        <institution>GVSU</institution>
      </contributor>

      <contributor>
        <personname>Allan Bickle</personname>
        <institution>GVSU</institution>
      </contributor>

      <contributor>
        <personname>David Clark</personname>
        <institution>GVSU</institution>
      </contributor>

      <contributor>
        <personname>Will Dickinson</personname>
        <institution>GVSU</institution>
      </contributor>

      <contributor>
        <personname>Charles Fortin</personname>
        <institution>Champlain Regional College</institution>
        <location>St-Lambert, Quebec, Canada</location>
      </contributor>

      <contributor>
        <personname>Marcia Frobish</personname>
        <institution>GVSU</institution>
      </contributor>

      <contributor>
        <personname>Patti Hunter</personname>
        <institution>Westmont College</institution>
      </contributor>

      <contributor>
        <personname>Mitchel Keller</personname>
        <institution>Morningside College</institution>
      </contributor>

      <contributor>
        <personname>Dave Kung</personname>
        <institution>St. Mary's College of Maryland</institution>
      </contributor>

      <contributor>
        <personname>Paul Latiolais</personname>
        <institution>Portland State University</institution>
      </contributor>

      <contributor>
        <personname>Wendy Lightheart</personname>
        <institution>Lane Community College</institution>
      </contributor>

      <contributor>
        <personname>Hugh McGuire</personname>
        <institution>GVSU</institution>
      </contributor>

      <contributor>
        <personname>Ray Rosentrater</personname>
        <institution>Westmont College</institution>
      </contributor>

      <contributor>
        <personname>Luis Sanjuan</personname>
        <institution>Conservatorio Profesional de Musica de Avila</institution>
        <location>Spain</location>
      </contributor>

      <contributor>
        <personname>Steven Schlicker</personname>
        <institution>GVSU</institution>
      </contributor>

      <contributor>
        <personname>Michael Shulman</personname>
        <institution>University of San Diego</institution>
      </contributor>

      <contributor>
        <personname>Brian Stanley</personname>
        <institution>Foothill Community College</institution>
      </contributor>

      <contributor>
        <personname>Amy Stone</personname>
        <institution>GVSU</institution>
      </contributor>

      <contributor>
        <personname>Robert Talbert</personname>
        <institution>GVSU</institution>
      </contributor>

      <contributor>
        <personname>Greg Thull</personname>
        <institution>GVSU</institution>
      </contributor>

      <contributor>
        <personname>Sue Van Hattum</personname>
        <institution>Contra Costa College</institution>
      </contributor>

      <contributor>
        <personname>Kathy Yoshiwara</personname>
        <institution>AIM Editorial Board</institution>
      </contributor>
    </contributors>

  </preface>

  <preface permid="Kpf">
    <title>Active Calculus: Our Goals</title>
    <p permid="PIS">
      Several fundamental ideas in calculus are more than 2000 years old.
      As a formal subdiscipline of mathematics,
      calculus was first introduced and developed in the late 1600s,
      with key independent contributions from Sir Isaac Newton and Gottfried Wilhelm Leibniz.
      The subject has been understood rigorously since the work of Augustin Louis Cauchy and Karl Weierstrass in the mid 1800s when the field of modern analysis was developed.
      As a body of knowledge,
      calculus has been completely understood for at least 150 years.
      The discipline is one of our great human intellectual achievements:
      among many spectacular ideas,
      calculus models how objects fall under the forces of gravity and wind resistance,
      explains how to compute areas and volumes of interesting shapes,
      enables us to work rigorously with infinitely small and infinitely large quantities,
      and connects the varying rates at which quantities change to the total change in the quantities themselves.
    </p>

    <p permid="vQb">
      While each author of a calculus textbook certainly offers their own creative perspective on the subject,
      it is hardly the case that many of the ideas they present are new.
      Indeed, the mathematics community broadly agrees on what the main ideas of calculus are,
      as well as their justification and their importance.
      In the 21st century and the age of the internet, 
      no one should be required to purchase a calculus text to read,
      to use for a class,
      or to find a coherent collection of problems to solve.
      Calculus belongs to humankind,
      not any individual author or publishing company.
      Thus, a primary purpose of this work is to present a calculus text that is <em>free</em>.
      See <url href="https://activecalculus.org">https://activecalculus.org</url> for links to both 
      the .html and .pdf versions of the text.
      In addition,
      instructors who are looking for a calculus text should have the opportunity to download the source files and make modifications that they see fit;
      thus this text is <em>open-source</em>.
      See <url href="https://github.com/active-calculus/active-calculus-single-mbx">GitHub</url> 
      for the <PreTeXt /> source.
      Since August 2013, <em>Active Calculus - Single Variable</em>
      has been endorsed by the American Institute of Mathematics and its 
      <url href="http://aimath.org/textbooks">Open Textbook Initiative</url>.
    </p>

    <p permid="bXk">
      In <pubtitle>Active Calculus - Single Variable</pubtitle>,
      we actively engage students in learning the subject through an activity-driven approach in which the vast majority of the examples are generated by students.
      Where many texts present a general theory followed by substantial collections of worked examples,
      we instead pose problems or situations,
      consider possibilities, and then ask students to investigate and explore.
      Following key activities or examples,
      the presentation normally includes some overall perspective and a brief synopsis of general trends or properties,
      followed by formal statements of rules or theorems.
      While we often offer plausibility arguments for such results,
      rarely do we include formal proofs.
      It is not the intent of this text for the instructor or author to demonstrate
      to students that the ideas of calculus are coherent and true,
      but rather for students to encounter these ideas in a supportive,
      leading manner that enables them to begin to understand calculus for themselves.
      This approach is consistent with the
      <url href="http://launchings.blogspot.com/2011/07/the-worst-way-to-teach.html">scholarly consensus</url>
      that calls for students to be interactively engaged in class.
    </p>

    <p permid="Iet">
      Moreover, this approach is consistent with the following goals:

      <ul permid="CKG">
        <li permid="vgh">
          <p permid="JjM">
            To have students engage in an active, inquiry-driven approach,
            where learners construct solutions and approaches to ideas,
            with appropriate support through questions posed, hints,
            and guidance from the instructor and text.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="bnq">
          <p permid="pqV">
            To build in students intuition for why the main ideas in calculus are natural and true.
            Often we do this through consideration of the instantaneous position and velocity of a moving object.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="Huz">
          <p permid="Vye">
            To challenge students to acquire deep,
            personal understanding of calculus through reading the text and completing preview activities on their own,
            working on activities in small groups in class,
            and doing substantial exercises outside of class time.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="nBI">
          <p permid="BFn">
            To strengthen students' written and oral communicating skills by having them write about and explain aloud the key ideas of calculus.
          </p>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </p>
  </preface>

  <preface permid="qwo">
    <title>Features of the Text</title>
    <p permid="olC">
      Instructors and students alike will find several consistent features in the presentation,
      including:
      <dl width="narrow" permid="iRP">
        <li permid="TIR">
          <title>Motivating Questions</title>
          <p permid="hMw">
            At the start of each section,
            we list 2<ndash />3 <em>motivating questions</em>
            that provide motivation for why the following material is of interest to us.
            One overall goal of each section is to answer each of the motivating questions.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="zQa">
          <title>Preview Activities</title>
          <p permid="NTF">
            Each section of the text begins with a short introduction,
            followed by a <em>preview activity</em>.
            This brief reading and the preview activity are designed to foreshadow the upcoming ideas in the remainder of the section;
            both the reading and preview activity are intended to be accessible to students
            <em>in advance</em> of class,
            and to be completed by students before the day on which a particular section is to be considered.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="fXj">
          <title>Activities</title>
          <p permid="uaO">
            A typical section in the text has at least three <em>activities</em>.
            These are designed to engage students in an inquiry-based style that encourages them to construct solutions to key examples on their own,
            working individually or in small groups.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="Mes">
          <title>Exercises</title>
          <p permid="ahX">
            There are dozens of calculus texts with (collectively) tens of thousands of exercises.
            Rather than repeat standard and routine exercises in this text,
            we recommend the use of
            <webwork />
            with its access to the Open Problem Library and around 20,000 calculus problems.
            In this text,
            each section includes a small number of anonymous
            <webwork />
            exercises,
            as well as 3<ndash />4 challenging problems per section.
            The
            <webwork />
            exercises are best completed in
            <url href="https://activecalculus.org/single/">the .html version of the text</url>.
            Almost every non-
            <webwork />
            exercise has multiple parts,
            requires the student to connect several key ideas,
            and expects that the student will do at least a modest amount of writing to answer the questions and explain their findings.
            For instructors interested in a more conventional source of exercises,
            consider the freely available <pubtitle>APEX Calculus</pubtitle> text by Greg Hartmann et al., available from
            <url href="http://www.apexcalculus.com">www.apexcalculus.com</url>.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="slB">
          <title>Graphics</title>
          <p permid="Gpg">
            As much as possible,
            we strive to demonstrate key fundamental ideas visually,
            and to encourage students to do the same.
            Throughout the text, we use full-color<fn>
            To keep cost low,
            the graphics in the print-on-demand version are in black and white.
            When the text itself refers to color in images,
            one needs to view the .html or .pdf electronically.
            </fn> graphics to exemplify and magnify key ideas,
            and to use this graphical perspective alongside both numerical and algebraic representations of calculus.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="YsK">
          <title>Links to interactive graphics</title>
          <p permid="mwp">
            Many of the ideas of calculus are best understood dynamically;
            java applets offer an often ideal format for investigations and demonstrations.
            Relying primarily on the work of David Austin of Grand Valley State University and Marc Renault of Shippensburg University,
            each of whom has developed a large library of applets for calculus,
            we frequently point the reader
            (through active links in the electronic versions of the text)
            to applets that are relevant for key ideas under consideration.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="EzT">
          <title>Summary of Key Ideas</title>
          <p permid="SDy">
            Each section concludes with a summary of the key ideas encountered in the preceding section;
            this summary normally reflects responses to the motivating questions that began the section.
          </p>
        </li>
      </dl>
    </p>
  </preface>

  <preface permid="WDx">
    <title>How to Use this Text</title>
    <p permid="UsL">
      Because the text is free,
      any professor or student may use the electronic version of the text for no charge.
      For reading on laptops or mobile devices,
      the best electronic version to use is the .html one at 
      <url href="https://activecalculus.org/single/">https://activecalculus.org/single/</url>,
      but you may also download a full .pdf copy of the text from 
      <url href="http://gvsu.edu/s/0vM">gvsu.edu/s/0vM</url>,
      where there is also a link to a print-on-demand option for purchasing a bound,
      softcover version for about <dollar />20.
      Other ancillary materials, such as
      <webwork /> .def files,
      an activities-only workbook,
      and sample computer laboratory activities are available upon direct request to the author via email 
      at
      <email>boelkinm@gvsu.edu</email>
      . Furthermore,
      because the text is open-source,
      any instructor may acquire the full set of source files,
      which are
      <url href="https://github.com/active-calculus/active-calculus-single-mbx">available on GitHub</url>.
    </p>

    <p permid="AzU">
      This text may be used as a stand-alone textbook for a standard first semester college calculus course or as a supplement to a more traditional text.
      <xref first="C-1" last="C-4">Chapters</xref>
      address the standard topics for differential calculus,
      while <xref first="C-5" last="C-8">Chapters</xref>
      correspond to integral calculus,
      including chapters on differential equations
      (<xref ref="C-7">Chapter</xref>)
      and infinite series
      (<xref ref="C-8">Chapter</xref>).
    </p>

    <p permid="gHd">
      <dl width="narrow" permid="OYY">
        <li permid="kHc">
          <title>Electronic Edition</title>
          <p permid="yKH">
            Because students and instructors alike have access to the book in electronic format,
            there are several advantages to the text over a traditional print text.
            One is that the text may be projected on a screen in the classroom
            (or even better, on a whiteboard)
            and the instructor may reference ideas in the text directly,
            add comments or notation or features to graphs,
            and indeed write right on the text itself.
            Students can do likewise,
            choosing to print only whatever portions of the text are needed for them.
            In addition,
            the electronic versions of the text includes live .html links to java applets,
            so student and instructor alike may follow those links to additional resources that lie outside the text itself.
            Finally,
            students can have access to a copy of the text anywhere they have internet access.
            The .html version is far superior to the .pdf version;
            this is especially true for viewing on a smartphone.
            It is worthwhile to download the .pdf version for local access in the event of internet issues.
          </p>

          <p permid="eRQ">
            <em>Note.</em> In the .pdf version,
            there is not an obvious visual indicator of the live .html links,
            so some available information is suppressed.
            If you are using the text electronically in a setting with internet access,
            please know that it is assumed you are using the .html version.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="QOl">
          <title>Activities Workbook</title>
          <p permid="KYZ">
            Each section of the text has a preview activity and typically at least three in-class activities 
            embedded in the discussion.
            As it is the expectation that students will complete all of these activities,
            it is ideal for them to have room to work on them adjacent to the problem statements themselves.
            As a separate document,
            we have compiled a workbook of activities that includes only the individual activity prompts,
            along with space provided for students to write their responses.
            This workbook is the one printing expense that students will almost certainly have to undertake,
            and is available in .pdf upon request,
            as well as for purchase for a nominal fee on Amazon.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="wVu">
          <title>Answers</title>
          <p permid="rgi">
            In the 2018 edition, we now offer answers to non-
            <webwork /> exercises and all activities other than the previews.
            To save printing cost,
            the answers are only available in the .html and .pdf versions of the text,
            not in the print version for sale on Amazon.
            Anyone using the print version should refer to the appendices in an electronic version for access to answers.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="dcD">
          <title>Community of Users</title>
          <p permid="Xnr">
            Because this text is free and open-source,
            we hope that as people use the text,
            they will contribute corrections,
            suggestions, and new material.
            The best way to communicate such feedback is by email to Matt Boelkins at boelkinm at gvsu dot edu.
            We also have a blog at <url href="http://opencalculus.wordpress.com">opencalculus.wordpress.com</url>,
            where we post new developments,
            other free resources, feedback,
            and other points of discussion.
          </p>
        </li>
        <li permid="WQm">
          <p permid="bAf">
             Brief discussion and possibly lecture to reach closure on the preceding activity, followed by transition to new ideas.  (Varies, but 5-15 minutes)
          </p>
        </li>
        <li permid="CXv">
          <p permid="HHo">
            Possibly begin next activity.
          </p>
        </li>
      </ul>
      The next hour of class would be similar, but without the Preview Activity to complete prior to class: the principal focus of class will be completing 2 activities.  Then rinse and repeat.
    </p>

    <p permid="JwB">
      We recommend that instructors use appropriate incentives to encourage students to complete Preview Activities prior to class.  Having these be part of completion-based assignments that count 5% of the semester grade usually results in the vast majority of students completing the vast majority of the previews.  If you'd like to see a sample syllabus for how to organize a course and weight various assignments, you can request one via email to the author.
    </p>

    <p permid="pDK">
      Note that the <webwork /> exercises in the HTML version are anonymous and there's not a way to track students' engagement with them.  These are intended to be formative for students and provide them with immediate feedback without penalty.  If your institution is a <webwork /> user, we have existing sets of .def files that correspond to the sections in the text; these are available upon request to the author.
    </p>

    <p permid="VKT">
      In the <xref ref="backmatter" text="custom">back matter of the text</xref>, you'll find answers to the Activities and to non-<webwork /> Exercises.  Instructors interested in solutions to these should contact the author directly.
    </p>

    <p permid="BSc">
      You and your students can find additional resources in the <url href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PL9bIjQJDwfGuXQHuS5Jkmum_CFILoCZX-">GVSU Math 201 YouTube Channel</url> and <url href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PL9bIjQJDwfGtewW75Nw7PnGNSkfqwAm3v">GVSU Math 202 YouTube Channel</url> where there are short video tutorials for every section of the text.  Math 201 (GVSU's Calculus I) corresponds to Chapters 1-4 and Math 202 (GVSU's Calculus II) to Chapters 5-8.
    </p>

    <p permid="hZl">
      The <pretext /> source code for the text can be found on <url href="https://github.com/active-calculus/active-calculus-single-mbx">GitHub</url>.  If you find errors in the text or have other suggestions, you can file an issue on GitHub, use the <url href="http://gvsu.edu/s/0vK">Feedback link</url> in the HTML version (found at the bottom left in the main menu), or email the author directly.  To engage with instructors who use the text, we maintain both an email list and the <url href="https://opencalculus.wordpress.com/">Open Calculus blog</url>; you can request that your address be added to the email list by contacting the author.  Finally, if you're interested in a video presentation on using the text, you can see this <url href="http://math.mit.edu/seminars/esme/videos/2018-10-02_Boelkins.mp4">online video presentation</url> to the <url href="http://math.mit.edu/seminars/esme/">MIT Electronic Seminar on Mathematics Education</url>; at about the 17-minute mark, the portion begins where we demonstrate features of and how to use the text. 
    </p>

    <p permid="Ogu">
      Thank you for considering <pubtitle>Active Calculus</pubtitle> as a resource to help your students develop deep understanding of the subject.  I wish you the very best in your work and hope to hear from you.
    </p>
  </preface>

</frontmatter>

