<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<!-- Copyright 2012-2018                                                   -->
<!-- Matthew Boelkins                                                      -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- This file is part of Active Calculus.                                 -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document -->
<!-- under the terms of the Creative Commons BY-SA license.  The work      -->
<!-- may be used for free by any party so long as attribution is given to  -->
<!-- the author(s), the work and its derivatives are used in the spirit of -->
<!-- "share and share alike".  All trademarks are the registered marks of  -->
<!-- their respective owners.                                              -->
<!-- **********************************************************************-->

<section xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec-6-1-area">
  <title>Using Definite Integrals to Find Area and Length</title>
  <objectives>
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>
          How can we use definite integrals to measure the area between two curves?
        </p>
      </li>

      <li>
        <p>
          How do we decide whether to integrate with respect to <m>x</m> or with respect to <m>y</m> when we try to find the area of a region?
        </p>
      </li>

      <li>
        <p>
          How can a definite integral be used to measure the length of a curve?
        </p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </objectives>
  <introduction>
    <p>
      Early on in our work with the definite integral,
      we learned that for an object moving along an axis, the area under a non-negative velocity function <m>v</m> between <m>a</m> and <m>b</m> tells us the distance the object traveled on that time interval, and that area is given precisely by the definite integral <m>\int_a^b v(t) \, dt</m>.
      In general, for any nonnegative function <m>f</m> on an interval <m>[a,b]</m>,
      <m>\int_a^b f(x) \, dx</m> measures the area bounded by the curve and the <m>x</m>-axis between <m>x = a</m> and <m>x = b</m>.
    </p>

    <p>
      Next,
      we will explore how definite integrals can be used to represent other physically important properties.
      In <xref ref="PA-6-1">Preview Activity</xref>,
      we investigate how a single definite integral may be used to represent the area between two curves.
    </p>

    <xi:include href="./previews/PA-6-1.xml" />
  </introduction>

  <subsection>
    <title>The Area Between Two Curves</title>
    <idx><h>area</h></idx>

    <p>
      In <xref ref="PA-6-1">Preview Activity</xref>,
      we saw a natural way to think about the area between two curves:
      it is the area beneath the upper curve minus the area below the lower curve.
    </p>

    <example>
      <statement>
        <p>
          Find the area bounded between the graphs of <m>f(x) = (x-1)^2 + 1</m> and <m>g(x) = x+2</m>.  
        </p>

        <figure xml:id="F-6-1-PA1revisited">
          <caption>The areas bounded by the functions <m>f(x) = (x-1)^2 + 1</m> and <m>g(x) = x+2</m> on the interval <m>[0,3]</m>.</caption>
          <image width="100%" source="images/6_1_PA1revisited" />
        </figure>
      </statement>

      <solution>
        <p>
          In <xref ref="F-6-1-PA1revisited">Figure</xref>, we see that the graphs intersect at <m>(0,2)</m> and <m>(3,5)</m>.
          We can find these intersection points algebraically by solving the system of equations given by
          <m>y = (x-1)^2 + 1</m> and <m>y = x+2</m>:
          substituting <m>x+2</m> for <m>y</m> in the first equation yields <m>x+2 = (x-1)^2 + 1</m>,
          so <m>x+2 = x^2 - 2x + 1 + 1</m>, and thus
          <me>
            x^2 - 3x = x(x-3) = 0
          </me>,
          from which it follows that <m>x = 0</m> or <m>x = 3</m>.
          Using <m>y = x+2</m>,
          we find the corresponding <m>y</m>-values of the intersection points.
        </p>

        <p>
          On the interval <m>[0,3]</m>,
          the area beneath <m>g</m> is
          <me>
            \int_0^3 (x+2) \, dx = \frac{21}{2}
          </me>,
          while the area under <m>f</m> on the same interval is
          <me>
            \int_0^3 [(x-1)^2 + 1] \, dx = 6
          </me>.
        </p>

        <p>
          Thus, the area between the curves is
          <men xml:id="E-DiffOfInt">
            A = \int_0^3 (x+2) \, dx -  \int_0^3 [(x-1)^2 + 1] \, dx = \frac{21}{2} - 6 = \frac{9}{2}
          </men>.
        </p>
      </solution>
    </example>

    <p>
      We can also think of the area this way:
      if we slice up the region between two curves into thin vertical rectangles
      (in the same spirit as we originally sliced the region between a single curve and the <m>x</m>-axis in <xref ref="sec-4-2-Riemann">Section</xref>),
      we see (as shown in <xref ref="F-6-1-PA1revisited2">Figure</xref>) that the height of a typical rectangle is given by the difference between the two functions,
      <m>g(x) - f(x)</m>,
      and its width is <m>\Delta x</m>.
      Thus the area of the rectangle is
      <me>
        A_{\text{rect} } = (g(x) - f(x)) \Delta x
      </me>.
    </p>

    <figure xml:id="F-6-1-PA1revisited2">
      <caption>The area bounded by the functions <m>f(x) = (x-1)^2 + 1</m> and <m>g(x) = x+2</m> on the interval <m>[0,3]</m>.</caption>
      <image width="100%" source="images/6_1_PA1revisited2" />
    </figure>

    <p>
      The area between the two curves on <m>[0,3]</m> is thus approximated by the Riemann sum
      <me>
        A \approx \sum_{i=1}^{n} (g(x_i) - f(x_i)) \Delta x
      </me>,
      and as we let <m>n \to \infty</m>,
      it follows that the area is given by the single definite integral
      <men xml:id="E-IntOfDiff">
        A = \int_0^3 (g(x) - f(x)) \, dx
      </men>.
    </p>

    <p>
      In many applications of the definite integral,
      we will find it helpful to think of a
      <q>representative slice</q>
      and use the definite integral to add these slices.
      Here, the integral sums the areas of thin rectangles.
    </p>

    <p>
      Finally, it doesn't matter whether we think of the area between two curves as the difference between the area bounded by the individual curves
      (as in<nbsp /><xref ref="E-DiffOfInt" />)
      or as the limit of a Riemann sum of the areas of thin rectangles between the curves
      (as in<nbsp /><xref ref="E-IntOfDiff" />).
      These two results are the same,
      since the difference of two integrals is the integral of the difference:
      <me>
        \int_0^3 g(x) \, dx -  \int_0^3 f(x) \, dx = \int_0^3 (g(x) - f(x)) \, dx
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p>
      Our work so far in this section illustrates the following general principle.
    </p>

    <assemblage>
      <p>
        If two curves <m>y = g(x)</m> and
        <m>y = f(x)</m> intersect at <m>(a,g(a))</m> and <m>(b,g(b))</m>,
        and for all <m>x</m> such that
        <m>a \le x \le b</m>, <m>g(x) \ge f(x)</m>,
        then the area between the curves is <m>A = \int_a^b (g(x) - f(x)) \, dx</m>.
      </p>
    </assemblage>

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-6-1-1.xml" />
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <title>Finding Area with Horizontal Slices</title>
    <p>
      At times, the shape of a region may dictate that we use horizontal rectangular slices,
      instead of vertical ones.
    </p>

    <example>
      <statement>
        <p>
          Find the area of the region bounded by the parabola
          <m>x = y^2 - 1</m> and the line <m>y = x-1</m>,
          shown at left in <xref ref="F-6-1-IntWRTy">Figure</xref>.
        </p>

        <figure xml:id="F-6-1-IntWRTy">
          <caption>The area bounded by the functions <m>x = y^2-1</m> and <m>y = x-1</m> (at left), with the region sliced vertically (center) and horizontally (at right).</caption>
          <image width="100%" source="images/6_1_IntWRTy" />
        </figure>

      </statement>

      <solution>
        <p>
          By solving the second equation for <m>x</m> and writing <m>x = y + 1</m>,
          we find that <m>y+1 = y^2 - 1</m>.
          Hence the curves intersect where <m>y^2 - y - 2 = 0</m>.
          Thus, we find <m>y = -1</m> or <m>y = 2</m>,
          so the intersection points of the two curves are <m>(0,-1)</m> and <m>(3,2)</m>.
        </p>

        <p>
          If we attempt to use vertical rectangles to slice up the area (as in the center graph 
          of <xref ref="F-6-1-IntWRTy">Figure</xref>), we see that
          from <m>x = -1</m> to <m>x = 0</m>
          the curves that bound the top and bottom of the rectangle are one and the same.
          This suggests, as shown in the rightmost graph in the figure,
          that we try using horizontal rectangles.
        </p>

        <p>
          Note that the width of a horizontal rectangle depends on <m>y</m>.
          Between <m>y = -1</m> and <m>y = 2</m>,
          the right end of a representative rectangle is determined by the line 
          <m>x = y+1</m>,
          and the left end is determined by the parabola, <m>x = y^2-1</m>.
          The thickness of the rectangle is <m>\Delta y</m>.
        </p>

        <p>
          Therefore, the area of the rectangle is
          <me>
            A_{\text{rect} } = [(y+1) - (y^2-1)] \Delta y
          </me>,
          and the area between the two curves on the <m>y</m>-interval <m>[-1,2]</m> is approximated by the Riemann sum
          <me>
            A \approx \sum_{i=1}^{n} [(y_i+1)-(y_i^2-1)] \Delta y
          </me>.
        </p>

        <p>
          Taking the limit of the Riemann sum,
          it follows that the area of the region is
          <men xml:id="E-IntWRTy">
            A = \int_{y=-1}^{y=2} [(y+1) - (y^2-1)] \, dy
          </men>.
        </p>

        <p>
          We emphasize that we are integrating with respect to <m>y</m>;
          this is because we chose to use horizontal rectangles whose widths depend on <m>y</m> and whose thickness is denoted <m>\Delta y</m>.
          It is a straightforward exercise to evaluate the integral in <xref ref="E-IntWRTy">Equation</xref> and find that <m>A = \frac{9}{2}</m>.
        </p>
      </solution>
    </example>

    <p>
      Just as with the use of vertical rectangles of thickness <m>\Delta x</m>,
      we have a general principle for finding the area between two curves,
      which we state as follows.
    </p>

    <assemblage>
      <p>
        If two curves <m>x = g(y)</m> and
        <m>x = f(y)</m> intersect at <m>(g(c),c)</m> and <m>(g(d),d)</m>,
        and for all <m>y</m> such that <m>c \le y \le d</m>,
        <m>g(y) \ge f(y)</m>, then the area between the curves is
        <me>
          A = \int_{y=c}^{y=d} (g(y) - f(y)) \, dy
        </me>.
      </p>
    </assemblage>

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-6-1-2.xml" />
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <title>Finding the length of a curve</title>
    <idx><h>arc length</h></idx>

    <p>
      We can also use the definite integral to find the length of a portion of a curve.
      We use the same fundamental principle:
      we slice the curve up into small pieces whose lengths we can easily approximate.
      Specifically,
      we subdivide the curve into small approximating line segments,
      as shown at left in <xref ref="F-6-1-ArcLength">Figure</xref>.
    </p>

    <figure xml:id="F-6-1-ArcLength">
      <caption>At left, a continuous function <m>y = f(x)</m> whose length we seek on the interval <m>a = x_0</m> to <m>b = x_3</m>.  At right, a close up view of a portion of the curve.</caption>
      <image width="100%" source="images/6_1_ArcLength" />
    </figure>

    <p>
      We estimate the length
      <m>L_{\text{slice} }</m> of each portion of the curve on a small interval of length <m>\Delta x</m>.
      We use the right triangle with legs parallel to the coordinate axes and hypotenuse connecting the endpoints of the slice,
      as seen at right in <xref ref="F-6-1-ArcLength">Figure</xref>.
      The length, <m>h</m>,
      of the hypotenuse approximates the length,
      <m>L_{\text{slice} }</m>, of the curve between the two selected points.
      Thus,
      <me>
        L_{\text{slice} } \approx h = \sqrt{ (\Delta x)^2 + (\Delta y)^2 }
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p>
      Next we use algebra to rearrange the expression for the length of the hypotenuse
      into a form that we can integrate.
      By removing a factor of <m>(\Delta x)^2</m>,
      we find 
      <md>
        <mrow>L_{\text{slice}} &amp;\approx  \sqrt{ (\Delta x)^2 + (\Delta y)^2 }</mrow>
        <mrow>   &amp;= \sqrt{ (\Delta x)^2\left(1 + \frac{(\Delta y)^2}{(\Delta x)^2} \right)}</mrow>
        <mrow>   &amp;= \sqrt{1 + \frac{(\Delta y)^2}{(\Delta x)^2} } \cdot \Delta x</mrow>
      </md>.
    </p>

    <p>
      Then, as <m>n \to \infty</m> and <m>\Delta x \to 0</m>,
      we have that <m>\frac{\Delta y}{\Delta x} \to \frac{dy}{dx} = f'(x)</m>.
      Thus, we can say that
      <me>
        L_{\text{slice} } \approx \sqrt{1 + f'(x)^2} \Delta x
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p>
      Taking a Riemann sum of all of these slices and letting <m>n \to \infty</m>,
      we arrive at the following fact.
    </p>

    <assemblage>
      <p>
        Given a differentiable function <m>f</m> on an interval <m>[a,b]</m>,
        the total arc length,
            <idx><h>arc length</h></idx>
        <m>L</m>, along the curve
        <m>y = f(x)</m> from <m>x = a</m> to <m>x = b</m> is given by
        <me>
          L = \int_a^b \sqrt{1+f'(x)^2} \, dx
        </me>.
      </p>
    </assemblage>

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-6-1-3.xml" />
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <title>Summary</title>
    <p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <p>
            To find the area between two curves,
            we think about slicing the region into thin rectangles.
            If, for instance,
            the area of a typical rectangle on the interval <m>x = a</m> to <m>x = b</m> is given by <m>A_{\text{rect} } = (g(x) - f(x)) \Delta x</m>,
            then the exact area of the region is given by the definite integral
            <me>
              A = \int_a^b (g(x)-f(x))\, dx
            </me>.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li>
          <p>
            The shape of the region usually dictates whether we should use vertical rectangles of thickness
            <m>\Delta x</m> or horizontal rectangles of thickness <m>\Delta y</m>.
            We want the height of the rectangle given by the difference between two curves:
            if those curves are best thought of as functions of <m>y</m>,
            we use horizontal rectangles,
            whereas if those curves are best viewed as functions of <m>x</m>,
            we use vertical rectangles.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li>
          <p>
            The arc length, <m>L</m>,
            along the curve <m>y = f(x)</m> from <m>x = a</m> to <m>x = b</m> is given by
            <me>
              L = \int_a^b \sqrt{1 + f'(x)^2} \, dx
            </me>.
          </p>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <xi:include href="./exercises/ez-6-1.xml" />
</section>

