<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<!-- Copyright 2012-2018                                                   -->
<!-- Matthew Boelkins                                                      -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- This file is part of Active Calculus.                                 -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document -->
<!-- under the terms of the Creative Commons BY-SA license.  The work      -->
<!-- may be used for free by any party so long as attribution is given to  -->
<!-- the author(s), the work and its derivatives are used in the spirit of -->
<!-- "share and share alike".  All trademarks are the registered marks of  -->
<!-- their respective owners.                                              -->
<!-- **********************************************************************-->

<section xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec-1-3-derivative-pt">
  <title>The derivative of a function at a point</title>
  <objectives>
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>
          How is the average rate of change of a function on a given interval defined,
          and what does this quantity measure?
        </p>
      </li>

      <li>
        <p>
          How is the instantaneous rate of change of a function at a particular point defined?
          How is the instantaneous rate of change linked to average rate of change?
        </p>
      </li>

      <li>
        <p>
          What is the derivative of a function at a given point?
          What does this derivative value measure?
          How do we interpret the derivative value graphically?
        </p>
      </li>

      <li>
        <p>
          How are limits used formally in the computation of derivatives?
        </p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </objectives>
  <introduction>
    <p>
      The <em>instantaneous rate of change</em> of a function is an idea that sits at the foundation of calculus.
      It is a generalization of the notion of instantaneous velocity and measures how fast a particular function is changing at a given point.
      If the original function represents the position of a moving object,
      this instantaneous rate of change is precisely the velocity of the object.
      In other contexts, instantaneous rate of change could measure the number of cells added to a bacteria culture per day,
      the number of additional gallons of gasoline consumed by increasing a car's velocity one mile per hour,
      or the number of dollars added to a mortgage payment for each percentage point increase in interest rate.
      The instantaneous rate of change can also be interpreted geometrically on the function's graph,
      and this connection is fundamental to many of the main ideas in calculus.
    </p>

    <p>
      Recall that for a moving object with position function <m>s</m>,
      its average velocity on the time interval <m>t = a</m> to <m>t = a+h</m> is given by the quotient
      <me>
        AV_{[a,a+h]} = \frac{s(a+h)-s(a)}{h}
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p>
      In a similar way,
      we make the following definition for an arbitrary function <m>y = f(x)</m>.
    </p>

    <definition>
      <statement>
        <p>
          For a function <m>f</m>, the <term>average rate of change</term>
              <idx><h>average rate of change</h></idx>
          of <m>f</m> on the interval <m>[a,a+h]</m> is given by the value
          <me>
            AV_{[a,a+h]} = \frac{f(a+h)-f(a)}{h}
          </me>.
        </p>
      </statement>
    </definition>

    <p>
      Equivalently,
      if we want to consider the average rate of change of <m>f</m> on <m>[a,b]</m>,
      we compute
      <me>
        AV_{[a,b]} = \frac{f(b)-f(a)}{b-a}
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p>
      It is essential that you understand how the average rate of change of <m>f</m> on an interval is connected to its graph.
    </p>

    <xi:include href="./previews/PA-1-3.xml" />
  </introduction>

  <subsection>
    <title>The Derivative of a Function at a Point</title>
    <p>
      Just as we defined instantaneous velocity in terms of average velocity,
      we now define the instantaneous rate of change of a function at a point in terms of the average rate of change of the function <m>f</m> over related intervals.
      
      This instantaneous rate of change of <m>f</m> at <m>a</m>
          <idx><h>instantaneous rate of change</h></idx>
      is called <q>the <em>derivative</em> of <m>f</m> at <m>a</m>,</q>
      and is denoted by <m>f'(a)</m>.
    </p>

    <definition xml:id="def-derivative">
      <statement>
        <p>
          Let <m>f</m> be a function and <m>x = a</m> a value in the function's domain.
          We define the <term>derivative of <m>f</m> with respect to <m>x</m> evaluated at <m>x = a</m></term>,
              <idx><h>derivative</h><h>definition</h></idx>
          denoted <m>f'(a)</m>, by the formula
          <me>
            f'(a) = \lim_{h \to 0} \frac{f(a+h)-f(a)}{h}
          </me>,
          provided this limit exists.
        </p>
      </statement>
    </definition>

    <p>
      Aloud, we read the symbol <m>f'(a)</m> as either
      <q><m>f</m>-prime at <m>a</m></q>
      or <q>the derivative of <m>f</m> evaluated at <m>x = a</m>.</q>
      Much of the next several chapters will be devoted to understanding,
      computing,
      applying, and interpreting derivatives.
      For now, we observe the following important things.
    </p>

    <note>
      <p>
        <ul>
          <li>The derivative of <m>f</m> at the value <m>x = a</m> is defined as the limit of the average rate of change of <m>f</m> on the interval <m>[a,a+h]</m> as <m>h \to 0</m>.
          This limit may not exist,
          so not every function has a derivative at every point.</li>

          <li>We say that a function  is <em>differentiable</em>
            <idx><h>differentiable</h></idx>
        at <m>x = a</m> if it has a derivative at <m>x = a</m>.</li>

          <li>The derivative is a generalization of the instantaneous velocity of a position function:
        if <m>y = s(t)</m> is a position function of a moving body,
        <m>s'(a)</m> tells us the instantaneous velocity of the body at time <m>t=a</m>.</li>

          <li>Because the units on <m>\frac{f(a+h)-f(a)}{h}</m> are
        <q>units of <m>f(x)</m> per unit of <m>x</m>,</q>
        the derivative has these very same units.
        For instance,
        if <m>s</m> measures position in feet and <m>t</m> measures time in seconds,
        the units on <m>s'(a)</m> are feet per second.</li>

          <li>Because the quantity
        <m>\frac{f(a+h)-f(a)}{h}</m> represents the slope of the line through
        <m>(a,f(a))</m> and <m>(a+h, f(a+h))</m>,
        when we compute the derivative we are taking the limit of a collection of slopes of lines.
        Thus, the derivative itself represents the slope of a particularly important line.</li>
        </ul>
      </p>
    </note>

    <p>
      We first consider the derivative at a given value as the slope of a certain line.
    </p>

    <p>
      When we compute an instantaneous rate of change, we allow the interval <m>[a,a+h]</m> to shrink as 
      <m>h \to 0</m>.  We can think of one endpoint of the interval as <q>sliding towards</q> the other.
      In particular, provided that <m>f</m> has a derivative at <m>(a,f(a))</m>,
      the point <m>(a+h,f(a+h))</m> will approach <m>(a,f(a))</m> as <m>h \to 0</m>.
      Because the process of taking a limit is a dynamic one,
      it can be helpful to use computing technology to visualize it.
      One option is a java applet in which the user is able to control the point that is moving.
      For a helpful collection of examples,
      consider the <url href="http://gvsu.edu/s/5r">work of David Austin</url> of Grand Valley State University,
      and <url href="http://gvsu.edu/s/5s">this particularly relevant example</url>.
      For applets that have been built in Geogebra<fn>You can even consider building your own examples;
      the fantastic program Geogebra is available for <url href="http://geogebra.org">free download</url> and is easy to learn and use.</fn>,
      see <url href="http://gvsu.edu/s/5p">Marc Renault's library</url> via Shippensburg University,
      with <url href="http://gvsu.edu/s/5q">this example</url> being especially fitting for our work in this section.
    </p>

    <p>
      <xref ref="F-1-3-SecToTanSeq">Figure</xref>
      shows a sequence of figures with several different lines through the points <m>(a, f(a))</m> and
      <m>(a+h,f(a+h))</m>, generated by different values of <m>h</m>.
      These lines
      (shown in the first three figures in magenta),
      are often called <em>secant lines</em>
          <idx><h>secant line</h></idx>
      to the curve <m>y = f(x)</m>.
      A secant line to a curve is simply a line that passes through two points on the curve.
      For each such line,
      the slope of the secant line is <m>m = \frac{f(a+h) - f(a)}{h}</m>,
      where the value of <m>h</m> depends on the location of the point we choose.
      We can see in the diagram how, as <m>h \to 0</m>,
      the secant lines start to approach a single line that passes through the point <m>(a,f(a))</m>.
      If the limit of the slopes of the secant lines exists,
      we say that the resulting value is the slope of the
      <em>tangent line</em> to the curve.
      This tangent line
          <idx><h>tangent line</h></idx>
      (shown in the right-most figure in green) to the graph of
      <m>y = f(x)</m> at the point <m>(a,f(a))</m> has slope <m>m = f'(a)</m>.
    </p>

    <figure xml:id="F-1-3-SecToTanSeq">
      <caption>A sequence of secant lines approaching the tangent line to <m>f</m> at <m>(a,f(a))</m>.</caption>
      <image width="100%" source="images/1_3_SecToTanSeq" />
    </figure>

    <p>
      If the tangent line at <m>x = a</m> exists, the graph of <m>f</m> looks like a straight line when viewed up close at <m>(a,f(a))</m>.
      In <xref ref="F-1-3-SecToTan">Figure</xref>
      we combine the four graphs in <xref ref="F-1-3-SecToTanSeq">Figure</xref>
      into the single one on the left,
      and zoom in on the box centered at <m>(a,f(a))</m>
       on the right.
      Note how the tangent line sits relative to the curve <m>y = f(x)</m> at
      <m>(a,f(a))</m> and how closely it resembles the curve near <m>x = a</m>.
    </p>

    <figure xml:id="F-1-3-SecToTan">
      <caption>A sequence of secant lines approaching the tangent line to <m>f</m> at <m>(a,f(a))</m>.  At right, we zoom in on the point <m>(a,f(a))</m>.  The slope of the tangent line (in green) to <m>f</m> at <m>(a,f(a))</m> is given by <m>f'(a)</m>.</caption>
      <image width="60%" source="images/1_3_SecToTan" />
    </figure>

    <note>
      <p>
        The instantaneous rate of change of <m>f</m> with respect to <m>x</m> at <m>x = a</m>,
        <m>f'(a)</m>,
        also measures the slope of the tangent line to the curve <m>y = f(x)</m> at <m>(a,f(a))</m>.
      </p>
    </note>

    <p>
      The following example demonstrates several key ideas involving the derivative of a function.
    </p>

    <example>
      <title>Using the limit definition of the derivative</title>
      <statement>
        <p>
          For the function <m>f(x) = x - x^2</m>,
          use the limit definition of the derivative to compute <m>f'(2)</m>.
          In addition,
          discuss the meaning of this value and draw a labeled graph that supports your explanation.
        </p>
      </statement>
      <solution>
        <p>
          From the limit definition, we know that
          <me>
            f'(2) = \lim_{h \to 0} \frac{f(2+h)-f(2)}{h}
          </me>.
        </p>

        <p>
          Now we use the rule for <m>f</m>,
          and observe that <m>f(2) = 2 - 2^2 = -2</m> and <m>f(2+h) = (2+h) - (2+h)^2</m>.
          Substituting these values into the limit definition, we have that
          <me>
            f'(2) = \lim_{h \to 0} \frac{(2+h) - (2+h)^2 -  (-2)}{h}
          </me>.
        </p>

        <p>
          In order to let <m>h \to 0</m>,
          we must simplify the quotient.
          Expanding and distributing in the numerator,
          <me>
            f'(2) = \lim_{h \to 0} \frac{2+h - 4 - 4h - h^2 + 2}{h}
          </me>.
        </p>

        <p>
          Combining like terms, we have
          <me>
            f'(2) = \lim_{h \to 0} \frac{ -3h - h^2}{h}
          </me>.
        </p>

        <p>
          Next, we remove a common factor of <m>h</m> in both the numerator and denominator and find that
          <me>
            f'(2) = \lim_{h \to 0} (-3-h)
          </me>.
        </p>

        <p>
          Finally, we are able to take the limit as <m>h \to 0</m>,
          and thus conclude that <m>f'(2) = -3</m>.  We note that <m>f'(2)</m> is the instantaneous 
          rate of change of <m>f</m> at the point <m>(2,-2)</m>.
          It is also the slope of the tangent line to the graph of
          <m>y = x - x^2</m> at the point <m>(2,-2)</m>.
          <xref ref="F-1-3-Ex1">Figure</xref> shows both the function and the line 
          through <m>(2,-2)</m> with slope <m>m = f'(2) = -3</m>.
        </p>

          <figure xml:id="F-1-3-Ex1">
            <caption>The tangent line to <m>y = x - x^2</m> at the point <m>(2,-2)</m>.</caption>
            <image width = "50%" source="images/1_3_Ex1" />
          </figure>
	
      </solution>
    </example>

    <p>
      The following activities will help you explore a variety of key ideas related to derivatives.
    </p>

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-1-3-1.xml" />

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-1-3-2.xml" />

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-1-3-3.xml" />
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <title>Summary</title>
    <p>
      <ul>
        <li>The average rate of change of a function <m>f</m> on the interval <m>[a,b]</m> is <m>\frac{f(b)-f(a)}{b-a}</m>.
      The units on the average rate of change are units of <m>f(x)</m> per unit of <m>x</m>,
      and the numerical value of the average rate of change represents the slope of the secant line between the points <m>(a,f(a))</m> and
      <m>(b,f(b))</m> on the graph of <m>y = f(x)</m>.
      If we view the interval as being <m>[a,a+h]</m> instead of <m>[a,b]</m>,
      the meaning is still the same,
      but the average rate of change is now computed by <m>\frac{f(a+h)-f(a)}{h}</m>.</li>

        <li>The instantaneous rate of change with respect to <m>x</m> of a function <m>f</m> at a value <m>x = a</m> is denoted <m>f'(a)</m>
          (read <q>the derivative of <m>f</m> evaluated at <m>a</m></q>
          or <q><m>f</m>-prime at <m>a</m></q>)
          and is defined by the formula
          <me>
            f'(a) = \lim_{h \to 0} \frac{f(a+h)-f(a)}{h}
          </me>,
          provided the limit exists.
          Note particularly that the instantaneous rate of change at <m>x = a</m> is the limit of the average rate of change on <m>[a,a+h]</m> as <m>h \to 0</m>.</li>

        <li>Provided the derivative <m>f'(a)</m> exists,
          its value tells us the instantaneous rate of change of <m>f</m> with respect to <m>x</m> at <m>x = a</m>,
          which geometrically is the slope of the tangent line to the curve
          <m>y = f(x)</m> at the point <m>(a,f(a))</m>.
          We even say that <m>f'(a)</m> is the
          <q>slope of the curve</q>
          at the point <m>(a,f(a))</m>.</li>

        <li>Limits allow us to move from the rate of change over an interval to the rate of change at a single point.</li>

      </ul>
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <xi:include href="./exercises/ez-1-3.xml" />
</section>

