<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<!-- Copyright 2012-2017                                                   -->
<!-- Matthew Boelkins                                                      -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- This file is part of Active Calculus.                                 -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document -->
<!-- under the terms of the Creative Commons BY-NC-SA license.  The work   -->
<!-- may be used for free by any party so long as attribution is given to  -->
<!-- the author(s), the work and its derivatives are used in the spirit of -->
<!-- "share and share alike"; no party may sell this work or any of its    -->
<!-- derivatives for profit.  All trademarks are the registered marks of   -->
<!-- their respective owners.                                              -->
<!-- **********************************************************************-->

<section xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec-7-2-qualitative">
  <title>Qualitative behavior of solutions to DEs</title>
  <objectives>
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>
          What is a slope field?
        </p>
      </li>

      <li>
        <p>
          How can we use a slope field to obtain qualitative information about the solutions of a differential equation?
        </p>
      </li>

      <li>
        <p>
          What are stable and unstable equilibrium solutions of an autonomous differential equation?
        </p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </objectives>
  <introduction>
    <p>
      In earlier work, we have used the tangent line to the graph of a
            function <m>f</m> at a point <m>a</m> to approximate the values of <m>f</m> near <m>a</m>.
            The usefulness of this approximation is that we need to know very
            little about the function;
      armed with only the value <m>f(a)</m> and the
            derivative <m>f'(a)</m>,
      we may find the equation of the tangent line and
            the approximation
      <me>
        f(x) \approx f(a) + f'(a)(x-a)
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p>
      Remember that a first-order differential equation gives us information about the derivative of an unknown function.
      Since the derivative at a point tells us the slope of the tangent line at this point,
      a differential equation gives us crucial information about the tangent lines to the graph of a solution.
      We will use this information about the tangent lines to create a <em>slope field</em>
      for the differential equation,
      which enables us to sketch solutions to initial value problems.
      Our aim will be to understand the solutions qualitatively.
      That is, we would like to understand the basic nature of solutions,
      such as their long-range behavior,
      without precisely determining the value of a solution at a particular point.
    </p>

    <xi:include href="./previews/PA-7-2.xml" />
  </introduction>

  <subsection>
    <title>Slope fields</title>
    <idx><h>slope field</h></idx>

    <p>
      <xref ref="PA-7-2">Preview Activity</xref>
      shows that we can sketch the solution to an initial value problem if we know an appropriate collection of tangent lines.
      We can use the differential equation to find the slope of the tangent line at any point of interest,
      and hence plot such a collection.
    </p>

    <sidebyside widths="50% 44%" margins="0%">
      <p>
        Let's continue looking at the differential equation <m>\frac{dy}{dt} = t-2</m>.
        If <m>t=0</m>, this equation says that <m>dy/dt = 0-2=-2</m>.
        Note that this value holds regardless of the value of <m>y</m>.
        We will therefore sketch tangent lines for several values of <m>y</m> and <m>t=0</m> with a slope of <m>-2</m>.
      </p>

      <figure xml:id="F-7-2-field-0">
        <caption>Tangent lines at points with <m>t=0</m>.</caption>
        <image source="images/7_2_field_0" />
      </figure>
    </sidebyside>
    <sidebyside widths="50% 44%" margins="0%">
      <p>
        Let's continue in the same way:
        if <m>t=1</m>,
        the differential equation tells us that <m>dy/dt = 1-2=-1</m>,
        and this holds regardless of the value of <m>y</m>.
        We now sketch tangent lines for several values of <m>y</m> and <m>t=1</m> with a slope of <m>-1</m>.
      </p>

      <figure xml:id="F-7-2-field-1">
        <caption>Adding tangent lines at points with <m>t=1</m>.</caption>
        <image source="images/7_2_field_1" />
      </figure>
    </sidebyside>
    <sidebyside widths="50% 44%" margins="0%">
      <p>
        Similarly, we see that when <m>t=2</m>,
        <m>dy/dt = 0</m> and when <m>t=3</m>, <m>dy/dt=1</m>.
        We may therefore add to our growing collection of tangent line plots to achieve the next figure.
      </p>

      <figure xml:id="F-7-2-field-2">
        <caption>Adding tangent lines at points with <m>t=2</m> and <m>t=3</m>.</caption>
        <image source="images/7_2_field_3" />
      </figure>
    </sidebyside>
    <sidebyside widths="50% 44%" margins="0%">
      <p>
        In this figure,
        we begin to see the solutions to the differential equation emerge.
        However, for the sake of clarity,
        we add more tangent lines to provide the even more complete picture shown below.
      </p>

      <figure xml:id="F-7-2-field-23">
        <caption>A completed slope field.</caption>
        <image source="images/7_2_field_23a" />
      </figure>
    </sidebyside>
    <sidebyside widths="50% 44%" margins="0%">
      <p>
        This figure is called a <em>slope field</em>
            <idx><h>slope field</h></idx>
        for the differential equation.  It
        allows us to sketch solutions just as we did in the preview activity.
        Here, we will begin with the initial value
        <m>y(0) = 1</m> and start sketching the solution by following the tangent line,
        as shown in the <xref ref="F-7-2-field-30">Figure</xref>.
      </p>

      <figure xml:id="F-7-2-field-30">
        <caption>Beginning to sketch the solution function.</caption>
        <image source="images/7_2_field_30" />
      </figure>
    </sidebyside>
    <p>
      We continue as follows:
      whenever the solution passes through a point at which a tangent line is drawn,
      that line is tangent to the solution.
      This principle leads us to the following sequence of images.
    </p>

    <sbsgroup>

    <sidebyside widths="47% 47%" margins="0%">
      <!--

      <figure xml:id="F-7-2-field-31">
        -->
        <image source="images/7_2_field_31" />
        <!--
      </figure>

      -->
         <!--

      <figure xml:id="F-7-2-field-32">
        -->
        <image source="images/7_2_field_32" />
        <!--
      </figure>

      -->
    </sidebyside>
    <sidebyside widths="47% 47%" margins="0%">
      <figure xml:id="F-7-2-field-33">
        <caption>The third image in a sequence that show how to sketch the IVP solution that satisfies <m>y(0)=1</m>.</caption>
        <image source="images/7_2_field_33" />
      </figure>

      <figure xml:id="F-7-2-field-4">
        <caption>Different solutions to <m>\frac{dy}{dt} = t-2</m> that correspond to different initial values.</caption>
        <image source="images/7_2_field_4" />
      </figure>
    </sidebyside>
    </sbsgroup>

    <p>
      In fact, we can draw solutions for any initial value.
      <xref ref="F-7-2-field-4">Figure</xref> shows solutions for several different initial values for <m>y(0)</m>.
    </p>

    <p>
      Just as we did for the equation <m>\frac{dy}{dt} = t-2</m>,
      we can construct a slope field for any differential equation of interest.
      The slope field provides us with visual information about how we expect solutions to the differential equation to behave.
    </p>

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-7-2-1.xml" />
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <title>Equilibrium solutions and stability</title>
    <p>
      As our work in <xref ref="act-7-2-1">Activity</xref> demonstrates,
      first-order autonomous equations may have solutions that are constant.
      These are quite easy to detect by inspecting the differential equation <m>dy/dt = f(y)</m>:
      constant solutions necessarily have a zero derivative, so <m>dy/dt = 0 = f(y)</m>.
    </p>

    <p>
      For example, in <xref ref="act-7-2-1">Activity</xref>,
      we considered the equation <m>\frac{dy}{dt} = f(y)=-\frac12(y-4)</m>.
      Constant solutions are found by setting <m>f(y) = -\frac12(y-4) = 0</m>,
      which we immediately see implies that <m>y = 4</m>.
    </p>

    <p>
      Values of <m>y</m> for which
      <m>f(y) = 0</m> in an autonomous differential equation
      <m>\frac{dy}{dt} = f(y)</m> are called 
      <em>equilibrium solutions</em>
          <idx><h>equilibrium solution</h></idx>
      of the differential equation.
    </p>

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-7-2-2.xml" />
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <title>Summary</title>
    <p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <p>
            A slope field is a plot created by graphing the tangent lines of many different solutions to a differential equation.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li>
          <p>
            Once we have a slope field,
            we may sketch the graph of solutions by drawing a curve that is always tangent to the lines in the slope field.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li>
          <p>
            Autonomous differential equations sometimes have constant solutions that we call equilibrium solutions.
            These may be classified as stable or unstable,
            depending on the behavior of nearby solutions.
          </p>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <xi:include href="./exercises/ez-7-2.xml" />
</section>

