<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<!-- Copyright 2012-2018                                                   -->
<!-- Matthew Boelkins                                                      -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- This file is part of Active Calculus.                                 -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document -->
<!-- under the terms of the Creative Commons BY-SA license.  The work      -->
<!-- may be used for free by any party so long as attribution is given to  -->
<!-- the author(s), the work and its derivatives are used in the spirit of -->
<!-- "share and share alike".  All trademarks are the registered marks of  -->
<!-- their respective owners.                                              -->
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<section xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec-4-3-definite-integral" permid="Oja">
  <title>The Definite Integral</title>
  <objectives permid="jRe">
    <ul permid="wfw">
      <li permid="ItO">
        <p permid="ZrZ">
          How does increasing the number of subintervals affect the accuracy of the approximation generated by a Riemann sum?
        </p>
      </li>

      <li permid="oAX">
        <p permid="Fzi">
          What is the definition of the definite integral of a function <m>f</m> over the interval <m>[a,b]</m>?
        </p>
      </li>

      <li permid="UIg">
        <p permid="lGr">
          What does the definite integral measure exactly,
          and what are some of the key properties of the definite integral?
        </p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </objectives>

  <introduction permid="PYn">
    <p permid="Wxt">
      In <xref ref="F-4-3-IncreaseN">Figure</xref>,
      we see evidence that increasing the number of rectangles in a Riemann sum improves the accuracy of the approximation of the net signed area bounded by the given function.
    </p>

    <figure xml:id="F-4-3-IncreaseN" permid="iLL">
      <caption>At left and center, two left Riemann sums for a function <m>f</m> that is sometimes negative; at right, the exact areas bounded by <m>f</m> on the interval <m>[a,d]</m>.</caption>
      <image width="100%" source="images/4_2_NegF" />
    </figure>

    <p permid="CEC">
      We therefore explore the natural idea of allowing the number of rectangles to increase without bound.
      In an effort to compute the exact net signed area we also consider the differences among left, right,
      and middle Riemann sums and the different results they generate as the value of <m>n</m> increases.
      We begin with functions that are exclusively positive on the interval under consideration.
    </p>

    <xi:include href="./previews/PA-4-3.xml" />
  </introduction>

  <subsection permid="uqj">
    <title>The definition of the definite integral</title>
    <idx><h>definite integral</h><h>definition</h></idx>

    <p permid="OSU">
      In <xref ref="PA-4-3">Preview Activity</xref>,
      we saw that as the number of rectangles got larger and larger,
      the values of <m>L_n</m>, <m>M_n</m>,
      and <m>R_n</m> all grew closer and closer to the same value.
      It turns out that this occurs for any continuous function on an interval <m>[a,b]</m>,
      and also for a Riemann sum using any point
      <m>x_{i+1}^*</m> in the interval <m>[x_i, x_{i+1}]</m>.
      Thus, as we let <m>n \to \infty</m>,
      it doesn't really matter where we choose to evaluate the function within a given subinterval, because
      <me permid="MIi">
        \lim_{n \to \infty} L_n = \lim_{n \to \infty} R_n = \lim_{n \to \infty} M_n = \lim_{n \to \infty} \sum_{i=1}^{n} f(x_i^*) \Delta x
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p permid="vad">
      That these limits always exist
      (and share the same value)
      when <m>f</m> is continuous<fn>
      It turns out that a function need not be continuous in order to have a definite integral.
      For our purposes,
      we assume that the functions we consider are continuous on the interval(s) of interest.
      It is straightforward to see that any function that is piecewise continuous on an interval of interest will also have a well-defined definite integral.
      </fn> allows us to make the following definition.
    </p>

    <definition xml:id="D-4-3-DefInt" permid="DJV">
      <idx><h>definite integral</h><h>definition</h></idx>
      <statement>
        <p permid="qqk">
          The <term>definite integral</term>
          of a continuous function <m>f</m> on the interval <m>[a,b]</m>,
          denoted <m>\int_a^b f(x) \, dx</m>,
          is the real number given by
          <me permid="sPr">
            \int_a^b f(x) \, dx = \lim_{n \to \infty} \sum_{i=1}^{n} f(x_i^*) \Delta x
          </me>,
          where <m>\Delta x = \frac{b-a}{n}</m>,
          <m>x_i = a + i\Delta x</m>
          (for <m>i = 0, \ldots, n</m>),
          and <m>x_i^*</m> satisfies
          <m>x_{i-1} \le x_i^* \le x_i</m>
          (for <m>i = 1, \ldots, n</m>).
        </p>
      </statement>
    </definition>

    <p permid="bhm">
      We call the symbol <m>\int</m> the
      <em>integral sign</em>,
          <idx><h>integral sign</h></idx>
      the values <m>a</m> and <m>b</m> the
      <em>limits of integration</em>, 
          <idx><h>limits of integration</h></idx>
      and the function <m>f</m> the <em>integrand</em>.
          <idx><h>integrand</h></idx>
      The process of determining the real number <m>\int_a^b f(x) \, dx</m> is called
      <em>evaluating the definite integral</em>.
      While there are several different interpretations of the definite integral,
      for now the most important is that
      <m>\int_a^b f(x) \, dx</m> measures the net signed area bounded by
      <m>y = f(x)</m> and the <m>x</m>-axis on the interval <m>[a,b]</m>.
    </p>
    <!--<sidebyside widths="47% 47%" margins="0%" valign="middle">-->
    <p permid="Hov">
      For example,
      if <m>f</m> is the function pictured in <xref ref="F-4-3-DefIntInterp">Figure</xref>,
      and <m>A_1</m>,
      <m>A_2</m>,
      and <m>A_3</m> are the exact areas bounded by <m>f</m> and the <m>x</m>-axis on the respective intervals <m>[a,b]</m>,
      <m>[b,c]</m>, and <m>[c,d]</m>, then
      <md permid="YWA">
        <mrow>\int_a^b f(x) \, dx = A_1, \ \int_b^c f(x) \, dx = -A_2,</mrow>
        <mrow>\int_c^d f(x) \, dx = A_3,</mrow>
        <mrow>\text{ and } \int_a^d f(x) \, dx = A_1 - A_2 + A_3</mrow>
      </md>.
    </p>

    <figure xml:id="F-4-3-DefIntInterp" permid="sfx">
      <caption>A continuous function <m>f</m> on the interval <m>[a,d]</m>.</caption>
      <image width="47%" source="images/4_3_DefIntInterp" />
    </figure>
  <!--</sidebyside>-->
    <p permid="nvE">
      We can also use definite integrals to express the change in position and the distance traveled by a moving object.
      If <m>v</m> is a velocity function on an interval <m>[a,b]</m>,
      then the change in position of the object,
      <m>s(b) - s(a)</m>, is given by
      <me permid="FdJ">
        s(b) - s(a) = \int_a^b v(t) \, dt
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p permid="TCN">
      If the velocity function is nonnegative on <m>[a,b]</m>,
      then <m>\int_a^b v(t) \,dt</m> tells us the distance the object traveled.
      If the velocity is sometimes negative on <m>[a,b]</m>,
      we can use definite integrals to find the areas bounded by the function on each interval where <m>v</m> does not change sign,
      and the sum of these areas will tell us the distance the object traveled.
    </p>

    <p permid="zJW">
      To compute the value of a definite integral from the definition,
      we have to take the limit of a sum.
      While this is possible to do in select circumstances,
      it is also tedious and time-consuming,
      and does not offer much additional insight into the meaning or interpretation of the definite integral.
      Instead, in <xref ref="sec-4-4-FTC">Section</xref>,
      we will learn the Fundamental Theorem of Calculus,
      which provides a shortcut for evaluating a large class of definite integrals.
      This will enable us to determine the exact net signed area bounded by a continuous function and the <m>x</m>-axis in many circumstances.
    </p>

    <p permid="fRf">
      For now, our goal is to understand the meaning and properties of the definite integral,
      rather than to compute its value.
      To do this, we will rely on the net signed area interpretation of the definite integral.
      So we will use as examples curves that produce regions whose areas we can compute exactly through area formulas.
      We can thus compute the exact value of the corresponding integral.
    </p>
    <!--<sidebyside widths="47% 47%" margins="0%" valign="middle">-->
    <p permid="LYo">
      For instance,
      if we wish to evaluate the definite integral <m>\int_1^4 (2x+1) \, dx</m>,
      we observe that the region bounded by this function and the <m>x</m>-axis is the trapezoid shown in <xref ref="F-4-3-TrapArea">Figure</xref>.
      By the formula for the area of a trapezoid,
      <m>A = \frac{1}{2}(3+9) \cdot 3 = 18</m>, so
      <me permid="lkS">
        \int_1^4 (2x+1) \, dx = 18
      </me>.
    </p>

    <figure xml:id="F-4-3-TrapArea" permid="YmG">
      <caption>The area bounded by <m>f(x)=2x+1</m> and the <m>x</m>-axis on the interval <m>[1,4]</m>.</caption>
      <image width="47%" source="images/4_3_TrapArea" />
    </figure>
<!--</sidebyside>-->
    <xi:include href="./activities/act-4-3-1.xml" />
  </subsection>

  <subsection permid="axs">
    <title>Some properties of the definite integral</title>
    <p permid="EtP">
      Regarding the definite integral of a function <m>f</m> over an interval <m>[a,b]</m> as the net signed area bounded by <m>f</m> and the <m>x</m>-axis,
      we discover several standard properties of the definite integral.
      It is helpful to remember that the definite integral is defined in terms of Riemann sums,
      which consist of the areas of rectangles.
    </p>

    <p permid="kAY">
      For any real number <m>a</m> and the definite integral
      <m>\int_a^a f(x) \, dx</m>
      it is evident that no area is enclosed,
      because the interval begins and ends with the same point.
      Hence,
    </p>

    <assemblage permid="SST">
      <p permid="QIh">
        If <m>f</m> is a continuous function and <m>a</m> is a real number,
        then <m>\int_a^a f(x) \,dx = 0</m>.
      </p>
    </assemblage>
<!--<sidebyside widths="47% 47%" margins="0%">-->
    <p permid="wPq">
      Next, we consider the result of subdividing the interval of integration.
      In <xref ref="F-4-3-AdditiveProp">Figure</xref>, we see that
      <md permid="Rsb">
        <mrow>\int_a^b f(x) \, dx = A_1, \ \int_b^c f(x) \, dx = A_2,</mrow>
        <mrow>\text{and }\int_a^c f(x) \, dx = A_1 + A_2</mrow>
      </md>,
      which illustrates the following general rule.
    </p>

    <figure xml:id="F-4-3-AdditiveProp" permid="eLM">
      <caption>The area bounded by <m>y=f(x)</m> on the interval <m>[a,c]</m>.</caption>
      <image width="47%" source="images/4_3_AdditiveProp" />
    </figure>
<!--</sidebyside>-->
    <assemblage permid="zac">
      <p permid="cWz">
        If <m>f</m> is a continuous function and <m>a</m>, <m>b</m>,
        and <m>c</m> are real numbers, then
        <me permid="xzk">
          \int_a^c f(x) \,dx = \int_a^b f(x) \,dx + \int_b^c f(x) \,dx
        </me>.
      </p>
    </assemblage>

    <p permid="JdI">
      While this rule is easy to see if <m>a \lt b \lt c</m>,
      it in fact holds in general for any values of <m>a</m>,
      <m>b</m>,
      and <m>c</m>.
      Another property of the definite integral states that if we reverse the order of the limits of integration,
      we change the sign of the integral's value.
    </p>

    <assemblage permid="fhl">
      <p permid="pkR">
        If <m>f</m> is a continuous function and <m>a</m> and <m>b</m> are real numbers, then
        <me permid="dGt">
          \int_b^a f(x) \,dx = -\int_a^b f(x) \,dx
        </me>.
      </p>
    </assemblage>

    <p permid="Vsa">
      This result makes sense because if we integrate from <m>a</m> to <m>b</m>,
      then in the defining Riemann sum we set <m>\Delta x = \frac{b-a}{n}</m>,
      while if we integrate from <m>b</m> to <m>a</m>, we have
      <m>\Delta x = \frac{a-b}{n} = -\frac{b-a}{n}</m>,
      and this is the only change in the sum used to define the integral.
    </p>

    <p permid="Bzj">
      There are two additional useful properties of the definite integral.
      When we worked with derivative rules in <xref ref="C-2">Chapter</xref>,
      we formulated the Constant Multiple Rule and the Sum Rule.
      Recall that the Constant Multiple Rule says that if <m>f</m> is a differentiable function and <m>k</m> is a constant, then
      <me permid="JNC">
        \frac{d}{dx} [kf(x)] = kf'(x)
      </me>,
      and the Sum Rule says that if <m>f</m> and <m>g</m> are differentiable functions, then
      <me permid="pUL">
        \frac{d}{dx}[f(x) + g(x)] = f'(x) + g'(x)
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p permid="hGs">
      These rules are useful because they allow to deal individually with the simplest parts of certain functions by taking advantage of addition and multiplying by a constant.
      In other words,
      the process of taking the derivative respects addition and multiplying by constants in the simplest possible way.
    </p>

    <p permid="NNB">
      It turns out that similar rules hold for the definite integral.
      First, let's consider the functions pictured in <xref ref="F-4-3-ConstMult">Figure</xref>.
    </p>

    <figure xml:id="F-4-3-ConstMult" permid="KSV">
      <caption>The areas bounded by <m>y = f(x)</m> and <m>y = 2f(x)</m> on <m>[a,b]</m>.</caption>
      <image width="100%" source="images/4_3_ConstMult" />
    </figure>

    <p permid="tUK">
      Because multiplying the function by 2 doubles its height at every <m>x</m>-value,
      we see that the height of each rectangle in a left Riemann sum is doubled,
      <m>f(x_i)</m> for the original function,
      versus <m>2f(x_i)</m> in the doubled function.
      For the areas <m>A</m> and <m>B</m>,
      it follows <m>B = 2A</m>.
      As this is true
      regardless of the value of <m>n</m> or the type of sum we use,
      we see that in the limit,
      the area of the red region bounded by
      <m>y = 2f(x)</m> will be twice the area of the blue region bounded by <m>y = f(x)</m>.
      As there is nothing special about the value <m>2</m> compared to an arbitrary constant <m>k</m>,
      the following general principle holds.
    </p>

    <assemblage permid="Lou">
      <title>Constant Multiple Rule</title>
      <idx><h>definite integral</h><h>constant multiple rule</h></idx>

      <p permid="abT">
        If <m>f</m> is a continuous function and <m>k</m> is any real number, then
        <me permid="WbU">
          \int_a^b k \cdot f(x) \,dx = k \int_a^b f(x) \,dx
        </me>.
      </p>
    </assemblage>

    <p permid="Gjc">
      We see a similar situation with the sum of two functions <m>f</m> and <m>g</m>.
    </p>

    <figure xml:id="F-4-3-Sum" permid="rae">
      <caption>The areas bounded by <m>y = f(x)</m> and <m>y = g(x)</m> on <m>[a,b]</m>, as well as the area bounded by <m>y = f(x) + g(x)</m>.</caption>
      <image width="100%" source="images/4_3_Sum" />
    </figure>

    <p permid="mql">
      If we take the sum of two functions <m>f</m> and <m>g</m>
      at every point in the interval,
      the height of the function <m>f+g</m> is given by <m>(f+g)(x_i) = f(x_i) + g(x_i)</m>.
      Hence, for the pictured rectangles with areas <m>A</m>,
      <m>B</m>,
      and <m>C</m>,
      it follows that <m>C = A + B</m>.
      Because this will occur for every such rectangle,
      in the limit the area of the gray region will be the sum of the areas of the blue and red regions.
      In terms of definite integrals,
      we have the following general rule.
    </p>

    <assemblage permid="rvD">
      <title>Sum Rule</title>
      <idx><h>definite integral</h><h>sum rule</h></idx>

      <p permid="Sxu">
        If <m>f</m> and <m>g</m> are continuous functions, then
        <me permid="Cjd">
          \int_a^b [f(x) + g(x)] \,dx = \int_a^b f(x) \,dx + \int_a^b g(x) \,dx
        </me>.
      </p>
    </assemblage>

    <p permid="yED">
      The Constant Multiple and Sum Rules can be combined to say that for any continuous functions <m>f</m> and <m>g</m> and any constants <m>c</m> and <m>k</m>,
      <me permid="iqm">
        \int_a^b [c f(x) \pm k g(x)] \,dx = c \int_a^b f(x) \,dx \pm k \int_a^b g(x) \,dx
      </me>.
    </p>

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-4-3-2.xml" />
  </subsection>

  <subsection permid="GEB">
    <title>How the definite integral is connected to a function's average value</title>
    <idx><h>average value of a function</h></idx>

    <p permid="Xhn">
      One of the most valuable applications of the definite integral is that it provides a way to discuss the average value of a function,
      even for a function that takes on infinitely many values.
      Recall that if we wish to take the average of <m>n</m> numbers <m>y_1</m>,
      <m>y_2</m>, <m>\ldots</m>, <m>y_n</m>, we compute
      <me permid="Oxv">
        AVG  = \frac{y_1 + y_2 + \cdots + y_n}{n}
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p permid="Dow">
      Since integrals arise from Riemann sums in which we add <m>n</m> values of a function,
      it should not be surprising that evaluating an integral is similar to averaging the output values of a function.
      Consider, for instance,
      the right Riemann sum <m>R_n</m> of a function <m>f</m>,
      which is given by
      <me permid="uEE">
        R_n = f(x_1) \Delta x + f(x_2) \Delta x + \cdots + f(x_n) \Delta x = (f(x_1) + f(x_2) + \cdots + f(x_n))\Delta x
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p permid="jvF">
      Since <m>\Delta x = \frac{b-a}{n}</m>, we can thus write
      <mdn permid="aLN">
        <mrow number="no">R_n =\mathstrut \amp (f(x_1) + f(x_2) + \cdots + f(x_n))\cdot \frac{b-a}{n}</mrow>
        <mrow xml:id="E-RAvg">=\mathstrut \amp (b-a) \frac{f(x_1) + f(x_2) + \cdots + f(x_n)}{n}</mrow>
      </mdn>.
    </p>

    <p permid="PCO">
      We see that the right Riemann sum with <m>n</m> subintervals is just the length of the interval <m>(b-a)</m> times the average of the <m>n</m> function values found at the right endpoints.
      And just as with our efforts to compute area,
      the larger the value of <m>n</m> we use,
      the more accurate our average will be.
      Indeed, we will define the average value of <m>f</m> on <m>[a,b]</m> to be
      <me permid="GSW">
        f_{\operatorname{AVG} [a,b]} = \lim_{n \to \infty} \frac{f(x_1) + f(x_2) + \cdots + f(x_n)}{n}
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p permid="vJX">
      But we also know that for any continuous function <m>f</m> on <m>[a,b]</m>,
      taking the limit of a Riemann sum leads precisely to the definite integral.
      That is, <m>\lim_{n \to \infty} R_n = \int_a^b f(x) \, dx</m>,
      and thus taking the limit as
      <m>n \to \infty</m> in <xref ref="E-RAvg">Equation</xref>,
      we have that
      <men xml:id="E-RAvg2" permid="naf">
        \int_a^b f(x) \, dx = (b-a) \cdot f_{\operatorname{AVG} [a,b]}
      </men>.
    </p>

    <p permid="bRg">
      Solving Equation<nbsp /><xref ref="E-RAvg2" /> for <m>f_{\operatorname{AVG} [a,b]}</m>,
      we have the following general principle.
    </p>

    <assemblage xml:id="average-value" permid="XCM">
      <title>Average value of a function</title>
      <p permid="HYp">
            <idx><h>average value</h></idx>
        If <m>f</m> is a continuous function on <m>[a,b]</m>,
        then its average value on <m>[a,b]</m> is given by the formula
        <me permid="Tho">
          f_{\operatorname{AVG} [a,b]} = \frac{1}{b-a} \cdot \int_a^b f(x) \, dx
        </me>.
      </p>
    </assemblage>

    <p permid="ofy">
      Equation<nbsp /><xref ref="E-RAvg2" /> tells us another way to interpret the definite integral:
      the definite integral of a function <m>f</m> from <m>a</m> to <m>b</m> is the length of the interval <m>(b-a)</m> times the average value of the function on the interval.
      In addition,
      when the function <m>f</m> is nonnegative on <m>[a,b]</m>, Equation<nbsp /><xref ref="E-RAvg2" /> has a natural visual interpretation.
    </p>

    <figure xml:id="F-4-3-AvgVal" permid="AtQ">
      <caption>A function <m>y = f(x)</m>, the area it bounds, and its average value on <m>[a,b]</m>.</caption>
      <image width="100%" source="images/4_3_AvgVal" />
    </figure>

    <p permid="UmH">
      Consider <xref ref="F-4-3-AvgVal">Figure</xref>,
      where we see at left the shaded region whose area is <m>\int_a^b f(x) \, dx</m>,
      at center the shaded rectangle whose dimensions are <m>(b-a)</m> by <m>f_{\operatorname{AVG} [a,b]}</m>,
      and at right these two figures superimposed.
      Note that in dark green we show the horizontal line <m>y = f_{\operatorname{AVG} [a,b]}</m>.
      Thus, the area of the green rectangle is given by <m>(b-a) \cdot f_{\operatorname{AVG} [a,b]}</m>,
      which is precisely the value of <m>\int_a^b f(x) \, dx</m>.
      The area of the blue region in the left figure is the same as the area of the green rectangle in the center figure.
      We can also observe that the areas <m>A_1</m> and <m>A_2</m> in the rightmost figure appear to be equal.
      Thus, knowing the average value of a function enables us to construct a rectangle whose area is the same as the value of the definite integral of the function on the interval.
      The java applet<fn>
      David Austin,
      <url href="http://gvsu.edu/s/5r">http://gvsu.edu/s/5r</url>.
      </fn> at
      <url href="http://gvsu.edu/s/az">http://gvsu.edu/s/az</url>
      provides an opportunity to explore how the average value of the function changes as the interval changes,
      through an image similar to that found in <xref ref="F-4-3-AvgVal">Figure</xref>.
    </p>

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-4-3-3.xml" />
  </subsection>

  <subsection permid="mLK">
    <title>Summary</title>
    <p permid="gAZ">
      <ul permid="cmF">
        <li permid="APp">
          <p permid="RNA">
            Any Riemann sum of a continuous function <m>f</m> on an interval <m>[a,b]</m> provides an estimate of the net signed area bounded by the function and the horizontal axis on the interval.
            Increasing the number of subintervals in the Riemann sum improves the accuracy of this estimate,
            and letting the number of subintervals increase without bound results in the values of the corresponding Riemann sums approaching the exact value of the enclosed net signed area.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="gWy">
          <p permid="xUJ">
            When we take the limit of Riemann sums,
            we arrive at what we call the definite integral of <m>f</m> over the interval <m>[a,b]</m>.
            In particular, the symbol
            <m>\int_a^b f(x) \, dx</m> denotes the definite integral of <m>f</m> over <m>[a,b]</m>,
            and this quantity is defined by the equation
            <me permid="zox">
              \int_a^b f(x) \, dx = \lim_{n \to \infty} \sum_{i=1}^{n} f(x_i^*) \Delta x
            </me>,
            where <m>\Delta x = \frac{b-a}{n}</m>,
            <m>x_i = a + i\Delta x</m>
            (for <m>i = 0, \ldots, n</m>),
            and <m>x_i^*</m> satisfies
            <m>x_{i-1} \le x_i^* \le x_i</m>
            (for <m>i = 1, \ldots, n</m>).
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="NdH">
          <p permid="ebS">
            The definite integral
            <m>\int_a^b f(x) \,dx</m> measures the exact net signed area bounded by <m>f</m> and the horizontal axis on <m>[a,b]</m>;
            in addition,
            the value of the definite integral is related to what we call the average value of the function on <m>[a,b]</m>:
            <m>f_{\text{AVG} [a,b]} = \frac{1}{b-a} \cdot \int_a^b f(x) \, dx</m>.
            In the setting where we consider the integral of a velocity function <m>v</m>,
            <m>\int_a^b v(t) \,dt</m> measures the exact change in position of the moving object on <m>[a,b]</m>;
            when <m>v</m> is nonnegative,
            <m>\int_a^b v(t) \,dt</m> is the object's distance traveled on <m>[a,b]</m>.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="tkQ">
          <p permid="Kjb">
            The definite integral is a sophisticated sum,
            and thus has some of the same natural properties that finite sums have.
            Perhaps most important of these is how the definite integral respects sums and constant multiples of functions,
            which can be summarized by the rule
            <me permid="fvG">
              \int_a^b [c f(x) \pm k g(x)] \,dx = c \int_a^b f(x) \,dx \pm k \int_a^b g(x) \,dx
            </me>
            where <m>f</m> and <m>g</m> are continuous functions on <m>[a,b]</m> and <m>c</m> and <m>k</m> are arbitrary constants.
          </p>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <xi:include href="./exercises/ez-4-3.xml" />
</section>

