<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<section xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec-4-2-Riemann">
  <title>Riemann Sums</title>
  <introduction>
    <objectives>
      <ul>
        <li><p>How can we use a Riemann sum to estimate the area between a given curve and the horizontal axis over a particular interval?</p></li>

        <li><p>What are the differences among left, right, middle, and random Riemann sums?</p></li>

        <li><p>How can we write Riemann sums in an abbreviated form??</p></li>
      </ul>
    </objectives>
    <p>In <xref ref="sec-4-1-velocity-distance">Section</xref>, we learned that if we have a moving object with velocity function <m>v</m>, whenever <m>v(t)</m> is positive, the area between <m>y = v(t)</m> and the <m>t</m>-axis over a given time interval tells us the distance traveled by the object over that time period; in addition, if <m>v(t)</m> is sometimes negative and we view the area of any region below the <m>t</m>-axis as having an associated negative sign, then the sum of these signed areas over a given interval tells us the moving object's change in position over the time interval.</p>

    <figure xml:id="F-4-2-Intro" >
      <caption>A velocity function that is sometimes negative.</caption>
      <image width="50%" source="images/4_2_Intro" />
    </figure>

    <p>For instance, for the velocity function given in <xref ref="F-4-2-Intro">Figure</xref>, if the areas of shaded regions are <m>A_1</m>, <m>A_2</m>, and <m>A_3</m> as labeled, then the total distance <m>D</m> traveled by the moving object on <m>[a,b]</m> is
      <me>
        D = A_1 + A_2 + A_3,
      </me>
      while the total change in the object's position on <m>[a,b]</m> is
      <me>
        s(b) - s(a) = A_1 - A_2 + A_3.
      </me>
    </p>

    <p>Because the motion is in the negative direction on the interval where <m>v(t) \lt  0</m>, we subtract <m>A_2</m> when determining the object's total change in position.</p>

    <p>Of course, finding <m>D</m> and <m>s(b)-s(a)</m> for the situation given in <xref ref="F-4-2-Intro">Figure</xref> presumes that we can actually find the areas represented by <m>A_1</m>, <m>A_2</m>, and <m>A_3</m>. In most of our work in <xref ref="sec-4-1-velocity-distance">Section</xref>, such as in <xref ref="act-4-1-2">Activities</xref> and <xref ref="act-4-1-3"></xref>, we worked with velocity functions that were either constant or linear, so that by finding the areas of rectangles and triangles, we could find the area bounded by the velocity function and the horizontal axis exactly. But when the curve that bounds a region is not one for which we have a known formula for area, we are unable to find this area exactly. Indeed, this is one of our biggest goals in <xref ref="C-4">Chapter</xref>: to learn how to find the exact area bounded between a curve and the horizontal axis for as many different types of functions as possible.</p>

    <p>To begin, we expand on the ideas in <xref ref="act-4-1-1">Activity</xref>, where we encountered a nonlinear velocity function and approximated the area under the curve using four and eight rectangles, respectively. In the following preview activity, we focus on three different options for deciding how to find the heights of the rectangles we will use.</p>

    <xi:include href="./previews/PA-4-2.xml" />

  </introduction>
  

<!-- <xi:include href="./activities/act-1-1-1.xml" /> -->
<!-- <xi:include href="./exercises/ez-1-1.xml" /> -->

</section>