<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<!-- Copyright 2012-2019                                                   -->
<!-- Matthew Boelkins                                                      -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- This file is part of Active Calculus.                                 -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document -->
<!-- under the terms of the Creative Commons BY-SA license.  The work      -->
<!-- may be used for free by any party so long as attribution is given to  -->
<!-- the author(s), the work and its derivatives are used in the spirit of -->
<!-- "share and share alike".  All trademarks are the registered marks of  -->
<!-- their respective owners.                                              -->
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<section xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec-5-1-antid-graphs" permid="mjh">
  <title>Constructing Accurate Graphs of Antiderivatives</title>
  <objectives permid="Dhs">
    <ul permid="vCT">
      <li permid="HRl">
        <p permid="sIn">
          Given the graph of a function's derivative,
          how can we construct a completely accurate graph of the original function?
        </p>
      </li>

      <li permid="nYu">
        <p permid="YPw">
          How many antiderivatives does a given function have?
          What do those antiderivatives all have in common?
        </p>
      </li>

      <li permid="UfD">
        <p permid="EWF">
          Given a function <m>f</m>,
          how does the rule <m>A(x) = \int_0^x f(t) \, dt</m> define a new function <m>A</m>?
        </p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </objectives>

  <introduction permid="joB">
    <p permid="pNH">
      A recurring theme in our discussion of differential calculus has been the question
      <q>Given information about the derivative of an unknown function <m>f</m>,
      how much information can we obtain about <m>f</m> itself?</q>
      In <xref ref="act-1-8-2">Activity</xref>,
      the graph of <m>y = f'(x)</m> was known
      (along with the value of <m>f</m> at a single point)
      and we endeavored to sketch a possible graph of <m>f</m> near the known point.
      In <xref ref="Ex-f-from-f-prime">Example</xref>
      <mdash /> we investigated how the first derivative test enables us to use information about <m>f'</m> to determine where the original function <m>f</m> is increasing and decreasing,
      as well as where <m>f</m> has relative extreme values.
      If we know a formula or graph of <m>f'</m>,
      by computing <m>f''</m> we can find where the original function <m>f</m> is concave up and concave down.
      Thus, knowing <m>f'</m> and <m>f''</m> enables us to understand the shape of the graph of <m>f</m>.
    </p>

    <p permid="VUQ">
      We returned to this question in even more detail in <xref ref="sec-4-1-velocity-distance">Section</xref>.
      In that setting,
      we knew the instantaneous velocity of a moving object and worked to determine as much as possible about the object's position function.
      We found connections between the net signed area under the velocity function and the corresponding change in position of the function, and 
      the Total Change Theorem further illuminated these connections between <m>f'</m> and <m>f</m>,
      showing that the total change in the value of <m>f</m> over an interval <m>[a,b]</m> is determined by the net signed area bounded by <m>f'</m> and the <m>x</m>-axis on the same interval.
    </p>

    <p permid="CbZ">
      In what follows,
      we explore the situation where we possess an accurate graph of the derivative function along with a single value of the function <m>f</m>.
      From that information,
      we'd like to determine a graph of <m>f</m> that shows where <m>f</m> is increasing,
      decreasing, concave up, and concave down,
      and also provides an accurate function value at any point.
    </p>

    <xi:include href="./previews/PA-5-1.xml" />
  </introduction>

  <subsection permid="Sqq">
    <title>Constructing the graph of an antiderivative</title>
    <idx><h>antiderivative</h><h>graph</h></idx>

    <p permid="iji">
      <xref ref="PA-5-1">Preview Activity</xref>
      demonstrates that when we can find the exact area under the graph of a function on any given interval,
      it is possible to construct a graph of the function's antiderivative.
      That is, we can find a function whose derivative is given.
      We can now determine not only the overall shape of the antiderivative graph,
      but also the actual <em>height</em>
      of the graph at any point of interest.
    </p>

    <p permid="Oqr">
      This is a consequence of the Fundamental Theorem of Calculus:
      if we know a function <m>f</m> and the value of the antiderivative <m>F</m> at some starting point <m>a</m>, 
      we can determine the value of <m>F(b)</m> via the definite integral.
      Since <m>F(b) - F(a) = \int_a^b f(x) \, dx</m>, it follows that
      <men xml:id="E-FTCTCT" permid="AWG">
        F(b) = F(a) + \int_a^b f(x) \, dx
      </men>.
    </p>

    <p permid="uxA">
      We can also interpret the equation
      <m>F(b) - F(a) = \int_a^b f(x) \, dx</m> in terms of the graphs of <m>f</m> and <m>F</m> as follows.
      On an interval <m>[a,b]</m>,
    </p>

    <blockquote permid="PvK">
      <p permid="dzp">
        <em>differences in heights on the graph of the antiderivative</em>
        <em>given by <m>F(b) - F(a)</m></em>
        <em>correspond to the net signed area bounded by the original function on the interval <m>[a,b]</m>,</em>
        <em>which is given by</em> <m>\int_a^b f(x) \, dx</m>.
      </p>
    </blockquote>

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-5-1-1.xml" />
  </subsection>

  <subsection permid="yxz">
    <title>Multiple antiderivatives of a single function</title>
    <p permid="aEJ">
      In the final question of <xref ref="act-5-1-1">Activity</xref>,
      we encountered a very important idea:
      a function <m>f</m> has more than one antiderivative.
      Each antiderivative of <m>f</m> is determined uniquely by its value at a single point.
      For example,
      suppose that <m>f</m> is the function given at left in <xref ref="F-5-1-Ex1">Figure</xref>,
      and suppose further that <m>F</m> is an antiderivative of <m>f</m> that satisfies <m>F(0) = 1</m>.
    </p>

    <figure xml:id="F-5-1-Ex1" permid="XKd">
      <caption>At left, the graph of <m>y = f(x)</m>.  At right, three different antiderivatives of <m>f</m>.</caption>
      <image width="75%" source="images/5_1_Ex1" />
    </figure>

    <p permid="GLS">
      Then, using <xref ref="E-FTCTCT">Equation</xref>,
      we can compute
      <md permid="hdP">
        <mrow>F(1) &amp;= F(0) + \int_0^1 f(x) \, dx</mrow>
        <mrow>&amp;= 1 + 0.5</mrow>
        <mrow>&amp;= 1.5</mrow>
      </md>.
      Similarly, <m>F(2) = 1.5</m>,
      <m>F(3) = -0.5</m>, <m>F(4) = -2</m>,
      <m>F(5) = -0.5</m>, and <m>F(6) = 1</m>.
      In addition,
      we can use the fact that <m>F' = f</m> to ascertain where <m>F</m> is increasing and decreasing,
      concave up and concave down,
      and has relative extremes and inflection points.
      We ultimately find that the graph of <m>F</m> is the one given in blue in <xref ref="F-5-1-Ex1">Figure</xref>.
    </p>

    <p permid="mTb">
      If we want an antiderivative <m>G</m> for which <m>G(0) = 3</m>,
      then <m>G</m> will have the exact same shape as <m>F</m>
      (since both share the derivative <m>f</m>),
      but <m>G</m> will be shifted vertically from the graph of <m>F</m>,
      as pictured in red in <xref ref="F-5-1-Ex1">Figure</xref>.
      Note that <m>G(1) - G(0) = \int_0^1 f(x) \, dx = 0.5</m>,
      just as <m>F(1) - F(0) = 0.5</m>,
      but since <m>G(0) = 3</m>,
      <m>G(1) = G(0) + 0.5 = 3.5</m>,
      whereas <m>F(1) = 1.5</m>.
      In the same way,
      if we assigned a different initial value to the antiderivative,
      say <m>H(0) = -1</m>, we would get still another antiderivative,
      as shown in magenta in <xref ref="F-5-1-Ex1">Figure</xref>.
    </p>

    <p permid="Tak">
      This example demonstrates an important fact that holds more generally:
    </p>

    <assemblage permid="qTa">
      <p permid="zht">
        If <m>G</m> and <m>H</m> are both antiderivatives of a function <m>f</m>,
        then the function <m>G - H</m> must be constant.
      </p>
    </assemblage>

    <p permid="foC">
      To see why this result holds,
      observe that if <m>G</m> and <m>H</m> are both antiderivatives of <m>f</m>,
      then <m>G' = f</m> and <m>H' = f</m>.
      Hence,
      <me permid="NkY">
        \frac{d}{dx}[ G(x) - H(x) ] = G'(x) - H'(x) = f(x) - f(x) = 0
      </me>.
      Since the only way a function can have derivative zero is by being a constant function,
      it follows that the function <m>G - H</m> must be constant.
    </p>

    <p permid="LvL">
      We now see that if a function has at least one antiderivative,
      it must have infinitely many:
      we can add any constant of our choice to the antiderivative and get another antiderivative.
      For this reason, we sometimes refer to the
      <em>general antiderivative</em>
          <idx><h>antiderivative</h><h>general</h></idx>
      of a function <m>f</m>.
    </p>

    <p permid="rCU">
      To identify a particular antiderivative of <m>f</m>,
      we must know a single value of the antiderivative <m>F</m>
      (this value is often called an
      <em>initial condition</em>).
          <idx><h>initial condition</h></idx>
      For example, if <m>f(x) = x^2</m>,
      its general antiderivative is <m>F(x) = \frac{1}{3}x^3 + C</m>,
      where we include the <q><m>+C</m></q>
      to indicate that <m>F</m> includes <em>all</em>
      of the possible antiderivatives of <m>f</m>.
      If we know that <m>F(2) = 3</m>,
      we substitute 2 for <m>x</m> in <m>F(x) = \frac{1}{3}x^3 + C</m>,
      and find that
      <me permid="tsh">
        3 = \frac{1}{3}(2)^3 + C
      </me>,
      or <m>C = 3 - \frac{8}{3} = \frac{1}{3}</m>.
      Therefore, the particular antiderivative in this case is <m>F(x) = \frac{1}{3}x^3 + \frac{1}{3}</m>.
    </p>

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-5-1-2.xml" />
  </subsection>

  <subsection permid="eEI">
    <title>Functions defined by integrals</title>
    <p permid="DRm">
      Equation<nbsp /><xref ref="E-FTCTCT" /> allows us to compute the value of the antiderivative <m>F</m> at a point <m>b</m>,
      provided that we know <m>F(a)</m> and can evaluate the definite integral from <m>a</m> to <m>b</m> of <m>f</m>.
      That is,
      <me permid="Zzq">
        F(b) = F(a) + \int_a^b f(x) \, dx
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p permid="jYv">
      In several situations,
      we have used this formula to compute <m>F(b)</m> for several different values of <m>b</m>,
      and then plotted the points
      <m>(b,F(b))</m> to help us draw an accurate graph of <m>F</m>.
      This suggests that we may want to think of <m>b</m>,
      the upper limit of integration, as a variable itself.
      To that end, we introduce the idea of an
      <em>integral function</em>,
          <idx><h>integral function</h></idx>
      a function whose formula involves a definite integral.
    </p>

    <definition permid="Xaj">
      <statement>
        <p permid="JGy">
          If <m>f</m> is a continuous function,
          we define the corresponding <term>integral function</term>
          <m>A</m> according to the rule
          <men xml:id="E-intfxn" permid="FGz">
            A(x) = \int_a^x f(t) \, dt
          </men>.
        </p>
      </statement>
    </definition>

    <p permid="QfE">
      Note that because <m>x</m> is the independent variable in the function <m>A</m>,
      and determines the endpoint of the interval of integration,
      we need to use a different variable as the variable of integration.
      A standard choice is <m>t</m>,
      but any variable other than <m>x</m> is acceptable.
    </p>

    <p permid="wmN">
      One way to think of the function <m>A</m> is as the
      <q>net signed area from <m>a</m> up to <m>x</m></q> function,
      where we consider the region bounded by
      <m>y = f(t)</m>.
      For example, in <xref ref="F-5-1-IntFxn">Figure</xref>,
      we see a function <m>f</m> pictured at left,
      and its corresponding area function
      (choosing <m>a = 0</m>),
      <m>A(x) = \int_0^x f(t) \, dt</m> shown at right.
    </p>

    <figure xml:id="F-5-1-IntFxn" permid="oIo">
      <caption>At left, the graph of the given function <m>f</m>.  At right, the area function <m>A(x) = \int_0^x f(t) \  dt</m>.</caption>
      <image width="100%" source="images/5_1_IntFxn" />
    </figure>

    <p permid="ctW">
      The function <m>A</m> measures the net signed area from <m>t = 0</m> to <m>t = x</m> bounded by the curve <m>y = f(t)</m>;
      this value is then reported as the corresponding height on the graph of <m>y = A(x)</m>.
      At <url href="http://gvsu.edu/s/cz">http://gvsu.edu/s/cz</url>,
      we find a java applet<fn>
      David Austin, Grand Valley State University
      </fn> that brings the static picture in <xref ref="F-5-1-IntFxn">Figure</xref> to life.
      There, the user can move the red point on the function <m>f</m> and see how the corresponding height changes at the light blue point on the graph of <m>A</m>.
    </p>

    <p permid="IBf">
      The choice of <m>a</m> is somewhat arbitrary.
      In the activity that follows,
      we explore how the value of <m>a</m> affects the graph of the integral function.
    </p>

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-5-1-3.xml" />
  </subsection>

  <subsection permid="KLR">
    <title>Summary</title>
    <p permid="UPx">
      <ul permid="bKc">
        <li permid="AmM">
          <p permid="ldO">
            Given the graph of a function <m>f</m>,
            we can construct the graph of its antiderivative <m>F</m> provided that (a) we know a starting value of <m>F</m>,
            say <m>F(a)</m>,
            and (b) we can evaluate the integral
            <m>\int_a^b f(x) \, dx</m> exactly for relevant choices of <m>a</m> and <m>b</m>.
            For instance, if we wish to know <m>F(3)</m>,
            we can compute <m>F(3) = F(a) + \int_a^3 f(x) \, dx</m>.
            When we combine this information about the function values of <m>F</m> together with our understanding of how the behavior of <m>F' = f</m> affects the overall shape of <m>F</m>,
            we can develop a completely accurate graph of the antiderivative <m>F</m>.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="gtV">
          <p permid="RkX">
            Because the derivative of a constant is zero,
            if <m>F</m> is an antiderivative of <m>f</m>,
            it follows that <m>G(x) = F(x) + C</m> will also be an antiderivative of <m>f</m>.
            Moreover,
            any two antiderivatives of a function <m>f</m> differ precisely by a constant.
            Thus, any function with at least one antiderivative in fact has infinitely many,
            and the graphs of any two antiderivatives will differ only by a vertical translation.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="MBe">
          <p permid="xsg">
            Given a function <m>f</m>,
            the rule <m>A(x) = \int_a^x f(t) \, dt</m> defines a new function <m>A</m> that measures the net-signed area bounded by <m>f</m> on the interval <m>[a,x]</m>.
            We call the function <m>A</m> the integral function corresponding to <m>f</m>.
          </p>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <xi:include href="./exercises/ez-5-1.xml" />
</section>

