<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<!-- Copyright 2012-2018                                                   -->
<!-- Matthew Boelkins                                                      -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- This file is part of Active Calculus.                                 -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document -->
<!-- under the terms of the Creative Commons BY-SA license.  The work      -->
<!-- may be used for free by any party so long as attribution is given to  -->
<!-- the author(s), the work and its derivatives are used in the spirit of -->
<!-- "share and share alike".  All trademarks are the registered marks of  -->
<!-- their respective owners.                                              -->
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<section xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec-3-5-rel-rates" permid="uiS">
  <title>Related Rates</title>
  <objectives permid="ySL">
    <ul permid="jJN">
      <li permid="cfo">
        <p permid="RGj">
          If two quantities that are related,
          such as the radius and volume of a spherical balloon,
          are both changing as implicit functions of time,
          how are their rates of change related?
          That is, how does the relationship between the values of the quantities affect the relationship between their respective derivatives with respect to time?
        </p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </objectives>

  <introduction permid="eZU">
    <p permid="IWr">
      In most of our applications of the derivative so far,
      we have been interested in the instantaneous rate at which one variable,
      say <m>y</m>, changes with respect to another, say <m>x</m>,
      leading us to compute and interpret <m>\frac{dy}{dx}</m>.
      We next consider situations where several variable quantities are related,
      but where each quantity is implicitly a function of time,
      which will be represented by the variable <m>t</m>.
      Through knowing how the quantities are related,
      we will be interested in determining how their respective rates of change with respect to time are related.
    </p>

    <p permid="pdA">
      For example,
      suppose that air is being pumped into a spherical balloon so that its volume increases at a constant rate of 20 cubic inches per second.
      Since the balloon's volume and radius are related,
      by knowing how fast the volume is changing,
      we ought to be able to discover how fast the radius is changing.
      We are interested in questions such as:
      can we determine how fast the radius of the balloon is increasing at the moment the balloon's diameter is 12 inches?
    </p>

    <xi:include href="./previews/PA-3-5.xml" />
  </introduction>

  <subsection permid="aqb">
    <title>Related Rates Problems</title>
    <p permid="VkJ">
      In problems where two or more quantities can be related to one another,
      and all of the variables involved are implicitly functions of time,
      <m>t</m>,
      we are often interested in how their rates are related;
      we call these <em>related rates</em> problems.
          <idx><h>related rates</h></idx>
      Once we have an equation establishing the relationship among the variables,
      we differentiate implicitly with respect to time to find connections among the rates of change.
    </p>

    <example xml:id="Ex-3-5-FallingSand" permid="mEt">
      <statement>
        <p permid="QAQ">
          Sand is being dumped by a conveyor belt onto a pile so that the sand forms a right circular cone,
          as pictured in <xref ref="F-3-5-ConeEx">Figure</xref>.
        </p>

        <figure xml:id="F-3-5-ConeEx" permid="wHZ">
          <caption>A conical pile of sand.</caption>
          <image width="50%" source="images/3_5_ConeEx" />
        </figure>
      </statement>
      <solution permid="Lhd">
        <p permid="Hhe">
          As sand falls from the conveyor belt,
          several features of the sand pile will change:
          the volume of the pile will grow,
          the height will increase, and the radius will get bigger, too.
          All of these quantities are related to one another,
          and the rate at which each is changing is related to the rate at which sand falls from the conveyor.
        </p>

        <p permid="non">
          We begin by identifying which variables are changing and how they are related.
          In this problem,
          we observe that the radius and height of the pile are related to its volume by the standard equation for the volume of a cone,
          <me permid="WZW">
            V = \frac{1}{3} \pi r^2 h
          </me>.
        </p>

        <p permid="Tvw">
          Viewing each of <m>V</m>, <m>r</m>,
          and <m>h</m> as functions of <m>t</m>,
          we differentiate implicitly to arrive at an equation that relates their respective rates of change.
          Taking the derivative of each side of the equation with respect to <m>t</m>, we find
          <me permid="Dhf">
            \frac{d}{dt}[V] = \frac{d}{dt}\left[\frac{1}{3} \pi r^2 h\right]
          </me>.
        </p>

        <p permid="zCF">
          On the left,
          <m>\frac{d}{dt}[V]</m> is simply <m>\frac{dV}{dt}</m>.
          On the right, the situation is more complicated,
          as both <m>r</m> and <m>h</m> are implicit functions of <m>t</m>.
          Hence we need the product and chain rules.
          We find that
          <md permid="joo">
            <mrow>\frac{dV}{dt} &amp;=  \frac{d}{dt}\left[\frac{1}{3} \pi r^2 h\right]</mrow>
            <mrow>&amp;=  \frac{1}{3} \pi r^2 \frac{d}{dt}[h] + \frac{1}{3} \pi h \frac{d}{dt}[r^2]</mrow>
            <mrow>&amp;=  \frac{1}{3} \pi r^2 \frac{dh}{dt} + \frac{1}{3} \pi h 2r \frac{dr}{dt}</mrow>
          </md>
        </p>

        <p permid="fJO">
          (Note particularly how we are using ideas from <xref ref="sec-2-7-implicit">Section</xref> on implicit differentiation.
          There we found that when <m>y</m> is an implicit function of <m>x</m>,
          <m>\frac{d}{dx}[y^2] = 2y \frac{dy}{dx}</m>.
          The same principles are applied here when we compute <m>\frac{d}{dt}[r^2] = 2r \frac{dr}{dt}</m>.)
        </p>

        <p permid="LQX">
          The equation
          <me permid="Pvx">
            \frac{dV}{dt} = \frac{1}{3} \pi r^2 \frac{dh}{dt} + \frac{2}{3} \pi rh \frac{dr}{dt}
          </me>,
          relates the rates of change of <m>V</m>, <m>h</m>,
          and <m>r</m>.
        </p>
      </solution>
    </example>

    <p permid="BrS">
      If we are given sufficient additional information,
      we may then find the value of one or more of these rates of change at a specific point in time.
    </p>

    <example permid="SLC">
      <statement>
        <p permid="cPi">
          In the setting of <xref ref="Ex-3-5-FallingSand">Example</xref>,
          suppose we also know the following: (a) sand falls from the conveyor in such a way that the height of the pile is always half the radius,
          and (b) sand falls from the conveyor belt at a constant rate of 10 cubic feet per minute.
          How fast is the height of the sandpile changing at the moment the radius is 4 feet?
        </p>
      </statement>
      <solution permid="rom">
        <p permid="rYg">
          The information that the height is always half the radius tells us that for all values of <m>t</m>,
          <m>h = \frac{1}{2}r</m>.
          Differentiating with respect to <m>t</m>,
          it follows that <m>\frac{dh}{dt} = \frac{1}{2} \frac{dr}{dt}</m>.
          These relationships enable us to relate
          <m>\frac{dV}{dt}</m> to just one of <m>r</m> or <m>h</m>.
          Substituting the expressions involving <m>r</m> and
          <m>\frac{dr}{dt}</m> for <m>h</m> and <m>\frac{dh}{dt}</m>,
          we now have that
          <men xml:id="E-ConeRR" permid="vCG">
            \frac{dV}{dt} = \frac{1}{3} \pi r^2 \cdot \frac{1}{2} \frac{dr}{dt} + \frac{2}{3} \pi r \cdot \frac{1}{2}r \cdot \frac{dr}{dt}
          </men>.
        </p>

        <p permid="Yfp">
          Since sand falls from the conveyor at the constant rate of 10 cubic feet per minute,
          the value of <m>\frac{dV}{dt}</m>,
          the rate at which the volume of the sand pile changes,
          is <m>\frac{dV}{dt} = 10</m> ft<m>^3</m>/min.
          We are interested in how fast the height of the pile is changing at the instant when <m>r = 4</m>, so
          we substitute <m>r = 4</m> and
          <m>\frac{dV}{dt} = 10</m> into Equation<nbsp /><xref ref="E-ConeRR" />, to find
          <me permid="bJP">
            10 = \frac{1}{3} \pi 4^2 \cdot \frac{1}{2}  \left. \frac{dr}{dt} \right|_{r=4} + \frac{2}{3} \pi 4 \cdot \frac{1}{2}4 \cdot \left. \frac{dr}{dt} \right|_{r=4} = \frac{8}{3}\pi \left. \frac{dr}{dt} \right|_{r=4} + \frac{16}{3} \pi \left. \frac{dr}{dt} \right|_{r=4}
          </me>.
        </p>

        <p permid="Emy">
          Only the value of <m>\left. \frac{dr}{dt} \right|_{r=4}</m> remains unknown.
          We combine like terms on the right side of the equation above to get
          <m>10 = 8 \pi \left. \frac{dr}{dt} \right|_{r=4}</m>,
          and solve for <m>\left. \frac{dr}{dt} \right|_{r=4}</m> to find
          <me permid="HQY">
            \left. \frac{dr}{dt} \right|_{r=4} = \frac{10}{8\pi} \approx 0.39789
          </me>
          feet per second.
          Because we were interested in how fast the height of the pile was changing at this instant,
          we want to know <m>\frac{dh}{dt}</m> when <m>r = 4</m>.
          Since <m>\frac{dh}{dt} = \frac{1}{2} \frac{dr}{dt}</m> for all values of <m>t</m>,
          it follows
          <me permid="nYh">
            \left. \frac{dh}{dt} \right|_{r=4} = \frac{5}{8\pi} \approx 0.19894 \ \text{ft/min}
          </me>.
        </p>
      </solution>
    </example>

    <p permid="hzb">
      Note the difference between the notations
      <m>\frac{dr}{dt}</m> and <m>\left. \frac{dr}{dt} \right|_{r=4}</m>.
      The former represents the rate of change of <m>r</m> with respect to <m>t</m> at an arbitrary value of <m>t</m>,
      while the latter is the rate of change of <m>r</m> with respect to <m>t</m> at a particular moment,
      the moment when <m>r = 4</m>.
    </p>

    <p permid="NGk">
      Had we known that <m>h = \frac{1}{2}r</m> at the beginning of <xref ref="Ex-3-5-FallingSand">Example</xref>,
      we could have immediately simplified our work by writing <m>V</m> solely in terms of <m>r</m> to have
      <me permid="Ufq">
        V = \frac{1}{3} \pi r^2 \left(\frac{1}{2}h\right) = \frac{1}{6} \pi r^3
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p permid="tNt">
      From this last equation, differentiating with respect to <m>t</m> implies
      <me permid="Amz">
        \frac{dV}{dt} = \frac{1}{2} \pi r^2 \frac{dr}{dt}
      </me>,
      from which the same conclusions can be made.
    </p>

    <p permid="ZUC">
      Our work with the sandpile problem above is similar in many ways to our approach in <xref ref="PA-3-5">Preview Activity</xref>,
      and these steps are typical of most related rates problems.
      In certain ways,
      they also resemble work we do in applied optimization problems,
      and here we summarize the main approach for consideration in subsequent problems.
    </p>

    <note permid="Xvv">
      <p permid="ktH">
        <ul permid="DCE">
          <li permid="Imx">
            <p permid="xNs">
              Identify the quantities in the problem that are changing and choose clearly defined variable names for them.
              Draw one or more figures that clearly represent the situation.
            </p>
          </li>

          <li permid="otG">
            <p permid="dUB">
              Determine all rates of change that are known or given and identify the rate(s) of change to be found.
            </p>
          </li>

          <li permid="UAP">
            <p permid="KbK">
              Find an equation that relates the variables whose rates of change are known to those variables whose rates of change are to be found.
            </p>
          </li>

          <li permid="AHY">
            <p permid="qiT">
              Differentiate implicitly with respect to <m>t</m> to relate the rates of change of the involved quantities.
            </p>
          </li>

          <li permid="gPh">
            <p permid="Wqc">
              Evaluate the derivatives and variables at the information relevant to the instant at which a certain rate of change is sought.
              Use proper notation to identify when a derivative is being evaluated at a particular instant,
              such as <m>\left. \frac{dr}{dt} \right|_{r=4}</m>.
            </p>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </p>
    </note>

    <p permid="GbL">
      When identifying variables and drawing a picture,
      it is important to think about the dynamic ways in which the quantities change.
      Sometimes a sequence of pictures can be helpful;
      for some pictures that can be easily modified as applets built in Geogebra,
      see the following links,<fn>
      We again refer to the work of Prof.<nbsp />Marc Renault of Shippensburg University,
      found at
      <url href="http://gvsu.edu/s/5p">http://gvsu.edu/s/5p</url>.
      </fn> which represent

      <ul permid="PQW">
        <li permid="MWq">
          <p permid="Cxl">
            how a circular oil slick's area grows as its radius increases <url href="http://gvsu.edu/s/9n">http://gvsu.edu/s/9n</url>;
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="tdz">
          <p permid="iEu">
            how the location of the base of a ladder and its height along a wall change as the ladder slides <url href="http://gvsu.edu/s/9o">http://gvsu.edu/s/9o</url>;
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="ZkI">
          <p permid="OLD">
            how the water level changes in a conical tank as it fills with water at a constant rate
            <url href="http://gvsu.edu/s/9p">http://gvsu.edu/s/9p</url>
            (compare the problem in <xref ref="act-3-5-1">Activity</xref>);
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="FrR">
          <p permid="uSM">
            how a skateboarder's shadow changes as he moves past a lamppost
            <url href="http://gvsu.edu/s/9q">http://gvsu.edu/s/9q</url>.
          </p>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </p>

    <p permid="miU">
      Drawing well-labeled diagrams and envisioning how different parts of the figure change is a key part of understanding related rates problems and being successful at solving them.
    </p>

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-3-5-1.xml" />

    <p permid="Sqd">
      Recognizing which geometric relationships are relevant in a given problem 
      is often the key to finding the function to optimize.
      For instance,
      although the problem in <xref ref="act-3-5-1">Activity</xref>
      is about a conical tank,
      the most important fact is that there are two similar right triangles involved.
      In another setting,
      we might use the Pythagorean Theorem to relate the legs of the triangle.
      But in the conical tank,
      the fact that the water fills the tank so that that the ratio of radius to depth is constant turns out to be the important relationship.
      In other situations where a changing angle is involved,
      trigonometric functions may provide the means to find relationships among various parts of the triangle.
    </p>

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-3-5-2.xml" />

    <p permid="yxm">
      In addition to finding instantaneous rates of change at particular points in time,
      we can often make more general observations about how particular rates themselves will change over time.
      For instance,
      when a conical tank is filling with water at a constant rate,
      it seems obvious that the depth of the water should increase more slowly over time.
      Note how carefully we must phrase the relationship:
      we mean to say that while the depth,
      <m>h</m>, of the water is increasing,
      its rate of change, <m>\frac{dh}{dt}</m>, is decreasing 
      (both as a function of <m>t</m> and as a function of <m>h</m>).
      We make this observation by solving the equation that relates the various rates for one particular rate,
      without substituting any particular values for known variables or rates.
      For instance,
      in the conical tank problem in <xref ref="act-3-5-1">Activity</xref>,
      we established that
      <me permid="gtI">
        \frac{dV}{dt} = \frac{1}{16} \pi h^2 \frac{dh}{dt}
      </me>,
      and hence
      <me permid="MAR">
        \frac{dh}{dt} = \frac{16}{\pi h^2} \frac{dV}{dt}
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p permid="eEv">
      Provided that <m>\frac{dV}{dt}</m> is constant,
      it is immediately apparent that as <m>h</m> gets larger,
      <m>\frac{dh}{dt}</m> will get smaller
      but remain positive.
      Hence, the depth of the water is increasing at a decreasing rate.
    </p>

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-3-5-3.xml" />

    <p permid="KLE">
      In the first three activities of this section,
      we provided guided instruction to build a solution in a step by step way.
      For the closing activity and the following exercises,
      most of the detailed work is left to the reader.
    </p>

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-3-5-4.xml" />
  </subsection>

  <reading-questions>

    <exercise>
      <p>
        Suppose that <m>V = s^3</m> and that both <m>V</m> and <m>s</m> are implicitly functions of <m>t</m>.  Differentiate both sides of the equation <m>V = s^3</m> with respect to <m>t</m> and find a resulting equation that relates <m>V</m>, <m>s</m>, <m>\frac{dV}{dt}</m>, and <m>\frac{ds}{dt}</m>.
      </p>
    </exercise>
  
    <exercise>
      <p>
        Suppose that <m>x^2 + y^2 = z^2</m> and that <m>x</m>, <m>y</m>, and <m>z</m> are all implicitly functions of <m>t</m>.  Differentiate both sides of the equation <m>x^2 + y^2 = z^2</m> with respect to <m>t</m> and find a resulting equation that relates <m>x</m>, <m>y</m>, <m>z</m>, <m>\frac{dx}{dt}</m>, <m>\frac{dy}{dt}</m>, and <m>\frac{dz}{dt}</m>.
      </p>
    </exercise>
  
    <exercise>
      <p>
        Suppose we have a circular cylinder of radius <m>r</m> and height <m>h</m>,
        so that its volume is <m>V = \pi r^2 h</m>.
        Suppose further that <m>V</m>,
        <m>r</m>, and <m>h</m> are all changing as time changes,
        and thus each is implicitly a function of <m>t</m>.
        Find an equation that relates <m>\frac{dV}{dt}</m>,
        <m>\frac{dr}{dt}</m>, and <m>\frac{dh}{dt}</m>.
        Write one sentence to say what derivative rule(s) you used to establish the equation that relates the rates.
      </p>
    </exercise>
    
  </reading-questions>

  <subsection permid="Gxk">
    <title>Summary</title>
    <p permid="qSN">
      <ul permid="vYf">
        <li permid="lza">
          <p permid="aZV">
            When two or more related quantities are changing as implicit functions of time,
            their rates of change can be related by implicitly differentiating the equation that relates the quantities themselves.
            For instance,
            if the sides of a right triangle are all changing as functions of time,
            say having lengths <m>x</m>, <m>y</m>, and <m>z</m>,
            then these quantities are related by the Pythagorean Theorem:
            <m>x^2 + y^2 = z^2</m>.
            It follows by implicitly differentiating with respect to <m>t</m> that their rates are related by the equation
            <me permid="sIa">
              2x \frac{dx}{dt} + 2y\frac{dy}{dt} = 2z \frac{dz}{dt}
            </me>,
            so that if we know the values of <m>x</m>, <m>y</m>,
            and <m>z</m> at a particular time,
            as well as two of the three rates,
            we can deduce the value of the third.
          </p>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <xi:include href="./exercises/ez-3-5.xml" />
</section>

