<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<section xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec-5-2-FTC2">
  <title>The Second Fundamental Theorem of Calculus</title>
  <introduction>
    <objectives>
      <ul>
        <li><p>How does the integral function <m>A(x) = \int_1^x f(t) \, dt</m> define an antiderivative of <m>f</m>?</p></li>

        <li><p>What is the statement of the Second Fundamental Theorem of Calculus?</p></li>

        <li><p>How do the First and Second Fundamental Theorems of Calculus enable us to formally see how differentiation and integration are almost inverse processes?</p></li>
      </ul>
    </objectives>
    <p>In <xref ref="sec-4-4-FTC">Section</xref>, we learned the Fundamental Theorem of Calculus (FTC), which from here forward will be referred to as the <em>First</em> Fundamental Theorem of Calculus<index><main>Fundamental Theorem of Calculus</main><sub>First</sub></index>, as in this section we develop a corresponding result that follows it. In particular, recall that the First FTC tells us that if <m>f</m> is a continuous function on <m>[a,b]</m> and <m>F</m> is any antiderivative of <m>f</m> (that is, <m>F' = f</m>), then
      <me>
        \int_a^b f(x) \, dx = F(b) - F(a).
      </me>
    </p>

    <p>We have typically used this result in two settings: (1) where <m>f</m> is a function whose graph we know and for which we can compute the exact area bounded by <m>f</m> on a certain interval <m>[a,b]</m>, we can compute the change in an antiderivative <m>F</m> over the interval; and (2) where <m>f</m> is a function for which it is easy to determine an algebraic formula for an antiderivative, we may evaluate the integral exactly and hence determine the net-signed area bounded by the function on the interval. For the former, see <xref ref="PA-5-1">Preview Activity</xref> or <xref ref="act-5-1-1">Activity</xref>. For the latter, we can easily evaluate exactly integrals such as
      <me>
        \int_1^4 x^2 \, dx,
      </me>
      since we know that the function <m>F(x) = \frac{1}{3}x^3</m> is an antiderivative of <m>f(x) = x^2</m>. Thus,
      <md>
        <mrow>\int_1^4 x^2 \, dx =\mathstrut \amp  \frac{1}{3}x^3 \bigg\vert_1^4</mrow>
        <mrow>=\mathstrut \amp  \frac{1}{3}(4)^3 - \frac{1}{3}(1)^3</mrow>
        <mrow>=\mathstrut \amp  21.</mrow>
      </md>
    </p>

    <p>Here we see that the First FTC can be viewed from at least two perspectives: first, as a tool to find the difference <m>F(b) - F(a)</m> for an antiderivative <m>F</m> of the integrand <m>f</m>. In this situation, we need to be able to determine the value of the integral <m>\int_a^b f(x) \, dx</m> exactly, perhaps through known geometric formulas for area. It is possible that we may not have a formula for <m>F</m> itself. From a second perspective, the First FTC provides a way to find the exact value of a definite integral, and hence a certain net-signed area exactly, by finding an antiderivative of the integrand and evaluating its total change over the interval. In this latter case, we need to know a formula for the antiderivative <m>F</m>, as this enables us to compute net-signed areas exactly through definite integrals, as demonstrated in <xref ref="F-5-2-Intro">Figure</xref>.</p>

    <figure xml:id="F-5-2-Intro" >
      <caption>At left, the graph of <m>f(x) = x^2</m> on the interval <m>[1,4]</m> and the area it bounds.  At right, the antiderivative function <m>F(x) = \frac{1}{3}x^3</m>, whose total change on <m>[1,4]</m> is the value of the definite integral at left.</caption>
      <image width="100%" source="images/5_2_Intro" />
    </figure>

    <p>We recall further that the value of a definite integral may have additional meaning depending on context: change in position when the integrand is a velocity function, total pollutant leaked from a tank when the integrand is the rate at which pollution is leaking, or other total changes that correspond to a given rate function that is the integrand. In addition, the value of the definite integral is always connected to the average value of a continuous function on a given interval: <m>f_{AVG [a,b]} = \frac{1}{b-a} \int_a^b f(x) \, dx</m>.</p>

    <p>Next, remember that in the last part of <xref ref="sec-5-1-antid-graphs">Section</xref>, we studied integral functions of the form <m>A(x) = \int_c^x f(t) \, dt</m>. <xref ref="F-5-1-IntFxn">Figure</xref> is a particularly important image to keep in mind as we work with integral functions, and the corresponding java applet at <url href="http://gvsu.edu/s/cz"><c>http://gvsu.edu/s/cz</c></url> is likewise foundational to our understanding of the function <m>A</m>. In what follows, we use the First FTC to gain additional understanding of the function <m>A(x) = \int_c^x f(t) \, dt</m>, where the integrand <m>f</m> is given (either through a graph or a formula), and <m>c</m> is a constant. In particular, we investigate further the special nature of the relationship between the functions <m>A</m> and <m>f</m>.</p>

    <xi:include href="./previews/PA-5-2.xml" />

  </introduction>

  <subsection>
    <title>The Second Fundamental Theorem of Calculus</title>
    <p><index><main>Fundamental Theorem of Calculus</main><sub>Second</sub></index></p>

    <p>The result of <xref ref="PA-5-2">Preview Activity</xref> is not particular to the function <m>f(t) = 4-2t</m>, nor to the choice of <q><m>1</m></q> as the lower bound in the integral that defines the function <m>A</m>. For instance, if we let <m>f(t) = \cos(t) - t</m> and set <m>A(x) = \int_2^x f(t) \, dt</m>, then we can determine a formula for <m>A</m> without integrals by the First FTC. Specifically,
      <md>
        <mrow>A(x) =\mathstrut \amp  \int_2^x (\cos(t) - t) \, dt</mrow>
        <mrow>=\mathstrut \amp  \sin(t) - \frac{1}{2}t^2 \bigg\vert_2^x</mrow>
        <mrow>=\mathstrut \amp  \sin(x) -  \frac{1}{2}x^2 - \left(\sin(2) - 2 \right).</mrow>
      </md>
    </p>

    <p>Differentiating <m>A(x)</m>, since <m>(\sin(2) - 2)</m> is constant, it follows that
      <me>
        A'(x) = \cos(x) - x,
      </me>
      and thus we see that <m>A'(x) = f(x)</m>. This tells us that for this particular choice of <m>f</m>, <m>A</m> is an antiderivative of <m>f</m>. More specifically, since <m>A(2) = \int_2^2 f(t) \, dt = 0</m>, <m>A</m> is the only antiderivative of <m>f</m> for which <m>A(2) = 0</m>.</p>

    <p>In general, if <m>f</m> is any continuous function, and we define the function <m>A</m> by the rule
      <me>
        A(x) = \int_c^x f(t) \, dt,
      </me>
      where <m>c</m> is an arbitrary constant, then we can show that <m>A</m> is an antiderivative of <m>f</m>. To see why, let's demonstrate that <m>A'(x) = f(x)</m> by using the limit definition of the derivative. Doing so, we observe that
      <md>
        <mrow>A'(x) \amp = \lim_{h \to 0} \frac{A(x+h) - A(x)}{h}</mrow>
        <mrow>\amp = \lim_{h \to 0} \frac{\int_c^{x+h} f(t) \, dt - \int_c^x f(t) \, dt}{h}</mrow>
        <mrow xml:id="E-FTC2limdef">\amp = \lim_{h \to 0} \frac{\int_x^{x+h} f(t) \, dt}{h},</mrow>
      </md>
      where Equation<nbsp /><xref ref="E-FTC2limdef" /> in the preceding chain follows from the fact that <m>\int_c^x f(t) \,dt + \int_x^{x+h} f(t) \, dt = \int_c^{x+h} f(t) \, dt</m>. Now, observe that for small values of <m>h</m>,
      <me>
        \int_x^{x+h} f(t) \, dt \approx f(x) \cdot h,
      </me>
      by a simple left-hand approximation of the integral. Thus, as we take the limit in Equation<nbsp /><xref ref="E-FTC2limdef" />, it follows that
      <me>
        A'(x) =  \lim_{h \to 0} \frac{\int_x^{x+h} f(t) \, dt}{h} = \lim_{h \to 0} \frac{f(x) \cdot h}{h} = f(x).
      </me>
    </p>

    <p>Hence, <m>A</m> is indeed an antiderivative of <m>f</m>. In addition, <m>A(c) = \int_c^c f(t) \, dt = 0.</m> The preceding argument demonstrates the truth of the Second Fundamental Theorem of Calculus, which we state as follows.</p>

    <aside xml:id="FTC-2">
        <title>The Second Fundamental Theorem of Calculus.<index><main>second fundamental theorem of calculus</main></index></title> 
        <p>If <m>f</m> is a continuous function and <m>c</m> is any constant, then <m>f</m> has a unique antiderivative <m>A</m> that satisfies <m>A(c) = 0</m>, and that antiderivative is given by the rule <m>A(x) = \int_c^x f(t) \, dt</m>.</p>
    </aside>    

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-5-2-1.xml" />

  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <title>Understanding Integral Functions</title>
    <p>The Second FTC provides us with a means to construct an antiderivative of any continuous function. In particular, if we are given a continuous function <m>g</m> and wish to find an antiderivative of <m>G</m>, we can now say that
      <me>
        G(x) = \int_c^x g(t) \, dt
      </me>
      provides the rule for such an antiderivative, and moreover that <m>G(c) = 0</m>. Note especially that we know that <m>G'(x) = g(x)</m>. We sometimes want to write this relationship between <m>G</m> and <m>g</m> from a different notational perspective. In particular, observe that
      <men xml:id="E_diffint" >
        \frac{d}{dx} \left[ \int_c^x g(t) \, dt \right] = g(x).
      </men>
    </p>

    <p>This result can be particularly useful when we're given an integral function such as <m>G</m> and wish to understand properties of its graph by recognizing that <m>G'(x) = g(x)</m>, while not necessarily being able to exactly evaluate the definite integral <m>\int_c^x g(t) \, dt</m>. To see how this is the case, we consider the following example.</p>

    <example>
      <statement>
        <p>Investigate the behavior of the integral function
          <me>
            E(x) = \int_0^x e^{-t^2} \, dt.
          </me>
        </p>
      </statement>
    <solution>
    <p><m>E</m> is closely related to the well known <em>error function</em><index><main>error functin</main></index><fn>The error function is defined by the rule <m>\mbox{erf} (x) = \frac{2}{\sqrt{\pi}} \int_0^x e^{-t^2} \,dt</m> and has the key property that <m>0 \le \mbox{erf} (x) \lt  1</m> for all <m>x \ge 0</m> and moreover that <m>\lim_{x \to \infty} \mbox{erf} (x) = 1</m>.</fn>, a function that is particularly important in probability and statistics. It turns out that the function <m>e^{-t^2}</m> does not have an elementary antiderivative that we can express without integrals. That is, whereas a function such as <m>f(t) = 4-2t</m> has elementary antiderivative <m>F(t) = 4t - t^2</m>, we are unable to find a simple formula for an antiderivative of <m>e^{-t^2}</m> that does not involve a definite integral. We will learn more about finding (complicated) algebraic formulas for antiderivatives without definite integrals in the chapter on infinite series.</p>

    <p>Returning our attention to the function <m>E</m>, while we cannot evaluate <m>E</m> exactly for any value other than <m>x = 0</m>,
      we still can gain a tremendous amount of information about the function <m>E</m>. To begin, applying the rule in Equation<nbsp /><xref ref="E_diffint" /> to <m>E</m>, it follows that
      <me>
        E'(x) = \frac{d}{dx} \left[ \int_0^x e^{-t^2} \, dt \right] = e^{-x^2},
      </me>
      so we know a formula for the derivative of <m>E</m>. Moreover, we know that <m>E(0) = 0</m>. This information is precisely the type we were given in problems such as the one in <xref ref="act-3-1-1">Activity</xref> and others in <xref ref="sec-3-1-tests">Section</xref>, where we were given information about the derivative of a function, but lacked a formula for the function itself.</p>

    <p>Here, using the first and second derivatives of <m>E</m>, along with the fact that <m>E(0) = 0</m>, we can determine more information about the behavior of <m>E</m>. First, with <m>E'(x) = e^{-x^2}</m>, we note that for all real numbers <m>x</m>, <m>e^{-x^2} \gt 0</m>, and thus <m>E'(x) \gt 0</m> for all <m>x</m>. Thus <m>E</m> is an always increasing function. Further, we note that as <m>x \to \infty</m>, <m>E'(x) = e^{-x^2} \to 0</m>, hence the slope of the function <m>E</m> tends to zero as <m>x \to \infty</m> (and similarly as <m>x \to -\infty</m>). Indeed, it turns out (due to some more sophisticated analysis) that <m>E</m> has horizontal asymptotes as <m>x</m> increases or decreases without bound.</p>

    <p>In addition, we can observe that <m>E''(x) = -2xe^{-x^2}</m>, and that <m>E''(0) = 0</m>, while <m>E''(x) \lt  0</m> for <m>x \gt 0</m> and <m>E''(x) \gt 0</m> for <m>x \lt  0</m>. This information tells us that <m>E</m> is concave up for <m>x\lt 0</m> and concave down for <m>x \gt 0</m> with a point of inflection at <m>x = 0</m>.</p>

    <p>The only thing we lack at this point is a sense of how big <m>E</m> can get as <m>x</m> increases. If we use a midpoint Riemann sum with 10 subintervals to estimate <m>E(2)</m>, we see that <m>E(2) \approx 0.8822</m>; a similar calculation to estimate <m>E(3)</m> shows little change (<m>E(3) \approx 0.8862</m>), so it appears that as <m>x</m> increases without bound, <m>E</m> approaches a value just larger than <m>0.886</m>, which aligns with the fact that <m>E</m> has horizontal asymptotes. Putting all of this information together (and using the symmetry of <m>f(t) = e^{-t^2}</m>), we see the results shown in <xref ref="F-5-2-erf">Figure</xref>.</p>

    <figure xml:id="F-5-2-erf" >
      <caption>At left, the graph of <m>f(t) = e^{-t^2}</m>.  At right, the integral function <m>E(x) = \int_0^x e^{-t^2} \ dt</m>, which is the unique antiderivative of <m>f</m> that satisfies <m>E(0) = 0</m>.</caption>
      <image width="100%" source="images/5_2_erf" />
    </figure>

    <p>Again, <m>E</m> is the antiderivative of <m>f(t) = e^{-t^2}</m> that satisfies <m>E(0) = 0</m>. Moreover, the values on the graph of <m>y = E(x)</m> represent the net-signed area of the region bounded by <m>f(t) = e^{-t^2}</m> from 0 up to <m>x</m>. We see that the value of <m>E</m> increases rapidly near zero but then levels off as <m>x</m> increases since there is less and less additional accumulated area bounded by <m>f(t) = e^{-t^2}</m> as <m>x</m> increases.</p>
    </solution>    
</example>

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-5-2-2.xml" />

  </subsection>  

  <subsection>
    <title>Differentiating an Integral Function</title>
    <p>We have seen that the Second FTC enables us to construct an antiderivative <m>F</m> of any continuous function <m>f</m> by defining <m>F</m> by the corresponding integral function <m>F(x) = \int_c^x f(t) \, dt</m>. Said differently, if we have a function of the form <m>F(x) = \int_c^x f(t) \, dt</m>, then we know that <m>F'(x) = \frac{d}{dx} \left[\int_c^x f(t) \, dt \right] = f(x)</m>. This shows that integral functions, while perhaps having the most complicated formulas of any functions we have encountered, are nonetheless particularly simple to differentiate. For instance, if
      <me>
        F(x) = \int_{\pi}^x \sin(t^2) \, dt,
      </me>
      then by the Second FTC, we know immediately that
      <me>
        F'(x) = \sin(x^2).
      </me>
    </p>

    <p>Stating this result more generally for an arbitrary function <m>f</m>, we know by the Second FTC that
      <me>
        \frac{d}{dx} \left[ \int_a^x f(t) \, dt \right] = f(x).
      </me>
    </p>

    <p>In words, the last equation essentially says that <q>the derivative of the integral function whose integrand is <m>f</m>, is <m>f</m>.</q> In this sense, we see that if we first integrate the function <m>f</m> from <m>t = a</m> to <m>t = x</m>, and then differentiate with respect to <m>x</m>, these two processes <q>undo</q> one another.</p>

    <p>Taking a different approach, say we begin with a function <m>f(t)</m> and differentiate with respect to <m>t</m>. What happens if we follow this by integrating the result from <m>t = a</m> to <m>t = x</m>? That is, what can we say about the quantity
      <me>
        \int_a^x \frac{d}{dt} \left[ f(t) \right] \, dt?
      </me>
    </p>

    <p>Here, we use the First FTC and note that <m>f(t)</m> is an antiderivative of <m>\frac{d}{dt} \left[ f(t) \right].</m> Applying this result and evaluating the antiderivative function, we see that
      <md>
        <mrow>\int_a^x \frac{d}{dt} \left[ f(t) \right] \, dt =\mathstrut \amp  f(t) \bigg\vert_a^x</mrow>
        <mrow>=\mathstrut \amp  f(x) - f(a).</mrow>
      </md>
    </p>

    <p>Thus, we see that if we apply the processes of first differentiating <m>f</m> and then integrating the result from <m>a</m> to <m>x</m>, we return to the function <m>f</m>, minus the constant value <m>f(a)</m>. So in this situation, the two processes almost undo one another, up to the constant <m>f(a)</m>.</p>

    <p>The observations made in the preceding two paragraphs demonstrate that differentiating and integrating (where we integrate from a constant up to a variable) are almost inverse processes. In one sense, this should not be surprising: integrating involves antidifferentiating, which reverses the process of differentiating. On the other hand, we see that there is some subtlety involved, as integrating the derivative of a function does not quite produce the function itself. This is connected to a key fact we observed in <xref ref="sec-5-1-antid-graphs">Section</xref>, which is that any function has an entire family of antiderivatives, and any two of those antiderivatives differ only by a constant.</p>

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-5-2-3.xml" />

  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <title>Summary</title>
    <ul>
      <li><p>For a continuous function <m>f</m>, the integral function <m>A(x) = \int_1^x f(t) \, dt</m> defines an antiderivative of <m>f</m>.</p></li>

      <li><p>The Second Fundamental Theorem of Calculus is the formal, more general statement of the preceding fact:  if <m>f</m> is a continuous function and <m>c</m> is any constant, then <m>A(x) = \int_c^x f(t) \, dt</m> is the unique antiderivative of <m>f</m> that satisfies <m>A(c) = 0</m>.</p></li>

      <li><p>Together, the First and Second FTC enable us to formally see how differentiation and integration are almost inverse processes through the observations that
          <me>
            \int_c^x \frac{d}{dt} \left[ f(t) \right] \, dt = f(x) - f(c)
          </me>
          and
          <me>
            \frac{d}{dx} \left[ \int_c^x f(t) \, dt \right] = f(x).
          </me>
        </p></li>
    </ul>
  </subsection>
  
    <xi:include href="./exercises/ez-5-2.xml" /> 



</section>