<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<!-- Copyright 2012-2018                                                   -->
<!-- Matthew Boelkins                                                      -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- This file is part of Active Calculus.                                 -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document -->
<!-- under the terms of the Creative Commons BY-SA license.  The work      -->
<!-- may be used for free by any party so long as attribution is given to  -->
<!-- the author(s), the work and its derivatives are used in the spirit of -->
<!-- "share and share alike".  All trademarks are the registered marks of  -->
<!-- their respective owners.                                              -->
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<section xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec-3-4-applied-opt" permid="ZGh">
  <title>Applied Optimization</title>
  <objectives permid="SbI">
    <ul permid="qEs">
      <li permid="CSK">
        <p permid="zYe">
          In a setting where a situation is described for which optimal parameters are sought,
          how do we develop a function that models the situation and use calculus to find the desired maximum or minimum?
        </p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </objectives>

  <introduction permid="yiR">
    <p permid="dkH">
      Near the conclusion of <xref ref="sec-3-3-optimization">Section</xref>,
      we considered two optimization problems where determining the function to be optimized was part of the problem.
      In <xref ref="Ex-3-3-1">Example</xref>,
      we sought to use a single piece of wire to build an equilateral triangle and square
      in order to maximize the total combined area enclosed.
      In the subsequent <xref ref="act-3-3-3">Activity</xref>,
      we investigated how the volume of a box constructed from a piece of cardboard by removing squares from each corner and folding up the sides depends on the size of the squares removed.
    </p>

    <p permid="JrQ">
      In neither of these problems was a function to optimize explicitly provided.
      Rather, we first tried to understand the problem by
      drawing a figure and introducing variables,
      and then sought to develop a formula for a function that modeled the quantity
      to be optimized.
      Once the function was established,
      we then considered what domain was appropriate.
      At that point,
      we were finally ready to apply the ideas of calculus to determine the absolute minimum or maximum.
    </p>

    <p permid="pyZ">
      Throughout what follows in the current section,
      the primary emphasis is on the reader solving problems.
      Initially, some substantial guidance is provided,
      with the problems progressing to require greater independence as we move along.
    </p>

    <xi:include href="./previews/PA-3-4.xml" />
  </introduction>

  <subsection permid="FNq">
    <title>More applied optimization problems</title>
    <p permid="VGi">
      Many of the steps in <xref ref="PA-3-4">Preview Activity</xref>
      are ones that we will execute in any applied optimization problem.
      We briefly summarize those here to provide an overview of our approach in subsequent questions.
    </p>

    <note permid="eqa">
      <p permid="xdy">
        <ul permid="Kxj">
          <li permid="iZT">
            <p permid="gfn">
              Draw a picture and introduce variables.
              It is essential to first understand what quantities are allowed to vary in the problem and then to represent those values with variables.
              Constructing a figure with the variables labeled is almost always an essential first step.
              Sometimes drawing several diagrams can be especially helpful to get a sense of the situation.
              A nice example of this can be seen at <url href="http://gvsu.edu/s/99">http://gvsu.edu/s/99</url>,
              where the choice of where to bend a piece of wire into the shape of a rectangle determines both the rectangle's shape and area.
            </p>
          </li>

          <li permid="Phc">
            <p permid="Mmw">
              Identify the quantity to be optimized as well as any key relationships among the variable quantities.
              Essentially this step involves writing equations that involve the variables that have been introduced:
              one to represent the quantity whose minimum or maximum is sought,
              and possibly others that show how multiple variables in the problem may be interrelated.
            </p>
          </li>

          <li permid="vol">
            <p permid="stF">
              Determine a function of a single variable that models the quantity to be optimized;
              this may involve using other relationships among variables to eliminate one or more variables in the function formula.
              For example, in <xref ref="PA-3-4">Preview Activity</xref>,
              we initially found that <m>V = x^2 y</m>,
              but then the additional relationship that <m>4x + y = 108</m>
              (girth plus length equals 108 inches)
              allows us to relate <m>x</m> and <m>y</m> and thus observe equivalently that <m>y = 108-4x</m>.
              Substituting for <m>y</m> in the volume equation yields <m>V(x) = x^2(108-4x)</m>,
              and thus we have written the volume as a function of the single variable <m>x</m>.
            </p>
          </li>

          <li permid="bvu">
            <p permid="YAO">
              Decide the domain on which to consider the function being optimized.
              Often the physical constraints of the problem will limit the possible values that the independent variable can take on.
              Thinking back to the diagram describing the overall situation and any relationships among variables in the problem often helps identify the smallest and largest values of the input variable.
            </p>
          </li>

          <li permid="HCD">
            <p permid="EHX">
              Use calculus to identify the absolute maximum and/or minimum of the quantity being optimized.
              This always involves finding the critical numbers of the function first.
              Then, depending on the domain,
              we either construct a first derivative sign chart
              (for an open or unbounded interval)
              or evaluate the function at the endpoints and critical numbers
              (for a closed, bounded interval),
              using ideas we've studied so far in <xref ref="C-3">Chapter</xref>.
            </p>
          </li>

          <li permid="nJM">
            <p permid="kPg">
              Finally, we make certain we have answered the question:
              does the question seek the absolute maximum of a quantity,
              or the values of the variables that produce the maximum?
              That is,
              finding the absolute maximum volume of a parcel is different from finding the dimensions of the parcel that produce the maximum.
            </p>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </p>
    </note>

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-3-4-1.xml" />

    <p permid="BNr">
      Familiarity with common geometric formulas is particularly helpful in problems such as the one in <xref ref="act-3-4-1">Activity</xref>.
      Sometimes those involve perimeter,
      area, volume, or surface area.
      At other times,
      the constraints of a problem introduce right triangles
      (where the Pythagorean Theorem applies)
      or other functions whose formulas provide relationships among the variables.
    </p>

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-3-4-2.xml" />

    <p permid="hUA">
      In more geometric problems,
      we often use curves or functions to provide natural constraints.
      For instance,
      we could investigate which isosceles triangle that circumscribes a unit circle has the smallest area,
      which you can explore for yourself at
      <url href="http://gvsu.edu/s/9b">http://gvsu.edu/s/9b</url>.
      Or similarly, for a region bounded by a parabola,
      we might seek the rectangle of largest area that fits beneath the curve,
      as shown at
      <url href="http://gvsu.edu/s/9c">http://gvsu.edu/s/9c</url>.
      The next activity is similar to the latter problem.
    </p>

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-3-4-3.xml" />

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-3-4-4.xml" />
  </subsection>

  <reading-questions>

    <exercise>
      <p>
        Suppose you are building an open rectangular box (no top) with a square base.  Say that the length of one side of the base is <m>x</m>, and the height of the box is <m>y</m>.  What is the surface area of the box?
      </p>
    </exercise>
  
    <exercise>
      <p>
        Suppose we want to build a box whose surface area is exactly <m>10</m> square units, so we must have the constraint that <m>10 = x^2 + 4xy</m>.  Solve this equation for <m>y</m> to write <m>y</m> in terms of <m>x</m>.
      </p>
    </exercise>
  
    <exercise>
      <p>
        Recall that the volume of a rectangular box is the product of its length, width, and height, so the volume of the box described above is 
        <me>
          V = x^2 y
        </me>.
        Use your work with the constraint equation to write <m>V</m> as a function of the single variable <m>x</m>.  How might you then investigate where the function <m>V</m> is maximized?
      </p>
    </exercise>
  
  </reading-questions>

  <subsection permid="lUz">
    <title>Summary</title>
    <p permid="ObJ">
      <ul permid="WLB">
        <li permid="TQV">
          <p permid="QWp">
            While there is no single algorithm that works in every situation where optimization is used,
            in most of the problems we consider,
            the following steps are helpful:
            draw a picture and introduce variables;
            identify the quantity to be optimized and find relationships among the variables;
            determine a function of a single variable that models the quantity to be optimized;
            decide the domain on which to consider the function being optimized;
            use calculus to identify the absolute maximum and/or minimum of the quantity being optimized.
          </p>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <xi:include href="./exercises/ez-3-4.xml" />
</section>

