<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<!-- Copyright 2012-2019                                                   -->
<!-- Matthew Boelkins                                                      -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- This file is part of Active Calculus.                                 -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document -->
<!-- under the terms of the Creative Commons BY-SA license.  The work      -->
<!-- may be used for free by any party so long as attribution is given to  -->
<!-- the author(s), the work and its derivatives are used in the spirit of -->
<!-- "share and share alike".  All trademarks are the registered marks of  -->
<!-- their respective owners.                                              -->
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<section xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec-1-5-units" permid="IVE">
  <title>Interpreting, estimating, and using the derivative</title>
  <objectives permid="NFx">
    <ul permid="mih">
      <li permid="ywz">
        <p permid="PuK">
          In contexts other than the position of a moving object,
          what does the derivative of a function measure?
        </p>
      </li>

      <li permid="eDI">
        <p permid="vBT">
          What are the units on the derivative function <m>f'</m>,
          and how are they related to the units of the original function <m>f</m>?
        </p>
      </li>

      <li permid="KKR">
        <p permid="bJc">
          What is a central difference,
          and how can one be used to estimate the value of the derivative at a point from given function data?
        </p>
      </li>

      <li permid="qSa">
        <p permid="HQl">
          Given the value of the derivative of a function at a point,
          what can we infer about how the value of the function changes nearby?
        </p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </objectives>

  <introduction permid="tMG">
    <p permid="lcO">
      It is a powerful feature of mathematics that it can be studied both as abstract discipline and as an applied one.
      For instance,
      calculus can be developed almost entirely as an abstract collection of ideas that focus on properties of functions.
      At the same time,
      if we consider functions that represent meaningful processes,
      calculus can describe our experience of physical reality.
      We have already seen that for the position function
      <m>y = s(t)</m> of a ball being tossed straight up in the air,
      the derivative of the position function,
      <m>v(t) = s'(t)</m>, gives the ball's velocity at time <m>t</m>.
    </p>

    <p permid="RjX">
      In this section,
      we investigate several functions with specific physical meaning,
      and consider how the units on the independent variable,
      dependent variable,
      and the derivative function add to our understanding.
      To start, we consider the familiar problem of a position function of a moving object.
    </p>

    <xi:include href="./previews/PA-1-5.xml" />
  </introduction>

  <subsection permid="pcN">
    <title>Units of the derivative function</title>
    <p permid="xrg">
      As we now know,
      the derivative of the function <m>f</m> at a fixed value <m>x</m> is given by
      <me permid="zgt">
        f'(x) = \lim_{h \to 0} \frac{f(x+h)-f(x)}{h}
      </me>,
      and this value has several different interpretations.
      If we set <m>x = a</m>,
      one meaning of <m>f'(a)</m> is the slope of the tangent line at the point <m>(a,f(a))</m>.
    </p>

    <p permid="dyp">
      We also sometimes write <m>\frac{df}{dx}</m> or
      <m>\frac{dy}{dx}</m> instead of <m>f'(x)</m>,
      and these alternate notations help us see the units
      (and thus the meaning)
      of the derivative as
      <em>the instantaneous rate of change of <m>f</m> with respect to <m>x</m></em>.
          <idx><h>instantaneous rate of change</h></idx>
      The units on the slope of the secant line,
      <m>\frac{f(x+h)-f(x)}{h}</m>,
      are <q>units of <m>y</m> per unit of <m>x</m>,</q> and
      when we take the limit as <m>h</m> goes to zero,
      the derivative <m>f'(x)</m> has the same units:
      units of <m>y</m> per unit of <m>x</m>.

      It is helpful to remember that the units on the derivative function are
      <q>units of output per unit of input,</q> for the variables
      of the original function.
    </p>

    <p permid="JFy">
      For example, suppose that the function <m>y = P(t)</m>
      measures the population of a city
      (in thousands)
      at the start of year <m>t</m>
      (where <m>t = 0</m> corresponds to 2010 AD).
      We are told that <m>P'(2) = 21.37</m>.
      What is the meaning of this value?
      Well, since <m>P</m> is measured in thousands and <m>t</m> is measured in years,
      we can say that the instantaneous rate of change of the city's population with respect to time at the start of 2012 is 21.37 thousand people per year.
      We therefore expect that in the coming year,
      about 21,370 people will be added to the city's population.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection permid="VjW">
    <title>Toward more accurate derivative estimates</title>
    <p permid="pMH">
      Recall that to estimate the value of <m>f'(x)</m> at a given <m>x</m>,
      we calculate a <em>difference quotient</em>
          <idx><h>difference quotient</h></idx>
      <m>\frac{f(x+h)-f(x)}{h}</m> with a relatively small value of <m>h</m>.
      We should use both positive and negative values of <m>h</m> in order to account for the behavior of the function on both sides of the point of interest.
      To that end, we introduce the notion of a
      <em>central difference</em>
      and its role in estimating derivatives.
    </p>

    <example xml:id="Ex-1-5-1" permid="hyo">
      <statement>
        <p permid="EVF">
          Suppose that <m>y = f(x)</m> is a function for which three values are known:
          <m>f(1) = 2.5</m>, <m>f(2) = 3.25</m>, and <m>f(3) = 3.625</m>.
          Estimate <m>f'(2)</m>.
        </p>
      </statement>
      <solution permid="ZTP">
        <p permid="gsV">
          We know that <m>f'(2) = \lim_{h \to 0} \frac{f(2+h) - f(2)}{h}</m>.
          But since we don't have a graph or a formula for the function,
          we can neither sketch a tangent line nor evaluate the limit algebraically.
          We can't even use smaller and smaller values of <m>h</m> to estimate the limit.
          Instead, we have just two choices:
          using <m>h = -1</m> or <m>h = 1</m>,
          depending on which point we pair with <m>(2,3.25)</m>.
        </p>

        <p permid="MAe">
          So, one estimate is
          <me permid="fnC">
            f'(2) \approx \frac{f(1)-f(2)}{1-2} = \frac{2.5-3.25}{-1} = 0.75
          </me>.
        </p>

        <p permid="sHn">
          The other is
          <me permid="LuL">
            f'(2) \approx \frac{f(3)-f(2)}{3-2} = \frac{3.625-3.25}{1} = 0.375
          </me>.
        </p>

        <p permid="YOw">
          Because the first approximation looks backward from the point
          <m>(2,3.25)</m> and the second approximation looks forward,
          it makes sense to average these two estimates in order to account for behavior on both sides of <m>x=2</m>.
          Doing so, we find that
          <me permid="rBU">
            f'(2) \approx \frac{0.75 + 0.375}{2} = 0.5625
          </me>.
        </p>
      </solution>
    </example>

    <p permid="VTQ">
      The intuitive approach to average the two estimates found in <xref ref="Ex-1-5-1">Example</xref>
      is in fact the best possible way estimate to a derivative when we have just two function values for <m>f</m> on opposite sides of the point of interest.
    </p>

    <figure xml:id="F-1-5-Ex1" permid="GKS">
      <caption>At left, the graph of <m>y = f(x)</m> along with the secant line through <m>(1,2.5)</m> and <m>(2,3.25)</m>, the secant line through <m>(2, 3.25)</m> and <m>(3,3.625)</m>, as well as the tangent line.  At right, the same graph along with the secant line through <m>(1,2.5)</m> and <m>(3,3.625)</m>, plus the tangent line.</caption>
      <image width="100%" source="images/1_5_Ex1" />
    </figure>

    <p permid="CaZ">
      To see why,
      we think about the diagram in <xref ref="F-1-5-Ex1">Figure</xref>.
      On the left,
      we see the two secant lines with slopes that come from computing the
      <em>backward difference</em>
          <idx><h>backward difference</h></idx>
      <m>\frac{f(1)-f(2)}{1-2} = 0.75</m> and from the
      <em>forward difference</em>
          <idx><h>forward difference</h></idx>
      <m>\frac{f(3)-f(2)}{3-2} = 0.375</m>.
      Note how the first slope over-estimates the slope of the tangent line at <m>(2,f(2))</m>,
      while the second slope underestimates <m>f'(2)</m>.
      On the right, we see the secant line whose slope is given by the
      <em>central difference</em>
          <idx><h>central difference</h></idx>
      <me permid="XJd">
        \frac{f(3)-f(1)}{3-1} = \frac{3.625-2.5}{2} = \frac{1.125}{2} = 0.5625
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p permid="iii">
      Note that this central difference has the same value as the average of the forward and backward differences
      (and it is straightforward to explain why this always holds).
      The central difference yields a very good approximation to the derivative's value,
      because it yields a line closer to being parallel to the tangent line.
    </p>

    <p permid="Opr">
      The <term>central difference approximation</term>
      to the value of the first derivative is given by
      <me permid="DQm">
        f'(a) \approx \frac{f(a+h) - f(a-h)}{2h}
      </me>.
      This quantity measures the slope of the secant line to <m>y = f(x)</m> through the points
      <m>(a-h, f(a-h))</m> and <m>(a+h, f(a+h))</m>.
    </p>

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-1-5-1.xml" />

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-1-5-2.xml" />

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-1-5-3.xml" />

    <p permid="uwA">
      In <xref ref="sec-1-4-derivative-fxn">Section</xref>,
      we learned how use to the graph of a given function <m>f</m> to plot the graph of its derivative,
      <m>f'</m>.
      It is important to remember that when we do so,
      the scale and the units on the vertical axis often have to change to represent <m>f'</m>.
      For example, suppose that
      <m>P(t) = 400-330e^{-0.03t}</m> tells us the temperature in degrees Fahrenheit of a potato in an oven at time <m>t</m> in minutes.
      In <xref ref="F-1-5-PPprime">Figure</xref>,
      we sketch the graph of <m>P</m> on the left and the graph of <m>P'</m> on the right.
    </p>

    <figure xml:id="F-1-5-PPprime" permid="mSb">
      <caption>Plot of <m>P(t) = 400-330e^{-0.03t}</m> at left, and its derivative <m>P'(t)</m> at right.</caption>
      <image width="100%" source="images/1_5_PPprimeplot" />
    </figure>

    <p permid="aDJ">
      Notice that the vertical scales different are in size
      and different in units,
      as the units of <m>P</m> are
      <m>^{\circ}</m>F, while those of <m>P'</m> are <m>^{\circ}</m>F/min.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection permid="Brf">
    <title>Summary</title>
    <p permid="SZk">
      <ul permid="Spq">
        <li permid="WZj">
          <p permid="nXu">
            The derivative of a given function <m>y=f(x)</m> measures the instantaneous rate of change of the output variable with respect to the input variable.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="Dgs">
          <p permid="UeD">
            The units on the derivative function
            <m>y = f'(x)</m> are units of <m>y</m> per unit of <m>x</m>.
            Again,
            this measures how fast the output of the function <m>f</m> changes when the input of the function changes.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="jnB">
          <p permid="AlM">
            The central difference approximation to the value of the first derivative is given by
            <me permid="jXv">
              f'(a) \approx \frac{f(a+h) - f(a-h)}{2h}
            </me>.
            This quantity measures the slope of the secant line to <m>y = f(x)</m> through the points
            <m>(a-h, f(a-h))</m> and <m>(a+h, f(a+h))</m>.
            The central difference generates a good approximation of the derivative's value.
          </p>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <xi:include href="./exercises/ez-1-5.xml" />
</section>

