<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<!-- Copyright 2012-2017                                                   -->
<!-- Matthew Boelkins                                                      -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- This file is part of Active Calculus.                                 -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document -->
<!-- under the terms of the Creative Commons BY-NC-SA license.  The work   -->
<!-- may be used for free by any party so long as attribution is given to  -->
<!-- the author(s), the work and its derivatives are used in the spirit of -->
<!-- "share and share alike"; no party may sell this work or any of its    -->
<!-- derivatives for profit.  All trademarks are the registered marks of   -->
<!-- their respective owners.                                              -->
<!-- **********************************************************************-->

<section xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec-4-4-FTC">
  <title>The Fundamental Theorem of Calculus</title>
  <objectives>
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>
          How can we find the exact value of a definite integral without taking the limit of a Riemann sum?
        </p>
      </li>

      <li>
        <p>
          What is the statement of the Fundamental Theorem of Calculus,
          and how do antiderivatives of functions play a key role in applying the theorem?
        </p>
      </li>

      <li>
        <p>
          What is the meaning of the definite integral of a rate of change in contexts other than when the rate of change represents velocity?
        </p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </objectives>
  <introduction>
    <p>
      Much of our work in <xref ref="C-4">Chapter</xref>
      has been motivated by the velocity-distance problem:
      if we know the instantaneous velocity function, <m>v(t)</m>,
      for a moving object on a given time interval <m>[a,b]</m>,
      can we determine the distance it traveled on <m>[a,b]</m>?
      If the velocity function is nonnegative on <m>[a,b]</m>, the area bounded by
      <m>y = v(t)</m> and the <m>t</m>-axis on <m>[a,b]</m> is equal to the distance traveled.
      This area is also the value of the definite integral <m>\int_a^b v(t) \, dt</m>.
      If the velocity is sometimes negative,
      the total area bounded by the velocity function still tells us distance traveled,
      while the net signed area tells us the object's change in position.
    </p>

    <sidebyside widths="47% 47%" margins="0%">
      <p>
       For instance, for the velocity function in <xref ref="F-4-4-Intro">Figure</xref>,
        the total distance <m>D</m> traveled by the moving object on <m>[a,b]</m> is
        <me>
          D = A_1 + A_2 + A_3
        </me>,
        and the total change in the object's position is
        <me>
          s(b) - s(a) = A_1 - A_2 + A_3
        </me>.
        The areas <m>A_1</m>, <m>A_2</m>,
        and <m>A_3</m> are each given by definite integrals, which
        may be computed by limits of Riemann sums (and in special circumstances by geometric formulas).
      </p>

      <figure xml:id="F-4-4-Intro">
        <caption>A velocity function that is sometimes negative.</caption>
        <image source="images/4_2_Intro" />
      </figure>
    </sidebyside>
    <p>
      We turn our attention to an alternate approach.
    </p>

    <xi:include href="./previews/PA-4-4.xml" />
  </introduction>

  <subsection>
    <title>The Fundamental Theorem of Calculus</title>
    <idx><h>fundamental theorem of calculus</h></idx>

    <figure xml:id="F-4-4-FTCVel">
      <caption>Finding distance traveled when we know a velocity function <m>v</m>.</caption>
      <sidebyside widths="47% 47%" margins="0%">
        <image source="images/4_4_FTCVel" />
        <p>
          Suppose we know the position function <m>s(t)</m> and the velocity function <m>v(t)</m> of an object moving in a straight line,
          and for the moment let us assume that <m>v(t)</m> is positive on <m>[a,b]</m>.
          Then, as shown in <xref ref="F-4-4-FTCVel">Figure</xref>,
          we know two different ways to compute the distance,
          <m>D</m>, the object travels:
          one is that <m>D = s(b) - s(a)</m>,
          the object's change in position.
          The other is the area under the velocity curve,
          which is given by the definite integral,
          so <m>D = \int_a^b v(t) \, dt</m>.
        </p>
      </sidebyside>
    </figure>

    <p>
      Since both of these expressions tell us the distance traveled,
      it follows that they are equal, so
      <men xml:id="E-FTCVel">
        s(b) - s(a) = \int_a^b v(t) \, dt
      </men>.
    </p>

    <p>
      <xref ref="E-FTCVel">Equation</xref> holds even when velocity is sometimes negative,
      because <m>s(b) - s(a)</m>,the object's change in position,
      is also measured by the net signed area on <m>[a,b]</m> which is given by <m>\int_a^b v(t) \, dt</m>.
    </p>

    <p>
      Perhaps the most powerful fact <xref ref="E-FTCVel">Equation</xref> reveals is that we can compute the integral's value if we can find a formula for <m>s</m>.
      Remember, <m>s</m> and <m>v</m> are related by the fact that <m>v</m> is the derivative of <m>s</m>,
      or equivalently that <m>s</m> is an antiderivative of <m>v</m>.
    </p>
     
  <p> 
    <example xml:id="Ex-FTCVel">
      <statement>
        <p>
          Determine the exact distance traveled on <m>[1,5]</m> by an object with velocity function <m>v(t) = 3t^2 + 40</m> feet per second.

          The distance traveled on the interval <m>[1,5]</m> is given by
          <me>
            D  =  \int_1^5 v(t) \,dt  =  \int_1^5 (3t^2 + 40) \, dt  =   s(5) - s(1)
          </me>,
          where <m>s</m> is an antiderivative of <m>v</m>.
          Now, the derivative of <m>t^3</m> is <m>3t^2</m> and the derivative of <m>40t</m> is <m>40</m>,
          so it follows that <m>s(t) = t^3 + 40t</m> is an antiderivative of <m>v</m>.
          Therefore,
          <md>
            <mrow>D &amp;= \int_1^5 3t^2 + 40 \, dt  = s(5) - s(1)</mrow>
            <mrow>  &amp;=  (5^3 + 40 \cdot 5) - (1^3 + 40\cdot 1) = 284 \ \text{feet}</mrow>
          </md>.
        </p>        
      </statement>
    </example>  
  </p>

    <sidebyside widths="47% 47%" margins="0%">
      <p>
        Note the key lesson of <xref ref="Ex-FTCVel">Example</xref>:
        to find the distance traveled,
        we need to compute the area under a curve,
        which is given by the definite integral.
        But to evaluate the integral,
        we can find an antiderivative, <m>s</m>, of the velocity function,
        and then compute the total change in <m>s</m> on the interval.
        In particular, we can evaluate the integral without computing the limit of a Riemann sum.
      </p>

      <figure xml:id="F-4-4-FTCVel2">
        <caption>The exact area of the region enclosed by <m>v(t) = 3t^2 + 40</m> on <m>[1,5]</m>.</caption>
        <image source="images/4_4_FTCVel2" />
      </figure>
    </sidebyside>
    <p>
      It will be convenient to have a shorthand symbol for a function's antiderivative.
      For a continuous function <m>f</m>,
      we will often denote an antiderivative of <m>f</m> by <m>F</m>,
      so that 
      <m>F'(x) = f(x)</m> for all relevant <m>x</m>.
      Using the notation <m>V</m> in place of <m>s</m>
      (so that <m>V</m> is an antiderivative of <m>v</m>)
      in Equation<nbsp /><xref ref="E-FTCVel" />, we can write
      <men xml:id="E-FTCV">
        V(b) - V(a) = \int_a^b v(t) \, dt
      </men>.
    </p>

    <p>
      Now, to evaluate the definite integral
      <m>\int_a^b f(x) \, dx</m> for an arbitrary continuous function <m>f</m>,
      we could certainly think of <m>f</m> as representing the velocity of some moving object,
      and <m>x</m> as the variable that represents time.
      But <xref ref="E-FTCVel">Equations</xref> and<nbsp /><xref ref="E-FTCV" /> hold for any 
      continuous velocity function,
      even when <m>v</m> is sometimes negative.
      So <xref ref="E-FTCV">Equation</xref> offers a shortcut route to evaluating any definite integral,
      provided that we can find an antiderivative of the integrand.
      The Fundamental Theorem of Calculus (FTC)
          <idx><h>FTC</h></idx>
      summarizes these observations.
    </p>

    <assemblage xml:id="FTC">
      <title>Fundamental Theorem of Calculus</title>
      <p>
            <idx><h>fundamental theorem of calculus</h></idx>
        If <m>f</m> is a continuous function on <m>[a,b]</m>,
        and <m>F</m> is any antiderivative of <m>f</m>,
        then <m>\int_a^b f(x) \, dx = F(b) - F(a)</m>.
      </p>
    </assemblage>

    <p>
      A common alternate notation for <m>F(b) - F(a)</m> is
      <me>
        F(b) - F(a) = \left.
        F(x) \right|_a^b
      </me>,
      where we read the righthand side as
      <q>the function <m>F</m> evaluated from <m>a</m> to <m>b</m>.</q>
      In this notation, the FTC says that
      <me>
        \int_a^b f(x) \, dx = \left.
        F(x) \right|_a^b
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p>
      The FTC opens the door to evaluating a wide range of integrals if we can find an antiderivative <m>F</m> for the integrand <m>f</m>.
      For instance since <m>\frac{d}{dx}[\frac{1}{3}x^3] = x^2</m>,
      the FTC tells us that
      <md>
        <mrow>\int_0^1 x^2 \, dx =\mathstrut \amp  \left. \frac{1}{3} \, x^3 \right|_0^1</mrow>
        <mrow>=\mathstrut \amp  \frac{1}{3} \, (1)^3 - \frac{1}{3} \, (0)^3</mrow>
        <mrow>=\mathstrut \amp  \frac{1}{3}</mrow>
      </md>.
    </p>

    <p>
      But finding an antiderivative can be far from simple; it is often difficult or even impossible.
      While we can differentiate just about any function,
      even some relatively simple functions don't have an elementary antiderivative.
      A significant portion of integral calculus
      (which is the main focus of second semester college calculus)
      is devoted to the problem of finding antiderivatives.
    </p>

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-4-4-1.xml" />
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <title>Basic antiderivatives</title>
    <p>
      The general problem of finding an antiderivative is difficult.
      In part, this is due to the fact that we are trying to undo the process of differentiating,
      and the undoing is much more difficult than the doing.
      For example,
      while it is evident that an antiderivative of <m>f(x) = \sin(x)</m> is
      <m>F(x) = -\cos(x)</m> and that an antiderivative of
      <m>g(x) = x^2</m> is <m>G(x) = \frac{1}{3} x^3</m>,
      combinations of <m>f</m> and <m>g</m> can be far more complicated.
      Consider the functions 
      <me>
        5\sin(x) - 4x^2, \ x^2 \sin(x), \ \frac{\sin(x)}{x^2}, \ \text{and}  \ \sin(x^2)
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p>
      What is involved in trying to find an antiderivative for each?
      From our experience with derivative rules,
      we know that derivatives of sums and constant multiples of basic functions are simple to execute, but
      derivatives involving products, quotients,
      and composites of familiar functions are more complicated.
      Therefore, it stands to reason that antidifferentiating products,
      quotients,
      and composites of basic functions may be even more challenging.
      We defer our study of all but the most elementary antiderivatives to later in the text.
    </p>

    <p>
      We do note that whenever we know the derivative of a function,
      we have a <em>function-derivative pair</em>,
      so we also know the antiderivative of a function.
      For instance, since we know that
      <me>
        \frac{d}{dx}[-\cos(x)] = \sin(x)
      </me>,
      we also know that <m>F(x) = -\cos(x)</m> is an antiderivative of <m>f(x) = \sin(x)</m>.
      <m>F</m> and <m>f</m> together form a function-derivative pair.
      Clearly, every basic derivative rule leads us to such a pair,
      and thus to a known antiderivative.</p>
      
      <p>In <xref ref="act-4-4-2">Activity</xref>,
      we will construct a list of the basic antiderivatives we know at this time. Those rules will help us  antidifferentiate sums and constant multiples of basic functions.
      For example, since <m>-\cos(x)</m> is an antiderivative of <m>\sin(x)</m> and
      <m>\frac{1}{3}x^3</m> is an antiderivative of <m>x^2</m>,
      it follows that
      <me>
        F(x) = -5\cos(x) - \frac{4}{3}x^3
      </me>
      is an antiderivative of <m>f(x) = 5\sin(x) - 4x^2</m>,
      by the sum and constant multiple rules for differentiation.
    </p>

    <p>
      Finally, before proceeding to build a list of common functions whose antiderivatives we know,
      we recall that each function has more than one antiderivative.
      Because the derivative of any constant is zero,
      we may add a constant of our choice to 
      any antiderivative.
      For instance, we know that <m>G(x) = \frac{1}{3}x^3</m> is an antiderivative of <m>g(x) = x^2</m>.
      But we could also have chosen <m>G(x) = \frac{1}{3}x^3 + 7</m>,
      since in this case as well, <m>G'(x) = x^2</m>.
      
      If <m>g(x) = x^2</m>, we say that the
      <em>general antiderivative</em>
          <idx><h>antiderivative</h><h>general</h></idx>
      of <m>g</m> is
      <me>
        G(x) = \frac{1}{3}x^3 + C
      </me>,
      where <m>C</m> represents an arbitrary real number constant.
      Regardless of the formula for <m>g</m>,
      including <m>+C</m> in the formula for its antiderivative <m>G</m> results in the most general possible antiderivative.
    </p>

    <p>
      Our current interest in antiderivatives is so that we can evaluate definite integrals 
      by the Fundamental Theorem of Calculus.
      For that task, the constant <m>C</m> is irrelevant,
      and we usually omit it.
      To see why, consider the definite integral
      <me>
        \int_0^1 x^2 \, dx
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p>
      For the integrand <m>g(x) = x^2</m>,
      suppose we find and use the general antiderivative <m>G(x) = \frac{1}{3} x^3 + C</m>.
      Then, by the FTC,
      <md>
        <mrow>\int_0^1 x^2 \, dx &amp;=  \left. \frac{1}{3} x^3 + C \right|_0^1</mrow>
        <mrow>   &amp;= \left(\frac{1}{3} (1)^3 + C  \right) - \left(\frac{1}{3} (0)^3 + C  \right)</mrow>
        <mrow>   &amp;= \frac{1}{3} + C - 0 - C</mrow>
        <mrow>   &amp;= \frac{1}{3}</mrow>
      </md>.
    </p>

    <p>
      Observe that the <m>C</m>-values appear as opposites in the evaluation of the integral and thus do not affect the definite integral's value.
       </p>

    <p>
      In the following activity,
      we work to build a list of basic functions whose antiderivatives we already know.
    </p>

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-4-4-2.xml" />
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <title>The total change theorem</title>
    <idx><h>total change theorem</h></idx>

    <p>
      Let us review three interpretations of the definite integral.

      <ul>
        <li>
          <p>
            For a moving object with instantaneous velocity <m>v(t)</m>,
            the object's change in position on the time interval <m>[a,b]</m> is given by <m>\int_a^b v(t) \, dt</m>,
            and whenever <m>v(t) \ge 0</m> on <m>[a,b]</m>,
            <m>\int_a^b v(t) \, dt</m> tells us the total distance traveled by the object on <m>[a,b]</m>.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li>
          <p>
            For any continuous function <m>f</m>,
            its definite integral
      <m>\int_a^b f(x) \, dx</m> represents the net signed area bounded by
            <m>y = f(x)</m> and the <m>x</m>-axis on <m>[a,b]</m>,
            where regions that lie below the <m>x</m>-axis have a minus sign associated with their area.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li>
          <p>
            The value of a definite integral is linked to the average value of a function:
            for a continuous function <m>f</m> on <m>[a,b]</m>,
            its average value <m>f_{\operatorname{AVG} [a,b]}</m> is given by
            <me>
              f_{\operatorname{AVG} [a,b]} = \frac{1}{b-a} \int_a^b f(x) \, dx
            </me>.
          </p>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </p>

    <p>
      The Fundamental Theorem of Calculus now enables us to evaluate exactly
      (without taking a limit of Riemann sums)
      any definite integral for which we are able to find an antiderivative of the integrand.
    </p>

    <p>
      A slight change in perspective allows us to gain even more insight into the meaning of the definite integral.
      Recall <xref ref="E-FTCV">Equation</xref>, where we wrote the Fundamental Theorem of Calculus for a velocity function <m>v</m> with antiderivative <m>V</m> as
      <me>
        V(b) - V(a) = \int_a^b v(t) \, dt
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p>
      If we instead replace <m>V</m> with <m>s</m>
      (which represents position)
      and replace <m>v</m> with <m>s'</m>
      (since velocity is the derivative of position),
      <xref ref="E-FTCV">Equation</xref> then reads as
      <men xml:id="E-FTCs">
        s(b) - s(a) = \int_a^b s'(t) \, dt
      </men>.
    </p>

    <p>
      In words, this version of the FTC tells us that the total change in an object's position function on a particular interval is given by the definite integral of the position function's derivative over that interval.
    </p>

    <p>
      Of course, this result is not limited to only the setting of position and velocity.
      Writing the result in terms of a more general function <m>f</m>,
      we have the Total Change Theorem.
    </p>

    <assemblage xml:id="total-change-theorem">
      <title>Total Change Theorem</title>
      <p>
            <idx><h>total change theorem</h></idx>
        If <m>f</m> is a continuously differentiable function on <m>[a,b]</m> with derivative <m>f'</m>,
        then <m>f(b) - f(a) = \int_a^b f'(x) \, dx</m>.
        That is, the definite integral of the rate of change of a function on <m>[a,b]</m> is the total change of the function itself on <m>[a,b]</m>.
      </p>
    </assemblage>

    <p>
      The Total Change Theorem tells us more about the relationship between the graph of a function and that of its derivative.
      Recall that heights on the graph of the derivative function are equal to slopes on the graph of the function itself.
      If instead we know <m>f'</m> and are seeking information about <m>f</m>,
      we can say the following:
    </p>

    <blockquote>
      <p>
        <em>differences in heights on <m>f</m> correspond to net signed areas bounded by <m>f'</m>.</em>
      </p>
    </blockquote>

    <figure xml:id="F-4-4-TCT">
      <caption>The graphs of <m>f'(x) = 4 - 2x</m> (at left) and an antiderivative <m>f(x) = 4x - x^2</m> at right.  Differences in heights on <m>f</m> correspond to net signed areas bounded by <m>f'</m>.</caption>
      <image width="80%" source="images/4_4_TCT" />
    </figure>

    <p>
      To see why this is so, consider the difference <m>f(1) - f(0)</m>.
      This value is 3, because <m>f(1) = 3</m> and <m>f(0) = 0</m>,
      but also because the net signed area bounded by
      <m>y = f'(x)</m> on <m>[0,1]</m> is 3.
      That is, <me>f(1) - f(0) = \int_0^1 f'(x) \, dx</me>.
      </p>

    <p>
      In addition to this observation about area,
      the Total Change Theorem enables us to answer questions about a function whose rate of change we know.
    </p>

    <example xml:id="Ex-4-4-1">
      <statement>
        <p>
          Suppose that pollutants are leaking out of an underground storage tank at a rate of <m>r(t)</m> gallons/day,
          where <m>t</m> is measured in days.
          It is conjectured that <m>r(t)</m> is given by the formula
          <m>r(t) = 0.0069t^3 -0.125t^2+11.079</m> over a certain 12-day period.
          The graph of <m>y=r(t)</m> is given in <xref ref="F-4-4-TCTEx">Figure</xref>.
          What is the meaning of <m>\int_4^{10} r(t) \, dt</m> and what is its value?
          What is the average rate at which pollutants are leaving the tank on the time interval <m>4 \le t \le 10</m>?
        </p>

        <figure xml:id="F-4-4-TCTEx">
          <caption>The rate <m>r(t)</m> of pollution leaking from a tank, measured in gallons per day.</caption>
          <image width="47%" source="images/4_4_TCTEx" />
        </figure>
      </statement>
      <solution>
        <p>
          Since <m>r(t) \ge 0</m>,
          the value of <m>\int_4^{10} r(t) \, dt</m> is the area under the curve on the interval <m>[4,10]</m>.
          A Riemann sum for this area will have rectangles with heights measured in gallons per day and widths measured in days, so the area of each rectangle will have units of
          <me>
            \frac{\text{gallons} }{\text{day} } \cdot \text{days}  = \text{gallons}
          </me>.
        </p>

        <p>
          Thus, the definite integral tells us the total number of gallons of pollutant that leak from the tank from day 4 to day 10.
          The Total Change Theorem tells us the same thing:
          if we let <m>R(t)</m> denote the total number of gallons of pollutant that have leaked from the tank up to day <m>t</m>,
          then <m>R'(t) = r(t)</m>, and
          <me>
            \int_4^{10} r(t) \, dt = R(10) - R(4)
          </me>,
          the number of gallons that have leaked from day 4 to day 10.
        </p>

        <p>
          To compute the exact value of the integral, we use the Fundamental Theorem of Calculus.
          Antidifferentiating <m>r(t) = 0.0069t^3 -0.125t^2+11.079</m>,
          we find that
          <md>
            <mrow>\int_4^{10} 0.0069t^3 -0.125t^2+11.079 \, dt =\mathstrut \amp  \left. 0.0069 \cdot \frac{1}{4} \, t^4 - 0.125 \cdot \frac{1}{3} t^3 + 11.079t \right|_4^{10}</mrow>
            <mrow>\approx\mathstrut \amp  44.282</mrow>
          </md>.
        </p>

        <p>
          Thus, approximately 44.282 gallons of pollutant leaked over the six day time period.
        </p>

        <p>
          To find the average rate at which pollutant leaked from the tank over <m>4 \le t \le 10</m>,
          we compute the average value of <m>r</m> on <m>[4,10]</m>.
          Thus,
          <me>
            r_{\operatorname{AVG} [4,10]} = \frac{1}{10-4} \int_4^{10} r(t) \, dt \approx \frac{44.282}{6} = 7.380
          </me>
          gallons per day.
        </p>
      </solution>
    </example>

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-4-4-3.xml" />
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <title>Summary</title>
    <p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <p>
            We can find the exact value of a definite integral without taking the limit of a Riemann sum or using a familiar area formula by finding the antiderivative of the integrand,
            and hence applying the Fundamental Theorem of Calculus.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li>
          <p>
            The Fundamental Theorem of Calculus says that if <m>f</m> is a continuous function on <m>[a,b]</m> and <m>F</m> is an antiderivative of <m>f</m>, then
            <me>
              \int_a^b f(x) \, dx = F(b) - F(a)
            </me>.
            Hence,
            if we can find an antiderivative for the integrand <m>f</m>,
            evaluating the definite integral comes from simply computing the change in <m>F</m> on <m>[a,b]</m>.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li>
          <p>
            A slightly different perspective on the FTC allows us to restate it as the Total Change Theorem,
            which says that
            <me>
              \int_a^b f'(x) \, dx = f(b) - f(a)
            </me>,
            for any continuously differentiable function <m>f</m>.
            This means that the definite integral of the instantaneous rate of change of a function <m>f</m> on an interval <m>[a,b]</m> is equal to the total change in the function <m>f</m> on <m>[a,b]</m>.
          </p>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <xi:include href="./exercises/ez-4-4.xml" />
</section>

