<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<!-- Copyright 2012-2019                                                   -->
<!-- Matthew Boelkins                                                      -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- This file is part of Active Calculus.                                 -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document -->
<!-- under the terms of the Creative Commons BY-SA license.  The work      -->
<!-- may be used for free by any party so long as attribution is given to  -->
<!-- the author(s), the work and its derivatives are used in the spirit of -->
<!-- "share and share alike".  All trademarks are the registered marks of  -->
<!-- their respective owners.                                              -->
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<section xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec-8a-1-linear-to-poly">
  <title>From Linear to Polynomial Approximation</title>
  <objectives>
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>
          A
        </p>
      </li>
    </ul>

  </objectives>

  <introduction>
    <p>
      Early in our study of calculus in <xref ref="sec-1-8-tan-line-approx">Section</xref>, we learned that if a function <m>f</m> has a derivative at a fixed value <m>x=a</m>, when we zoom in on its graph near <m>(a,f(a))</m>, the function looks linear.  Indeed, such a function is differentiable, and we know that near a fixed input value <m>a</m>, 
      <me>
        f(x) \approx L(x) = f(a) + f’(a)(x-a),
      </me>
      where <m>L</m> is the tangent line approximation to <m>f</m> at <m>a</m>.

    </p>

    <figure xml:id="F-8a-1-Intro">
      <caption>The function <m>f(x)=e^x</m> and its tangent line <m>L(x)=1+x</m> near the point <m>(0,f(0))</m>.</caption>
      <image width="100%" source="images/8a_1_intro" />
    </figure>

    <p>
      We see in <xref ref="F-8a-1-Intro"></xref> that near the point of tangency, the approximation is quite good; at the same time, the tangent line and the function itself only agree exactly at the point of tangency, and we need not go far away from the point of tangency to have the difference between <m>f</m> and <m>L</m> be substantial.  For example, while ***, ...
    </p>

    <p>
      It is natural to ask:  can we find a simple function that approximates <m>f</m> more closely than <m>L</m> does and for more values of <m>x</m> near <m>a = 0</m>?
    </p>

<!-- 
    <xi:include href="./previews/PA-8a-1.xml" />
-->    
  </introduction>

  <subsection>
    <title>From Linear to Quadratic Approximation</title>
    <idx><h>quadratic approximation</h></idx>
    <!-- think carefully about indexing -->

    <p>
      In Preview Activity **insert xref**, we found that a quadratic function can be used to produce a better approximation to a given function <m>f</m> near a fixed point of interest.  Indeed, this idea is a natural generalization of the tangent line approximation.
    </p>

    <p>
      We know that for any function <m>f</m> that has a derivative at <m>a=0</m>, it follows that its tangent line approximation at <m>a=0</m> is 
      <me>
        L(x) = f(0) + f’(0)(x - 0)
      </me>
      Moreover, we can observe that the functions <m>L</m> and <m>f</m> have two exact values in common.  First, their function values agree at the point of tangency: <m>L(0) = f(0)</m>.  And second, since <m>L(x)</m> is a linear function whose slope is <m>f’(0)</m>, it is also true that their derivative values agree at the point of tangency: <m>L’(0) = f’(0)</m>.
    </p>

    <p>
      To generate a quadratic function that approximates <m>f</m> near <m>a = 0</m>, a natural requirement we could consider is to have this quadratic function not only share the same function value and derivative value as <m>f</m> at <m>a=0</m>, but also -- in order to have the same concavity -- have the same second derivative value at <m>a=0</m>.  We can state these requirements more formally as follows:  we seek a function <m>Q(x)</m> of the form
      <me>
        Q(x) = c_0 + c_1 x + c_2 x^2
      </me>
       *** 
    </p>



<!-- 
    <xi:include href="./activities/act-8a-1-1.xml" />
-->
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <title>Summary</title>
    <p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <p>
            A .
          </p>
        </li>

      </ul>
    </p>
  </subsection>

<!-- 
  <xi:include href="./exercises/ez-8a-1.xml" />
-->

</section>

