<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<!-- Copyright 2012-2018                                                   -->
<!-- Matthew Boelkins                                                      -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- This file is part of Active Calculus.                                 -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document -->
<!-- under the terms of the Creative Commons BY-SA license.  The work      -->
<!-- may be used for free by any party so long as attribution is given to  -->
<!-- the author(s), the work and its derivatives are used in the spirit of -->
<!-- "share and share alike".  All trademarks are the registered marks of  -->
<!-- their respective owners.                                              -->
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<section permid="YPj" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec-4-1-velocity-distance">
  <title>Determining distance traveled from velocity</title>
  <objectives permid="JGl">
    <ul permid="VUD">
      <li permid="iiV">
        <p permid="fop">
          If we know the velocity of a moving body at every point in a given interval,
          can we determine the distance the object has traveled on the time interval?
        </p>
      </li>

      <li permid="Oqe">
        <p permid="Lvy">
          How is the problem of finding distance traveled related to finding the area under a certain curve?
        </p>
      </li>

      <li permid="uxn">
        <p permid="rCH">
          What does it mean to antidifferentiate a function and why is this process relevant to finding distance traveled?
        </p>
      </li>

      <li permid="aEw">
        <p permid="XJQ">
          If velocity is negative,
          how does this impact the problem of finding distance traveled?
        </p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </objectives>

  <introduction permid="pNu">
    <p permid="IAS">
      In the first section of the text,
      we considered a moving object with known position at time <m>t</m>, namely,
      a tennis ball tossed into the air with height <m>s</m>
      (in feet)
      at time <m>t</m>
      (in seconds)
      given by <m>s(t) = 64 - 16(t-1)^2</m>.
      We investigated the average velocity of the ball on an interval <m>[a,b]</m>,
      computed by the difference quotient <m>\frac{s(b)-s(a)}{b-a}</m>.
      We found that we could determine the instantaneous velocity of the ball at time <m>t</m> by taking the derivative of the position function,
      <me permid="BGn">
        s'(t) = \lim_{h \to 0} \frac{s(t+h)-s(t)}{h}
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p permid="oIb">
      Thus, if its position function is differentiable,
      we can find the velocity of a moving object at any point in time.
    </p>

    <p permid="UPk">
      From this study of position and velocity we have learned a great deal.
      We can use the derivative to find a function's instantaneous rate of change at any point in the domain,
      to find where the function is increasing or decreasing,
      where it is concave up or concave down,
      and to locate relative extremes.
      The vast majority of the problems and applications we have considered have involved the situation where a particular function is known and we seek information that relies on knowing the function's instantaneous rate of change.
      For all these tasks,
      we proceed from a function <m>f</m> to its derivative,
      <m>f'</m>,
      and use the meaning of the derivative to help us answer important questions.
    </p>

    <p permid="AWt">
      We have also encountered the reverse situation,
      where we know the derivative of a function,
      <m>f'</m>, and try to deduce information about <m>f</m>.
      We will focus our attention in <xref ref="C-4">Chapter</xref> on this problem:
      if we know the instantaneous rate of change of a function,
      can we find the function itself?
      We start with a more specific question:
      if we know the instantaneous velocity of an object moving along a straight line path,
      can we find its corresponding position function?
    </p>

    <xi:include href="./previews/PA-4-1.xml" />
  </introduction>

  <subsection permid="EWs">
    <title>Area under the graph of the velocity function</title>
    <idx><h>area</h><h>under velocity function</h></idx>

    <p permid="hdC">
      In <xref ref="PA-4-1">Preview Activity</xref>,
      we learned that
      when the velocity of a moving object's velocity is constant
      (and positive),
      the area under the velocity curve over an interval of time tells us the distance the object traveled.
    </p>

    <figure permid="ybN" xml:id="F-4-1-VelArea">
      <caption>At left, a constant velocity function; at right, a non-constant velocity function.</caption>
      <image width="74%" source="images/4_1_VelArea" />
    </figure>

    <p permid="NkL">
      The left-hand graph of <xref ref="F-4-1-VelArea">Figure</xref>
      shows the velocity of an object moving at 2 miles per hour over the time interval <m>[1,1.5]</m>.
      The area <m>A_1</m> of the shaded region under <m>y = v(t)</m> on <m>[1,1.5]</m> is
      <me permid="hNw">
        A_1= 2 \, \frac{\text{miles} }{\text{hour} } \cdot \frac{1}{2} \, \text{hours}  = 1 \, \text{mile}
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p permid="trU">
      This result is simply the fact that distance equals rate times time,
      provided the rate is constant.
      Thus, if <m>v(t)</m> is constant on the interval <m>[a,b]</m>,
      the distance traveled on <m>[a,b]</m> is equal to the area <m>A</m> given by
      <me permid="NUF">
        A = v(a) (b-a) = v(a) \Delta t
      </me>,
      where <m>\Delta t</m> is the change in <m>t</m> over the interval.
      (Since the velocity is constant,
      we can use any value of <m>v(t)</m> on the interval <m>[a,b]</m>,
      we simply chose <m>v(a)</m>,
      the value at the interval's left endpoint.)
      For several examples where the velocity function is piecewise constant, see
      <url href="http://gvsu.edu/s/9T">http://gvsu.edu/s/9T</url>.<fn>
      Marc Renault, calculus applets.
      </fn></p>

    <p permid="Zzd">
      The situation is more complicated when the velocity function is not constant.
      But on relatively small intervals where <m>v(t)</m> does not vary much,
      we can use 
      the area principle to estimate the distance traveled.
      The graph at right in <xref ref="F-4-1-VelArea">Figure</xref>
      shows a non-constant velocity function.
      On the interval <m>[1,1.5]</m>, the
      velocity varies from <m>v(1) = 2.5</m> down to <m>v(1.5) \approx 2.1</m>.
      One estimate for the distance traveled is the area of the pictured rectangle,
      <me permid="ubO">
        A_2 = v(1) \Delta t = 2.5 \, \frac{\text{miles} }{\text{hour} } \cdot \frac{1}{2} \, \text{hours}  = 1.25 \, \text{miles}
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p permid="FGm">
      Note that because <m>v</m> is decreasing on <m>[1,1.5]</m>,
      <m>A_2 = 1.25</m> is an over-estimate of the actual distance traveled.
    </p>
    <!--<sidebyside widths="47% 47%" margins="0%" valign="bottom">-->
    <p permid="lNv">
      To estimate the area under this non-constant velocity function on a wider interval,
      say <m>[0,3]</m>, one rectangle will not give a good approximation.
      Instead, we could use the six rectangles pictured in <xref ref="F-4-1-VelArea2">Figure</xref>,
      find the area of each rectangle, and add up the total.
      Obviously there are choices to make and issues to understand:
      How many rectangles should we use?
      Where should we evaluate the function to decide the rectangle's height?
      What happens if the velocity is sometimes negative?
      Can we find the exact area under any non-constant curve?
    </p>

    <figure permid="eiW" xml:id="F-4-1-VelArea2">
      <caption>Using six rectangles to estimate the area under <m>y = v(t)</m> on <m>[0,3]</m>.</caption>
      <image width="47%" source="images/4_1_VelArea2" />
    </figure>
<!--</sidebyside>-->
    <p permid="RUE">
      We will study these questions and more in what follows;
      for now it suffices to observe that the simple idea of the area of a rectangle gives us a powerful tool for estimating distance traveled from a velocity function,
      as well as for estimating the area under an arbitrary curve.
      To explore the use of multiple rectangles to approximate area under a non-constant velocity function,
      see the applet found at
      <url href="http://gvsu.edu/s/9U">http://gvsu.edu/s/9U</url>.<fn>
      Marc Renault, calculus applets.
      </fn></p>

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-4-1-1.xml" />
  </subsection>

  <subsection permid="ldB">
    <title>Two approaches: area and antidifferentiation</title>
    <idx><h>antidifferentiation</h></idx>
    <idx><h>distance traveled</h></idx>

    <p permid="Kqf">
      When the velocity of a moving object is positive,
      the object's position is always increasing.
      (We will soon consider situations where velocity is negative;
      for now, we focus on the situation where velocity is always positive.) We have established that whenever <m>v</m> is constant on an interval,
      the exact distance traveled is the area under the velocity curve.
      When <m>v</m> is not constant,
      we can estimate the total distance traveled by finding the areas of rectangles that approximate the area under the velocity curve.
    </p>

    <p permid="qxo">
      Thus, we see that finding the area between a curve and the horizontal axis is an important exercise:
      besides being an interesting geometric question,
      if the curve gives the velocity of a moving object,
      the area under the curve tells us the exact distance traveled on an interval.
      We can estimate this area if we have a graph or a table of values for the velocity function.
    </p>

    <p permid="WEx">
      In <xref ref="act-4-1-1">Activity</xref>,
      we encountered an alternate approach to finding the distance traveled.
      If <m>y = v(t)</m> is a formula for the instantaneous velocity
      of a moving object,
      then <m>v</m> must be the derivative of the object's position function,
      <m>s</m>.
      If we can find a formula for <m>s(t)</m> from the formula for <m>v(t)</m>,
      we will know the position of the object at time <m>t</m>,
      and the change in position over a particular time interval tells us the distance traveled on that interval.
    </p>

    <p permid="CLG">
      For a simple example,
      consider the situation from <xref ref="PA-4-1">Preview Activity</xref>,
      where a person is walking along a straight line with velocity function <m>v(t) = 3</m> mph.
    </p>

    <figure permid="Hvz" xml:id="F-4-1-PA1Soln">
      <caption>The velocity function <m>v(t) = 3</m> and corresponding position function <m>s(t) = 3t</m>.</caption>
      <image width="100%" source="images/4_1_PA1Soln" />
    </figure>

    <p permid="iSP">
      On the left-hand graph of the velocity function in <xref ref="F-4-1-PA1Soln">Figure</xref>,
      we see the relationship between area and distance traveled,
      <me permid="aiX">
        A= 3 \, \frac{\text{miles} }{\text{hour} } \cdot 1.25 \, \text{hours}  = 3.75 \, \text{miles}
      </me>.
      In addition, we observe<fn>
      Here we are making the implicit assumption that <m>s(0) = 0</m>;
      we will discuss different possibilities for values of <m>s(0)</m> in subsequent study.
      </fn> that if <m>s(t) = 3t</m>,
      then <m>s'(t) = 3</m>, 
      so <m>s(t) = 3t</m> is the position function whose derivative is the given velocity function,
      <m>v(t) = 3</m>.
      The respective locations of the person at times
      <m>t = 0.25</m> and <m>t = 1.5</m> are
      <m>s(1.5) = 4.5</m> and <m>s(0.25) = 0.75</m>, and therefore
      <me permid="Gqg">
        s(1.5) - s(0.25) = 4.5 - 0.75 = 3.75 \ \text{miles}
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p permid="OZY">
      This is the person's change in position on <m>[0.25,1.5]</m>,
      which is precisely the distance traveled.
      In this example there are profound ideas and connections that we will study throughout <xref ref="C-4">Chapter</xref>.
    </p>

    <p permid="vhh">
      For now, observe that if we know a formula for a velocity function <m>v</m>,
      it can be very helpful to find a function <m>s</m> that satisfies <m>s' = v</m>.
      We say that <m>s</m> is an
      <em>antiderivative</em> of <m>v</m>.
      More generally, we have the following formal definition.
    </p>

    <definition permid="dzc">
      <statement>
        <p permid="ctJ">
          If <m>g</m> and <m>G</m> are functions such that <m>G' = g</m>,
          we say that <m>G</m> is an <term>antiderivative</term>
              <idx><h>antiderivative</h></idx>
          of <m>g</m>.
        </p>
      </statement>
    </definition>

    <p permid="boq">
      For example, if <m>g(x) = 3x^2 + 2x</m>,
      <m>G(x) = x^3 + x^2</m> is an antiderivative of <m>g</m>,
      because <m>G'(x) = g(x)</m>.
      Note that we say <q>an</q>
      antiderivative of <m>g</m> rather than <q>the</q>
      antiderivative of <m>g</m>, because
      <m>H(x) = x^3 + x^2 + 5</m> is also a function whose derivative is <m>g</m>,
      and thus <m>H</m> is another antiderivative of <m>g</m>.
    </p>

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-4-1-2.xml" />
  </subsection>

  <subsection permid="RkK">
    <title>When velocity is negative</title>
    <p permid="nCI">
      The assumption that its velocity is positive on a given interval guarantees that the movement of an object is always in a single direction,
      and hence ensures that its change in position is the same as the distance it travels.
      As we saw in <xref ref="act-4-1-2">Activity</xref>,
      there are natural settings in which an object's velocity is negative, and
      we would like to understand this scenario as well.
    </p>

    <p permid="TJR">
      Consider a simple example where a woman goes for a walk on the beach along a stretch of very straight shoreline that runs east-west.
      We assume that her initial position is <m>s(0) = 0</m>,
      and that her position function increases as she moves east from her starting location.
      For instance,
      <m>s = 1</m> mile represents one mile east of the start location,
      while <m>s = -1</m> tells us she is one mile west of where she began walking on the beach.
    </p>

    <p permid="zRa">
      Now suppose she walks in the following manner.
      From the outset at <m>t = 0</m>,
      she walks due east at a constant rate of <m>3</m> mph for 1.5 hours.
      After 1.5 hours,
      she stops abruptly and begins walking due west at a constant rate of <m>4</m> mph and does so for 0.5 hours.
      Then, after another abrupt stop and start,
      she resumes walking at a constant rate of <m>3</m> mph to the east for one more hour.
      What is the total distance she traveled on the time interval from <m>t = 0</m> to <m>t = 3</m>?
      What the total change in her position over that time?
    </p>

    <p permid="fYj">
      These questions are possible to answer without calculus because the velocity is constant on each interval.
      From <m>t = 0</m> to <m>t = 1.5</m>, she traveled
      <me permid="mxp">
        D_{[0,1.5]} = 3 \ \text{miles per hour}  \cdot 1.5 \ \text{hours}  = 4.5 \ \text{miles}
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p permid="Mfs">
      On <m>t = 1.5</m> to <m>t = 2</m>,
      the distance traveled is
      <me permid="SEy">
        D_{[1.5,2]} = 4 \ \text{miles per hour}  \cdot 0.5 \ \text{hours}  = 2 \ \text{miles}
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p permid="smB">
      Finally, in the last hour she walked
      <me permid="yLH">
        D_{[2,3]} = 3 \ \text{miles per hour}  \cdot 1 \ \text{hours}  = 3 \ \text{miles}
      </me>,
      so the total distance she traveled is
      <me permid="eSQ">
        D = D_{[0,1.5]} + D_{[1.5,2]} + D_{[2,3]} = 4.5 + 2 + 3 = 9.5 \ \text{miles}
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p permid="YtK">
      Since the velocity for <m>1.5 \lt  t \lt  2</m> is <m>v = -4</m>,
      indicating motion in the westward direction,
      the woman first walked 4.5 miles east,
      then 2 miles west, followed by 3 more miles east.
      Thus, the total change in her position is
      <me permid="KZZ">
        \text{change in position}  = 4.5 - 2 + 3 = 5.5 \ \text{miles}
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p permid="EAT">
      We have been able to answer these questions fairly easily,
      and if we think about the problem graphically,
      we can generalize our solution to the more complicated setting when velocity is not constant,
      and possibly negative.
    </p>

    <figure permid="prV" xml:id="F-4-1-NegVel">
      <caption>At left, the velocity function of the person walking; at right, the corresponding position function.</caption>
      <image width="100%" source="images/4_1_NegVel" />
    </figure>

    <p permid="kIc">
      In <xref ref="F-4-1-NegVel">Figure</xref>,
      we see how the distances we computed can be viewed as areas:
      <m>A_1 = 4.5</m> comes from multiplyimg rate times time (<m>3 \cdot 1.5</m>),
      as do <m>A_2</m> and <m>A_3</m>.
      But while <m>A_2</m> is an area
      (and is therefore positive),
      because the velocity function is negative for <m>1.5 \lt t \lt 2</m>,
      this area has a negative sign associated with it.
      The negative area distinguishes between distance traveled and change in position.
    </p>

    <p permid="QPl">
      The distance traveled is the sum of the areas,
      <me permid="rhi">
        D = A_1 + A_2 + A_3 = 4.5 + 2 + 3 = 9.5 \ \text{miles}
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p permid="wWu">
      But the change in position has to account for travel in the negative direction.  
      An area above the <m>t</m>-axis is considered positive because it represents distance traveled in the positive direction,
      while one below the <m>t</m>-axis is viewed as negative because it represents travel in thenegative direction.
      Thus, the change in the woman's position is
      <me permid="Xor">
        s(3) - s(0) = (+4.5) + (-2) + (+3) = 5.5 \ \text{miles}
      </me>.
      In other words,
      the woman walks 4.5 miles in the positive direction,
      followed by two miles in the negative direction,
      and then 3 more miles in the positive direction.
    </p>

    <p permid="ddD">
      Negative velocity is also seen in the graph of the position function <m>y=s(t)</m>.
      Its slope is negative (specifically,
      <m>-4</m>) on the interval
      <m>1.5\lt t\lt 2</m> because the velocity is <m>-4</m> on that interval.
      The negative slope shows the position function is decreasing because the woman is walking east,
      rather than west.
    </p>

    <p permid="JkM">
      To summarize, we see that if velocity is sometimes negative,
      a moving object's change in position different from its distance traveled.
      If we compute separately the distance traveled on each interval where velocity is positive or negative,
      we can calculate either the total distance traveled or the total change in position.
      We assign a negative value to distances traveled in the negative direction when we calculate change in position,
      but a positive value when we calculate the total distance traveled.
    </p>

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-4-1-3.xml" />
  </subsection>

  <subsection permid="xrT">
    <title>Summary</title>
    <p permid="Vze">
      <ul permid="CbM">
        <li permid="GLF">
          <p permid="DQZ">
            If we know the velocity of a moving body at every point in a given interval and the velocity is positive throughout,
            we can estimate the object's distance traveled and in some circumstances determine this value exactly.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="mSO">
          <p permid="jYi">
            In particular, when velocity is positive on an interval,
            we can find the total distance traveled by finding the area under the velocity curve and above the <m>t</m>-axis on the given time interval.
            We may only be able to estimate this area,
            depending on the shape of the velocity curve.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="SZX">
          <p permid="Qfr">
            An antiderivative of a function <m>f</m> is a new function <m>F</m> whose derivative is <m>f</m>.
            That is,
            <m>F</m> is an antiderivative of <m>f</m> provided that <m>F' = f</m>.
            In the context of velocity and position,
            if we know a velocity function <m>v</m>,
            an antiderivative of <m>v</m> is a position function <m>s</m> that satisfies <m>s' = v</m>.
            If <m>v</m> is positive on a given interval,
            say <m>[a,b]</m>, then the change in position, <m>s(b) - s(a)</m>,
            measures the distance the moving object traveled on <m>[a,b]</m>.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="zhg">
          <p permid="wmA">
            If its velocity is sometimes negative,
            a moving object is sometimes traveling in the opposite direction
            or backtracking.
            To determine distance traveled,
            we have to think compute the distance separately on intervals where velocity is positive or negative,
            and account for the change in position on each such interval.
          </p>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <xi:include href="./exercises/ez-4-1.xml" />
</section>

