<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<!-- Copyright 2012-2018                                                   -->
<!-- Matthew Boelkins                                                      -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- This file is part of Active Calculus.                                 -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document -->
<!-- under the terms of the Creative Commons BY-SA license.  The work      -->
<!-- may be used for free by any party so long as attribution is given to  -->
<!-- the author(s), the work and its derivatives are used in the spirit of -->
<!-- "share and share alike".  All trademarks are the registered marks of  -->
<!-- their respective owners.                                              -->
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<section xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec-1-6-second-d" permid="QeE">
  <title>The second derivative</title>
  <objectives permid="NjY">
    <ul permid="Zyq">
      <li permid="lMI">
        <p permid="iSc">
          How does the derivative of a function tell us whether the function is increasing or decreasing at a point or on an interval?
        </p>
      </li>

      <li permid="RTR">
        <p permid="OZl">
          What can we learn by taking the derivative of the derivative
          (the <em>second</em> derivative)
          of a function <m>f</m>?
        </p>
      </li>

      <li permid="yba">
        <p permid="vgu">
          What does it mean to say that a function is concave up or concave down?
          How are these characteristics connected to certain properties of the derivative of the function?
        </p>
      </li>

      <li permid="eij">
        <p permid="bnD">
          What are the units of the second derivative?
          How do they help us understand the rate of change of the rate of change?
        </p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </objectives>

  <introduction permid="trh">
    <p permid="YsX">
      Given a differentiable function <m>y= f(x)</m>,
      we know that its derivative, <m>y = f'(x)</m>,
      is a related function whose output at <m>x=a</m> tells us the slope of the tangent line to
      <m>y = f(x)</m> at the point <m>(a,f(a))</m>.
      That is, heights on the derivative graph tell us the values of slopes on the original function's graph.
    </p>

    <p permid="EAg">
      At a point where <m>f'(x)</m> is positive,
      the slope of the tangent line to <m>f</m> is positive.
      Therefore, on an interval where <m>f'(x)</m> is positive,
      the function <m>f</m> is increasing
      (or rising).
          <idx><h>increasing</h></idx>
      Similarly,
      if <m>f'(x)</m> is negative on an interval,
      the graph of <m>f</m> is decreasing 
          <idx><h>decreasing</h></idx>
      (or falling).
    </p>

    <p permid="kHp">
      The derivative of <m>f</m> tells us not only <em>whether</em>
      the function <m>f</m> is increasing or decreasing on an interval,
      but also <em>how</em> the function <m>f</m> is increasing or decreasing.
      Look at the two tangent lines shown in <xref ref="F-1-6-Intro">Figure</xref>.
      We see that at point <m>A</m>
      the value of <m>f'(x)</m> is positive and relatively close to zero,
      and at that point the graph is rising slowly.
      By contrast, at point <m>B</m>,
      the derivative is negative and relatively large in absolute value,
      and <m>f</m> is decreasing rapidly at <m>B</m>.
    </p>

    <figure xml:id="F-1-6-Intro" permid="dcQ">
      <caption>Two tangent lines on a graph.</caption>
      <image width="45%" source="images/1_6_Intro" />
    </figure>

    <p permid="QOy">
      Besides asking whether the value of the derivative function is positive or negative and whether it is large or small,
      we can also ask <q>how is the derivative changing?</q>
    </p>

    <p permid="wVH">
      Because the derivative,
      <m>y = f'(x)</m>, is itself a function,
      we can consider taking its derivative <mdash /> the derivative of the derivative <mdash /> and ask 
      <q>what does the derivative of the derivative tell us about how the original function behaves?</q>
      We start with an investigation of a moving object.
    </p>

    <xi:include href="./previews/PA-1-6.xml" />
  </introduction>

  <subsection permid="wlN">
    <title>Increasing, decreasing, or neither</title>
    <p permid="JjZ">
      So far,
      we have used the words
      <em>increasing</em> and <em>decreasing</em> intuitively
      to describe a function's graph.
      Here we define these terms more formally.
    </p>

    <definition permid="UOx">
      <statement>
        <p permid="fXw">
          Given a function <m>f(x)</m> defined on the interval <m>(a,b)</m>,
          we say that <term><m>f</m> is increasing on <m>(a,b)</m></term>
          provided that for all <m>x</m>,
          <m>y</m> in the interval <m>(a,b)</m>,
          if <m>x \lt y</m>, then <m>f(x) \lt f(y)</m>.
          Similarly, we say that <term><m>f</m> is decreasing on <m>(a,b)</m></term>
          provided that for all <m>x</m>,
          <m>y</m> in the interval <m>(a,b)</m>,
          if <m>x \lt y</m>, then <m>f(x) \gt f(y)</m>.
        </p>
      </statement>
    </definition>

    <p permid="pri">
      Simply put,
      an increasing function is one that is rising as we move from left to right along the graph,
      and a decreasing function is one that falls as the value of the input increases.
      If the function has a derivative,
      the sign of the derivative tells us whether the function is increasing or decreasing.
    </p>

    <p permid="Vyr">
      Let <m>f</m> be a function that is differentiable on an interval <m>(a,b)</m>.
      It is possible to show that that <m>f</m> is increasing on <m>(a,b)</m> if and only if
      <m>f'(x) > 0</m> for every <m>x</m> such that <m>a \lt x \lt b</m>;
      similarly, <m>f</m> is decreasing on <m>(a,b)</m> if and only if <m>f'(x) \lt 0</m>.
      If <m>f'(a) = 0</m>,
      then <m>f</m> is neither increasing nor decreasing at <m>x = a</m>.
    </p>

    <p permid="BFA">
      For example,
      the function pictured in <xref ref="F-1-6-Intro2">Figure</xref>
      is increasing on the entire interval <m>-2 \lt x \lt 0</m>.
      Note that at both <m>x = \pm 2</m> and <m>x = 0</m>,
      we say that <m>f</m> is neither increasing nor decreasing,
      because <m>f'(x) = 0</m> at these values.
    </p>

    <figure xml:id="F-1-6-Intro2" permid="hMJ">
      <caption>A function that is decreasing on the intervals <m>-3 \lt  x \lt  -2</m> and <m>0 \lt  x  \lt  2</m> and increasing on <m>-2 \lt  x \lt  0</m> and <m>2 \lt  x \lt  3</m>.</caption>
      <image width="47%" source="images/1_6_Intro2" />
    </figure>
  </subsection>

  <subsection permid="csW">
    <title>The Second Derivative</title>
    <idx><h>second derivative</h></idx>

    <p permid="NTS">
      We are now accustomed to investigating the behavior of a function by examining its derivative.
      The derivative of a function <m>f</m>
      is a new function given by the rule
      <me permid="IeG">
        f'(x) = \lim_{h \to 0} \frac{f(x+h)-f(x)}{h}
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p permid="ubb">
      Because <m>f'</m> is itself a function,
      it is perfectly feasible for us to consider the derivative of the derivative,
      which is the new function <m>y = [f'(x)]'</m>.
      We call this resulting function
      <em>the second derivative</em>
          <idx><h>second derivative</h></idx>
      of <m>y = f(x)</m>,
      and denote the second derivative by <m>y = f''(x)</m>.
      Consequently,
      we will sometimes call <m>f'</m>
      <q>the first derivative</q> of <m>f</m>,
      rather than simply <q>the derivative</q> of <m>f</m>.
    </p>

    <definition permid="AVG">
      <statement>
        <p permid="MeF">
          The <term>second derivative</term>
          is defined by the limit definition of the derivative of the first derivative.
          That is,
          <me permid="olP">
            f''(x) = \lim_{h \to 0} \frac{f'(x+h)-f'(x)}{h}
          </me>.
        </p>
      </statement>
    </definition>

    <p permid="aik">
      The meaning of the derivative function still holds,
      so when we compute <m>y = f''(x)</m>,
      this new function measures slopes of tangent lines to the curve <m>y = f'(x)</m>,
      as well as the instantaneous rate of change of <m>y = f'(x)</m>.
      In other words,
      just as the first derivative measures the rate at which the original function changes,
      the second derivative measures the rate at which the first derivative changes.
      The second derivative will help us understand how the rate of change of the original function is itself changing.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection permid="IAf">
    <title>Concavity</title>
    <p permid="Gpt">
      In addition to asking <em>whether</em>
      a function is increasing or decreasing,
      it is also natural to inquire <em>how</em>
      a function is increasing or decreasing.
      There are three basic behaviors that an increasing function can demonstrate on an interval,
      as pictured in <xref ref="F-1-6-3optsi">Figure</xref>:
      the function can increase more and more rapidly,
      it can increase at the same rate,
      or it can increase in a way that is slowing down.
      Fundamentally,
      we are beginning to think about how a particular curve bends,
      with the natural comparison being made to lines, which don't bend at all.
      More than this,
      we want to understand how the bend in a function's graph is tied to behavior characterized by the first derivative of the function.
    </p>

    <figure xml:id="F-1-6-3optsi" permid="jBW">
      <caption>Three functions that are all increasing, but doing so at an increasing rate, at a constant rate, and at a decreasing rate, respectively.</caption>
      <image width="100%" source="images/1_6_3optsi" />
    </figure>

    <p permid="mwC">
      On the leftmost curve in <xref ref="F-1-6-3optsi">Figure</xref>,
      draw a sequence of tangent lines to the curve.
      As we move from left to right,
      the slopes of those tangent lines will increase.
      Therefore, the rate of change of the pictured function is increasing,
      and this explains why we say this function is
      <em>increasing at an increasing rate</em>.
      For the rightmost graph in <xref ref="F-1-6-3optsi">Figure</xref>,
      observe that as <m>x</m> increases,
      the function increases, but the slopes of the tangent lines decrease.
      This function is <em>increasing at a decreasing rate</em>.
    </p>

    <p permid="SDL">
      Similar options hold for how a function can decrease.
      Here we must be extra careful with our language,
      because decreasing functions involve negative slopes.
      Negative numbers present an interesting tension between common language and mathematical language.
      For example, it can be tempting to say that
      <q><m>-100</m> is bigger than <m>-2</m>.</q>
      But we must remember that <q>greater than</q>
      describes how numbers lie on a number line:
      <m>x \gt y</m> provided that <m>x</m> lies to the right of <m>y</m>.
      So of course, <m>-100</m> is less than <m>-2</m>.
      Informally, it might be helpful to say that
      <q><m>-100</m> is more negative than <m>-2</m>.</q>
      When a function's values are negative,
      and those values get more negative as the input increases,
      the function must be decreasing.
    </p>

    <figure xml:id="F-1-6-3optsd" permid="PJf">
      <caption>From left to right, three functions that are all decreasing, but doing so in different ways.</caption>
      <image width="100%" source="images/1_6_3optsd" />
    </figure>

    <p permid="yKU">
      Now consider the three graphs shown in <xref ref="F-1-6-3optsd">Figure</xref>.
      Clearly the middle graph depicts a function decreasing at a constant rate.
      Now, on the first curve, draw a sequence of tangent lines.
      We see that the slopes of these lines get less and less negative as we move from left to right.
      That means that the values of the first derivative,
      while all negative, are increasing,
      and thus we say that the leftmost curve is
      <em>decreasing at an increasing rate</em>.
    </p>

    <p permid="eSd">
      This leaves only the rightmost curve in <xref ref="F-1-6-3optsd">Figure</xref> to consider.
      For that function,
      the slopes of the tangent lines are negative throughout the pictured interval,
      but as we move from left to right,
      the slopes get more and more negative.
      Hence the slope of the curve is decreasing,
      and we say that the function is
      <em>decreasing at a decreasing rate</em>.
    </p>

    <p permid="KZm">
      We now introduce the notion of <em>concavity</em>
          <idx><h>concavity</h></idx>
      which provides simpler language to describe these behaviors.
      When a curve opens upward on a given interval,
      like the parabola <m>y = x^2</m> or the exponential growth function <m>y = e^x</m>,
      we say that the curve is <em>concave up</em> on that interval.
      Likewise, when a curve opens down,
      like the parabola <m>y = -x^2</m> or the opposite of the exponential function <m>y = -e^{x}</m>,
      we say that the function is <em>concave down</em>.
      Concavity is linked to both the first and second derivatives of the function.
    </p>

    <p permid="rgv">
      In <xref ref="F-1-6-concavity">Figure</xref>,
      we see two functions and a sequence of tangent lines to each.
      On the lefthand plot, where the function is concave up,
      observe that the tangent lines always lie below the curve itself, and 
      the slopes of the tangent lines are increasing as we move from left to right.
      In other words,
      the function <m>f</m> is concave up on the interval shown because its derivative,
      <m>f'</m>, is increasing on that interval.
      Similarly, on the righthand plot in <xref ref="F-1-6-concavity">Figure</xref>,
      where the function shown is concave down,
      we see that the tangent lines alway lie above the curve,
      and the slopes of the tangent lines are decreasing as we move from left to right.
      The fact that its derivative,
      <m>f'</m>, is decreasing makes <m>f</m> concave down on the interval.
    </p>

    <figure xml:id="F-1-6-concavity" permid="vQo">
      <caption>At left, a function that is concave up; at right, one that is concave down.</caption>
      <image width="90%" source="images/1_6_concavity" />
    </figure>

    <p permid="XnE">
      We state these most recent observations formally as the definitions of the terms
      <em>concave up</em> and <em>concave down</em>.
    </p>

    <definition permid="hcP">
      <statement>
        <p permid="slO">
          Let <m>f</m> be a differentiable function on an interval <m>(a,b)</m>.
          Then <m>f</m> is <term>concave up</term>
              <idx><h>concave up</h></idx>
          on <m>(a,b)</m> if and only if <m>f'</m> is increasing on <m>(a,b)</m>;
          <m>f</m> is <term>concave down</term>
              <idx><h>concave down</h></idx>
          on <m>(a,b)</m> if and only if <m>f'</m> is decreasing on <m>(a,b)</m>.
        </p>
      </statement>
    </definition>

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-1-6-1.xml" />

    <p permid="DuN">
      Exploring the context of position, velocity,
      and acceleration is an excellent way to understand how a function,
      its first derivative,
      and its second derivative are related to one another.
      In <xref ref="act-1-6-1">Activity</xref>,
      we can replace <m>s</m>, <m>v</m>,
      and <m>a</m> with an arbitrary function <m>f</m> and its derivatives <m>f'</m> and <m>f''</m>,
      and essentially all the same observations hold.
      In particular, note that the following are equivalent:
      on an interval where the graph of <m>f</m> is concave up,
      <m>f'</m> is increasing and <m>f''</m> is positive.
      Likewise, on an interval where the graph of <m>f</m> is concave down,
      <m>f'</m> is decreasing and <m>f''</m> is negative.
    </p>

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-1-6-2.xml" />

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-1-6-3.xml" />
  </subsection>

  <subsection permid="oHo">
    <title>Summary</title>
    <p permid="bXx">
      <ul permid="FFz">
        <li permid="Kps">
          <p permid="HuM">
            A differentiable function <m>f</m> is increasing at a point or on an interval whenever its first derivative is positive,
            and decreasing whenever its first derivative is negative.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="qwB">
          <p permid="nBV">
            By taking the derivative of the derivative of a function <m>f</m>,
            we arrive at the second derivative, <m>f''</m>.
            The second derivative measures the instantaneous rate of change of the first derivative.
            The sign of the second derivative tells us whether the slope of the tangent line to <m>f</m> is increasing or decreasing.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="WDK">
          <p permid="TJe">
            A differentiable function is concave up whenever its first derivative is increasing
            (or equivalently whenever its second derivative is positive),
            and concave down whenever its first derivative is decreasing
            (or equivalently whenever its second derivative is negative).
            Examples of functions that are everywhere concave up are <m>y = x^2</m> and <m>y = e^x</m>;
            examples of functions that are everywhere concave down are <m>y = -x^2</m> and <m>y = -e^x</m>.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="CKT">
          <p permid="zQn">
            The units on the second derivative are
            <q>units of output per unit of input per unit of input.</q>
            They tell us how the value of the derivative function is changing in response to changes in the input.
            In other words,
            the second derivative tells us the rate of change of the rate of change of the original function.
          </p>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <xi:include href="./exercises/ez-1-6.xml" />
</section>

