<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<!-- Copyright 2012-2018                                                   -->
<!-- Matthew Boelkins                                                      -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- This file is part of Active Calculus.                                 -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document -->
<!-- under the terms of the Creative Commons BY-SA license.  The work      -->
<!-- may be used for free by any party so long as attribution is given to  -->
<!-- the author(s), the work and its derivatives are used in the spirit of -->
<!-- "share and share alike".  All trademarks are the registered marks of  -->
<!-- their respective owners.                                              -->
<!-- **********************************************************************-->

<section xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec-6-2-volume">
  <title>Using Definite Integrals to Find Volume</title>
  <objectives>
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>
          How can we use a definite integral to find the volume of a three-dimensional solid of revolution that results from revolving a two-dimensional region about a particular axis?
        </p>
      </li>

      <li>
        <p>
          In what circumstances do we integrate with respect to <m>y</m> instead of integrating with respect to <m>x</m>?
        </p>
      </li>

      <li>
        <p>
          What adjustments do we need to make if we revolve about a line other than the <m>x</m>- or <m>y</m>-axis?
        </p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </objectives>
  <introduction>
    <p>
      Just as we can use definite integrals to add the areas of rectangular slices to find the exact area that lies between two curves,
      we can also use integrals to find the volume of regions whose cross-sections have a particular shape.
    </p>

    <p>
      In particular, we can determine the volume of solids whose cross-sections are all thin cylinders
      (or washers) by adding up the volumes of these individual slices.
      We first consider a familiar shape in <xref ref="PA-6-2">Preview Activity</xref>:
      a circular cone.
    </p>

    <xi:include href="./previews/PA-6-2.xml" />
  </introduction>

  <subsection>
    <title>The Volume of a Solid of Revolution</title>
    <idx><h>solid of revolution</h></idx>

    <p>
      A solid of revolution is a three dimensional solid that can be generated by revolving one or more curves around a fixed axis.
      For example, the circular cone in <xref ref="F-PA-6-2">Figure</xref>
      is the solid of revolution generated by revolving the portion of the line
      <m>y = 3 - \frac{3}{5}x</m> from <m>x = 0</m> to <m>x = 5</m> about the <m>x</m>-axis.
      Notice that if we slice a solid of revolution perpendicular to the axis of revolution,
      the resulting cross-section is a circle.
    </p>

    <p>
      We first consider solids whose slices are thin cylinders.  Recall that the volume of a cylinder is given by <m>V = \pi r^2 h</m>.
    </p>

    <example xml:id="Ex-6-2-Disks">
      <statement>
        <p>
          Find the volume of the solid of revolution generated when the region <m>R</m> bounded by
          <m>y = 4-x^2</m> and the <m>x</m>-axis is revolved about the <m>x</m>-axis.
        </p>
      </statement>

      <solution>
        <p>
          First, we observe that <m>y = 4-x^2</m> intersects the <m>x</m>-axis at the points <m>(-2,0)</m> and <m>(2,0)</m>.
          When we revolve the region <m>R</m> about the <m>x</m>-axis,
          we get the three-dimensional solid pictured in <xref ref="F-6-2-Ex1">Figure</xref>.
        </p>

          <figure xml:id="F-6-2-Ex1">
            <caption>The solid of revolution in <xref ref="Ex-6-2-Disks">Example</xref>.</caption>
            <image width="47%" source="images/6_2_Ex1" />
          </figure>
          <p>
            We slice the solid into vertical slices of thickness <m>\Delta x</m> between <m>x = -2</m> and <m>x = 2</m>.
            A representative slice is a cylinder of height <m>\Delta x</m> and radius <m>4-x^2</m>.
            Hence, the volume of the slice is
            <me>
              V_{\text{slice} } = \pi (4-x^2)^2 \Delta x
            </me>.
          </p>

        <p>
          Using a definite integral to sum the volumes of the representative slices,
          it follows that
          <me>
            V = \int_{-2}^{2} \pi (4-x^2)^2 \, dx
          </me>.
        </p>

        <p>
          It is straightforward to evaluate the integral and find that the volume is <m>V = \frac{512}{15}\pi</m>.
        </p>
      </solution>
    </example>

    <p>
      For a solid such as the one in <xref ref="Ex-6-2-Disks">Example</xref>,
      where each slice is a cylindrical disk,
      we first find the volume of a typical slice
      (noting particularly how this volume depends on <m>x</m>),
      and then integrate over the range of <m>x</m>-values that bound the solid.
      Often, we will be content with simply finding the integral that represents the volume;
      if we desire a numeric value for the integral,
      we typically use a calculator or computer algebra system to find that value.
    </p>

    <p>
      This method for finding the volume of a solid of revolution is often called the <em>disk method</em>.
          <idx><h>disk method</h></idx>
    </p>

    <assemblage>
      <title>The Disk Method</title>
      <p>
        If <m>y = r(x)</m> is a nonnegative continuous function on <m>[a,b]</m>,
        then the volume of the solid of revolution generated by revolving the curve about the <m>x</m>-axis over this interval is given by
        <me>
          V = \int_a^b \pi r(x)^2 \, dx
        </me>.
      </p>
    </assemblage>

    <p>
      A different type of solid can emerge when two curves are involved,
      as we see in the following example.
    </p>

    <example xml:id="Ex-6-2-Washers">
      <statement>
        <p>
          Find the volume of the solid of revolution generated when the finite region <m>R</m> that lies between
          <m>y = 4-x^2</m> and <m>y = x+2</m> is revolved about the <m>x</m>-axis.
        </p>
      </statement>

      <solution>
        <p>
          First, we must determine where the curves
          <m>y = 4-x^2</m> and <m>y = x+2</m> intersect.
          Substituting the expression for <m>y</m> from the second equation into the first equation,
          we find that <m>x + 2 = 4-x^2</m>.
          Rearranging, it follows that
          <me>
            x^2 + x - 2 = 0
          </me>,
          and the solutions to this equation are <m>x = -2</m> and <m>x = 1</m>.
          The curves therefore cross at <m>(-2,0)</m> and <m>(1,1)</m>.
        </p>

        <p>
          When we revolve the region <m>R</m> about the <m>x</m>-axis,
          we get the three-dimensional solid pictured at left in <xref ref="F-6-2-Ex2">Figure</xref>.
        </p>

        <figure xml:id="F-6-2-Ex2">
          <caption>At left, the solid of revolution in <xref ref="Ex-6-2-Washers">Example</xref>.  At right, a typical slice with inner radius <m>r(x)</m> and outer radius <m>R(x)</m>.</caption>
          <sidebyside>
            <image source="images/6_2_Ex2_left" />
            <image source="images/6_2_Ex2_right" />
          </sidebyside>
        </figure>

        <p>
          Immediately we see a major difference between the solid in this example and the one in <xref ref="Ex-6-2-Disks">Example</xref>:
          here, the three-dimensional solid of revolution isn't <q>solid</q>
          because it has open space in its center along the axis of revolution.
          If we slice the solid perpendicular to the axis of revolution,
          we observe that the resulting slice is not a solid disk,
          but rather a <em>washer</em>,
          as pictured at right in <xref ref="F-6-2-Ex2">Figure</xref>.
          At a given location <m>x</m> between <m>x = -2</m> and <m>x = 1</m>,
          the small radius <m>r(x)</m> of the inner circle is determined by the curve <m>y = x+2</m>,
          so <m>r(x) = x+2</m>.
          Similarly, the big radius <m>R(x)</m> comes from the function <m>y = 4-x^2</m>,
          and thus <m>R(x) = 4-x^2</m>.
        </p>

        <p>
          To find the volume of a representative slice,
          we compute the volume of the outer disk and subtract the volume of the inner disk.
          Since
          <me>
            \pi R(x)^2 \Delta x - \pi r(x)^2 \Delta x = \pi [ R(x)^2 - r(x)^2] \Delta x
          </me>,
          it follows that the volume of a typical slice is
          <me>
            V_{\text{slice} } = \pi [ (4-x^2)^2 - (x+2)^2 ] \Delta x
          </me>.
        </p>

        <p>
          Using a definite integral to sum the volumes of the respective slices across the integral,
          we find that
          <me>
            V = \int_{-2}^1 \pi[ (4-x^2)^2 - (x+2)^2 ] \, dx
          </me>.
        </p>

        <p>
          Evaluating the integral, we find that
          the volume of the solid of revolution is <m>V = \frac{108}{5}\pi</m>.
        </p>
      </solution>
    </example>

    <p>
      This method for finding the volume of a solid of revolution generated by two curves is often called the <em>washer method</em>.
          <idx><h>washer method</h></idx>
    </p>

    <assemblage>
      <title>The Washer Method</title>
      <p>
        If <m>y = R(x)</m> and <m>y = r(x)</m> are nonnegative continuous functions on <m>[a,b]</m> that satisfy
        <m>R(x) \ge r(x)</m> for all <m>x</m> in <m>[a,b]</m>,
        then the volume of the solid of revolution generated by revolving the region between them about the <m>x</m>-axis over this interval is given by
        <me>
          V = \int_a^b \pi [R(x)^2 - r(x)^2] \, dx
        </me>.
      </p>
    </assemblage>

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-6-2-1.xml" />
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <title>Revolving about the <m>y</m>-axis</title>
    <p>
      When we revolve a given region about the <m>y</m>-axis, the representative slices now have 
      thickness <m>\Delta y</m>,
      which means that we must integrate with respect to <m>y</m>.
    </p>

    <example xml:id="Ex-6-2-AboutY">
      <statement>
        <p>
          Find the volume of the solid of revolution generated when the region <m>R</m> that lies between
          <m>y = \sqrt{x}</m> and <m>y = x^4</m> is revolved about the <m>y</m>-axis.
        </p>
      </statement>

      <solution>
        <p>
          These two curves intersect when <m>x = 1</m>,
          hence at the point <m>(1,1)</m>.
          When we revolve the region <m>R</m> about the <m>y</m>-axis,
          we get the three-dimensional solid pictured at left in <xref ref="F-6-2-Ex3">Figure</xref>.
        </p>

        <figure xml:id="F-6-2-Ex3">
          <caption>At left, the solid of revolution in <xref ref="Ex-6-2-AboutY">Example</xref>.  At right, a typical slice with inner radius <m>r(y)</m> and outer radius <m>R(y)</m>.</caption>
          <sidebyside>
            <image source="images/6_2_Ex3_left" />
            <image source="images/6_2_Ex3_right" />
          </sidebyside>
        </figure>

        <p>
          Note that the slices are cylindrical washers only if taken perpendicular to the <m>y</m>-axis. 
          We slice the solid horizontally,
          starting at <m>y = 0</m> and proceeding up to <m>y = 1</m>. The thickness of a representative slice is <m>\Delta y</m>, so we must express the integrand in terms of <m>y</m>.
          The inner radius is determined by the curve <m>y = \sqrt{x}</m>,
          so we solve for <m>x</m> and get <m>x = y^2 = r(y)</m>.
          In the same way, we solve the curve <m>y = x^4</m>
          (which governs the outer radius)
          for <m>x</m> in terms of <m>y</m>,
          and hence <m>x = \sqrt[4]{y}</m>.
          Therefore, the volume of a typical slice is
          <me>
            V_{\text{slice} } = \pi [R(y)^2 - r(y)^2] = \pi[(\sqrt[4]{y})^2 - (y^2)^2] \Delta y
          </me>.
        </p>

        <p>
          We use a definite integral to sum the volumes of all the slices from <m>y = 0</m> to <m>y = 1</m>.
          The total volume is
          <me>
            V = \int_{y=0}^{y=1} \pi \left[ (\sqrt[4]{y})^2 - (y^2)^2 \right] \, dy
          </me>.
        </p>

        <p>
          It is straightforward to evaluate the integral and find that <m>V = \frac{7}{15} \pi</m>.
        </p>
      </solution>
    </example>

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-6-2-2.xml" />
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <title>Revolving about horizontal and vertical lines other than the coordinate axes</title>
    <p>
      It is possible to revolve a region around any horizontal or vertical line.
      Doing so adjusts the radii of the cylinders or washers involved by a constant value.
      A careful, well-labeled plot of the solid of revolution will usually reveal how the different axis of revolution affects the definite integral.
    </p>

    <example xml:id="Ex-6-2-AboutNotY">
      <statement>
        <p>
          Find the volume of the solid of revolution generated when the finite region <m>S</m> that lies between <m>y = x^2</m> and <m>y = x</m> is revolved about the line <m>y = -1</m>.
        </p>
      </statement>
      <solution>
          <p>
            Graphing the region between the two curves in the first quadrant between their points of intersection (<m>(0,0)</m> and <m>(1,1)</m>) and then revolving the region about the line <m>y = -1</m>,
            we see the solid shown in <xref ref="F-6-2-Ex4">Figure</xref>.
            Each slice of the solid perpendicular to the axis of revolution is a washer,
            and the radii of each washer are governed by the curves <m>y = x^2</m> and <m>y = x</m>.
            But we also see that there is one added change:
            the axis of revolution adds a fixed length to each radius.
            The inner radius of a typical slice, <m>r(x)</m>,
            is given by <m>r(x) = x^2 + 1</m>,
            while the outer radius is <m>R(x) = x+1</m>.
          </p>

          <figure xml:id="F-6-2-Ex4">
            <caption>The solid of revolution described in <xref ref="Ex-6-2-AboutNotY">Example</xref>.</caption>
            <image width="47%" source="images/6_2_Ex4" />
          </figure>
        <p>
          Therefore, the volume of a typical slice is
          <me>
            V_{\text{slice} } = \pi[ R(x)^2 - r(x)^2 ] \Delta x = \pi \left[ (x+1)^2 - (x^2 + 1)^2 \right] \Delta x
          </me>.
        </p>

        <p>
          Finally, we integrate to find the total volume, and
          <me>
            V = \int_0^1  \pi \left[ (x+1)^2 - (x^2 + 1)^2 \right] \, dx = \frac{7}{15} \pi
          </me>.
        </p>
      </solution>
    </example>

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-6-2-3.xml" />
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <title>Summary</title>
    <p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <p>
            We can use a definite integral to find the volume of a three-dimensional solid of revolution that results from revolving a two-dimensional region about a particular axis by taking slices perpendicular to the axis of revolution which will then be circular disks or washers.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li>
          <p>
            If we revolve about a vertical line and slice perpendicular to that line,
            then our slices are horizontal and of thickness <m>\Delta y</m>.
            This leads us to integrate with respect to <m>y</m>,
            as opposed to with respect to <m>x</m> when we slice a solid vertically.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li>
          <p>
            If we revolve about a line other than the <m>x</m>- or <m>y</m>-axis,
            we need to carefully account for the shift that occurs in the radius of a typical slice.
            Normally,
      this shift involves taking a sum or difference of the function along with the constant connected to the equation for the horizontal or vertical line;
            a well-labeled diagram is usually the best way to decide the new expression for the radius.
          </p>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <xi:include href="./exercises/ez-6-2.xml" />
</section>

