<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<!-- Copyright 2012-2019                                                   -->
<!-- Matthew Boelkins                                                      -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- This file is part of Active Calculus.                                 -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document -->
<!-- under the terms of the Creative Commons BY-SA license.  The work      -->
<!-- may be used for free by any party so long as attribution is given to  -->
<!-- the author(s), the work and its derivatives are used in the spirit of -->
<!-- "share and share alike".  All trademarks are the registered marks of  -->
<!-- their respective owners.                                              -->
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<section xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec-5-2-FTC2">
  <title>The Second Fundamental Theorem of Calculus</title>
  <objectives>
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>
          How does the integral function
          <m>A(x) = \int_1^x f(t) \, dt</m> define an antiderivative of <m>f</m>?
        </p>
      </li>

      <li>
        <p>
          What is the statement of the Second Fundamental Theorem of Calculus?
        </p>
      </li>

      <li>
        <p>
          How do the First and Second Fundamental Theorems of Calculus enable us to formally see how differentiation and integration are almost inverse processes?
        </p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </objectives>

  <subsection><title>Introduction</title>
    <p>
      In <xref ref="sec-4-4-FTC">Section</xref>,
      we learned the Fundamental Theorem of Calculus (FTC), which from here forward will be referred to as the <em>First</em>
      Fundamental Theorem of Calculus,
          <idx><h>Fundamental Theorem of Calculus</h><h>First</h></idx>
      as in this section we develop a corresponding result that follows it.
      Recall that the First FTC tells us that if <m>f</m> is a continuous function on <m>[a,b]</m> and <m>F</m> is any antiderivative of <m>f</m>
      (that is, <m>F' = f</m>),
      then
      <me>
        \int_a^b f(x) \, dx = F(b) - F(a)
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p>
      We have used this result in two settings:

      <ol marker="1">
        <li>
          <p>
            If we have a graph of <m>f</m> and we can compute the exact area bounded by <m>f</m> 
            on an interval <m>[a,b]</m>,
            we can compute the change in an antiderivative <m>F</m> over the interval.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li>
          <p>
            If we can find an algebraic formula for an antiderivative of <m>f</m>,
            we can evaluate the integral to find the net signed area bounded by the function on the interval.
          </p>
        </li>
      </ol>

      For the former, see <xref ref="PA-5-1">Preview Activity</xref>
      or <xref ref="act-5-1-1">Activity</xref>.
      For the latter, we can easily evaluate exactly integrals such as
      <me>
        \int_1^4 x^2 \, dx
      </me>,
      since we know that the function
      <m>F(x) = \frac{1}{3}x^3</m> is an antiderivative of <m>f(x) = x^2</m>.
      Thus,
      <md>
        <mrow>\int_1^4 x^2 \, dx &amp;= \frac{1}{3}x^3 \bigg\vert_1^4</mrow>
        <mrow>&amp;=  \frac{1}{3}(4)^3 - \frac{1}{3}(1)^3</mrow>
        <mrow>&amp;=  21</mrow>
      </md>.
    </p>

    <p>
      Thus, the First FTC can be used in two ways.
      First, to find the difference
      <m>F(b) - F(a)</m> for an antiderivative <m>F</m> of the integrand <m>f</m>,
      even if we may not have a formula for <m>F</m> itself.
      To do this,
      we must know the value of the integral <m>\int_a^b f(x) \, dx</m> exactly,
      perhaps through known geometric formulas for area.
      In addition,
      the First FTC provides a way to find the exact value of a definite integral,
      and hence a certain net signed area exactly,
      by finding an antiderivative of the integrand and evaluating its total change over the interval.
      In this case,
      we need to know a formula for the antiderivative <m>F</m>.
      Both of these perspectives are reflected in <xref ref="F-5-2-Intro">Figure</xref>.
    </p>

    <figure xml:id="F-5-2-Intro">
      <caption>At left, the graph of <m>f(x) = x^2</m> on the interval <m>[1,4]</m> and the area it bounds.  At right, the antiderivative function <m>F(x) = \frac{1}{3}x^3</m>, whose total change on <m>[1,4]</m> is the value of the definite integral at left.</caption>
      <image width="100%" source="images/5_2_Intro"/>
    </figure>

    <p>
      The value of a definite integral may have additional meaning depending on context:
      as the change in position when the integrand is a velocity function,
      the total amount of pollutant leaked from a tank when the integrand is the rate at which pollution is leaking,
      or other total changes if the integrand is a rate function.
      Also, the value of the definite integral is connected to the average value of a continuous function on a given interval:
      <m>f_{\operatorname{AVG} [a,b]} = \frac{1}{b-a} \int_a^b f(x) \, dx</m>.
    </p>

    <p>
      In the last part of <xref ref="sec-5-1-antid-graphs">Section</xref>,
      we studied integral functions of the form <m>A(x) = \int_c^x f(t) \, dt</m>.
      <xref ref="F-5-1-IntFxn">Figure</xref>
      is a particularly important image to keep in mind as we work with integral functions,
      and the corresponding <url href="https://gvsu.edu/s/cz" visual="gvsu.edu/s/cz">applet</url>
      can help us understand the function <m>A</m>.
      In what follows,
      we use the First FTC to gain additional understanding of the function <m>A(x) = \int_c^x f(t) \, dt</m>,
      where the integrand <m>f</m> is given
      (either through a graph or a formula),
      and <m>c</m> is a constant.
    </p>

    <xi:include href="./previews/PA-5-2.xml"/>
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <title>The Second Fundamental Theorem of Calculus</title>
    <idx><h>Fundamental Theorem of Calculus</h><h>Second</h></idx>

    <p>
      The result of <xref ref="PA-5-2">Preview Activity</xref>
      is not particular to the function <m>f(t) = 4-2t</m>,
      nor to the choice of <q><m>1</m></q>
      as the lower bound in the integral that defines the function <m>A</m>.
      For instance,
      if we let <m>f(t) = \cos(t) - t</m> and set <m>A(x) = \int_2^x f(t) \, dt</m>,
      we can determine a formula for <m>A</m> by the First FTC. Specifically,
      <md>
        <mrow>A(x) &amp;=  \int_2^x (\cos(t) - t) \, dt</mrow>
        <mrow>&amp;=  \sin(t) - \frac{1}{2}t^2 \bigg\vert_2^x</mrow>
        <mrow>&amp;=  \sin(x) -  \frac{1}{2}x^2 - \left(\sin(2) - 2 \right)</mrow>
      </md>.
    </p>

    <p>
      Differentiating <m>A(x)</m>,
      since <m>(\sin(2) - 2)</m> is constant, it follows that
      <me>
        A'(x) = \cos(x) - x
      </me>,
      and thus we see that <m>A'(x) = f(x)</m>,
      so <m>A</m> is an antiderivative of <m>f</m>.
      And since <m>A(2) = \int_2^2 f(t) \, dt = 0</m>,
      <m>A</m> is the only antiderivative of <m>f</m> for which <m>A(2) = 0</m>.
    </p>

    <p>
      In general, if <m>f</m> is any continuous function,
      and we define the function <m>A</m> by the rule
      <me>
        A(x) = \int_c^x f(t) \, dt
      </me>,
      where <m>c</m> is an arbitrary constant,
      then we can show that <m>A</m> is an antiderivative of <m>f</m>.
      To see why, let's demonstrate that
      <m>A'(x) = f(x)</m> by using the limit definition of the derivative.
      Doing so, we observe that
      <mdn>
        <mrow number="no">A'(x) \amp = \lim_{h \to 0} \frac{A(x+h) - A(x)}{h}</mrow>
        <mrow number="no">\amp = \lim_{h \to 0} \frac{\int_c^{x+h} f(t) \, dt - \int_c^x f(t) \, dt}{h}</mrow>
        <mrow xml:id="E-FTC2limdef">\amp = \lim_{h \to 0} \frac{\int_x^{x+h} f(t) \, dt}{h}</mrow>
      </mdn>,
      where <xref ref="E-FTC2limdef">Equation</xref>
      follows from the fact that <m>\int_c^x f(t) \,dt + \int_x^{x+h} f(t) \, dt = \int_c^{x+h} f(t) \, dt</m>.
      Now, observe that for small values of <m>h</m>,
      <me>
        \int_x^{x+h} f(t) \, dt \approx f(x) \cdot h
      </me>,
      by a simple left-hand approximation of the integral.
      Thus, as we take the limit in <xref ref="E-FTC2limdef">Equation</xref>,
      it follows that
      <me>
        A'(x) =  \lim_{h \to 0} \frac{\int_x^{x+h} f(t) \, dt}{h} = \lim_{h \to 0} \frac{f(x) \cdot h}{h} = f(x)
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p>
      Hence, <m>A</m> is indeed an antiderivative of <m>f</m>.
      In addition, <m>A(c) = \int_c^c f(t) \, dt = 0</m>.
      The preceding argument demonstrates the truth of the Second Fundamental Theorem of Calculus,
      which we state as follows.
    </p>

    <assemblage xml:id="FTC-2">
      <title>The Second Fundamental Theorem of Calculus</title>
      <p>
            <idx><h>second fundamental theorem of calculus</h></idx>
        If <m>f</m> is a continuous function and <m>c</m> is any constant,
        then <m>f</m> has a unique antiderivative <m>A</m> that satisfies <m>A(c) = 0</m>,
        and that antiderivative is given by the rule <m>A(x) = \int_c^x f(t) \, dt</m>.
      </p>
    </assemblage>

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-5-2-1.xml"/>
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <title>Understanding Integral Functions</title>
    <p>
      The Second FTC provides us with a way to construct an antiderivative of any continuous function.
      In particular,
      if we are given a continuous function <m>g</m> and wish to find an antiderivative <m>G</m>,
      we can now say that
      <me>
        G(x) = \int_c^x g(t) \, dt
      </me>
      provides the rule for such an antiderivative,
      and moreover that <m>G(c) = 0</m>.
      Note especially that we know that <m>G'(x) = g(x)</m>, or
      <men xml:id="E_diffint">
        \frac{d}{dx} \left[ \int_c^x g(t) \, dt \right] = g(x)
      </men>.
    </p>

    <p>
      This result is useful for understanding the graph of <m>G</m>.
    </p>

    <example>
      <statement>
        <p>
          Investigate the behavior of the integral function
          <me>
            E(x) = \int_0^x e^{-t^2} \, dt
          </me>.
        </p>
      </statement>
      <solution>
        <p>
          <m>E</m> is closely related to the well known <em>error function</em>
              <idx><h>error function</h></idx><fn>
          The error function is defined by the rule
          <m>\erf (x) = \frac{2}{\sqrt{\pi}} \int_0^x e^{-t^2} \,dt</m> and has the key property that
          <m>0 \le \erf (x) \lt 1</m> for all <m>x \ge 0</m> and moreover that <m>\lim_{x \to \infty} \erf (x) = 1</m>.
          </fn> in probability and statistics.
          It turns out that the function
          <m>e^{-t^2}</m> does not have an elementary antiderivative.
        </p>

        <p>
          While we cannot evaluate <m>E</m> exactly for any value other than <m>x = 0</m>,
          we still can gain a tremendous amount of information about the function <m>E</m>.
          By applying the rule in <xref ref="E_diffint">Equation</xref> to <m>E</m>,
          it follows that
          <me>
            E'(x) = \frac{d}{dx} \left[ \int_0^x e^{-t^2} \, dt \right] = e^{-x^2}
          </me>,
          so we know a formula for the derivative of <m>E</m>,
          and we know that <m>E(0) = 0</m>.
          This information is precisely the type we were given in <xref ref="act-3-1-1">Activity</xref>,
          where we were given information about the derivative of a function,
          but lacked a formula for the function itself.
        </p>

        <p>
          Using the first and second derivatives of <m>E</m>,
          along with the fact that <m>E(0) = 0</m>,
          we can determine more information about the behavior of <m>E</m>.
          First, we note that for all real numbers <m>x</m>,
          <m>e^{-x^2} \gt 0</m>, and thus <m>E'(x) \gt 0</m> for all <m>x</m>.
          Thus <m>E</m> is an always increasing function.
          Further, as <m>x \to \infty</m>,
          <m>E'(x) = e^{-x^2} \to 0</m>,
          so the slope of the function <m>E</m> tends to zero as
          <m>x \to \infty</m>
          (and similarly as <m>x \to -\infty</m>).
          Indeed, it turns out that <m>E</m> has horizontal asymptotes as <m>x</m> increases or decreases without bound.
        </p>

        <p>
          In addition, we can observe that <m>E''(x) = -2xe^{-x^2}</m>,
          and that <m>E''(0) = 0</m>,
          while <m>E''(x) \lt 0</m> for <m>x \gt 0</m> and <m>E''(x) \gt 0</m> for <m>x \lt 0</m>.
          This information tells us that <m>E</m> is concave up for <m>x\lt 0</m> and concave down for <m>x \gt 0</m> with a point of inflection at <m>x = 0</m>.
        </p>

        <p>
          The only thing we lack at this point is a sense of how big <m>E</m> can get as <m>x</m> increases.
          If we use a midpoint Riemann sum with 10 subintervals to estimate <m>E(2)</m>,
          we see that <m>E(2) \approx 0.8822</m>;
          a similar calculation to estimate <m>E(3)</m> shows little change (<m>E(3) \approx 0.8862</m>),
          so it appears that as <m>x</m> increases without bound,
          <m>E</m> approaches a value just larger than <m>0.886</m>,
          which aligns with the fact that <m>E</m> has horizontal asymptotes.
          Putting all of this information together (and using the symmetry of <m>f(t) = e^{-t^2}</m>),
          we see the results shown in <xref ref="F-5-2-erf">Figure</xref>.
        </p>

        <figure xml:id="F-5-2-erf">
          <caption>At left, the graph of <m>f(t) = e^{-t^2}</m>.  At right, the integral function <m>E(x) = \int_0^x e^{-t^2} \ dt</m>, which is the unique antiderivative of <m>f</m> that satisfies <m>E(0) = 0</m>.</caption>
          <image width="100%" source="images/5_2_erf"/>
        </figure>

        <p>
          Because <m>E</m> is the antiderivative of
          <m>f(t) = e^{-t^2}</m> that satisfies <m>E(0) = 0</m>,
          values on the graph of <m>y = E(x)</m> represent the net signed area of the region bounded by
          <m>f(t) = e^{-t^2}</m> from 0 up to <m>x</m>.
          We see that the value of <m>E</m> increases rapidly near zero but then levels off as <m>x</m> increases,
          since there is less and less additional accumulated area bounded by
          <m>f(t) = e^{-t^2}</m> as <m>x</m> increases.
        </p>
      </solution>
    </example>

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-5-2-2.xml"/>
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <title>Differentiating an Integral Function</title>
    <p>
      We have seen that the Second FTC enables us to construct an antiderivative <m>F</m> for any continuous function <m>f</m> as the integral function <m>F(x) = \int_c^x f(t) \, dt</m>.
      If we have a function of the form <m>F(x) = \int_c^x f(t) \, dt</m>,
      then we know that <m>F'(x) = \frac{d}{dx} \left[\int_c^x f(t) \, dt \right] = f(x)</m>.
      This shows that integral functions,
      while perhaps having the most complicated formulas of any functions we have encountered,
      are nonetheless particularly simple to differentiate.
      For instance, if
      <me>
        F(x) = \int_{\pi}^x \sin(t^2) \, dt
      </me>,
      then by the Second FTC, we know immediately that
      <me>
        F'(x) = \sin(x^2)
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p>
      In general,
      we know by the Second FTC that
      <me>
        \frac{d}{dx} \left[ \int_a^x f(t) \, dt \right] = f(x)
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p>
      This equation says that
      <q>the derivative of the integral function whose integrand is <m>f</m>,
      is <m>f</m>.</q> We see that if we first integrate the function <m>f</m> from <m>t = a</m> to <m>t = x</m>,
      and then differentiate with respect to <m>x</m>,
      these two processes <q>undo</q> each other.
    </p>

    <p>
      What happens if we differentiate a function <m>f(t)</m> and then integrate the result from <m>t = a</m> to <m>t = x</m>?
      That is, what can we say about the quantity
      <me>
        \int_a^x \frac{d}{dt} \left[ f(t) \right] \, dt?
      </me>
    </p>

    <p>
      We note that <m>f(t)</m> is an antiderivative of
      <m>\frac{d}{dt} \left[ f(t) \right]</m> and apply the First FTC.
      We see that
      <md>
        <mrow>\int_a^x \frac{d}{dt} \left[ f(t) \right] \, dt &amp;=  f(t) \bigg\vert_a^x</mrow>
        <mrow>&amp;=  f(x) - f(a)</mrow>
      </md>.
    </p>

    <p>
      Thus, we see that if we first differentiate <m>f</m> and then integrate the result from <m>a</m> to <m>x</m>,
      we return to the function <m>f</m>,
      minus the constant value <m>f(a)</m>.
      So the two processes almost undo each other,
      up to the constant <m>f(a)</m>.
    </p>

    <p>
      The observations made in the preceding two paragraphs demonstrate that differentiating and integrating
      (where we integrate from a constant up to a variable)
      are almost inverse processes.
      This should not be surprising:
      integrating involves antidifferentiating,
      which reverses the process of differentiating.
      On the other hand, we see that there is some subtlety involved,
      because integrating the derivative of a function does not quite produce the function itself.
      This is because every function has an entire family of antiderivatives,
      and any two of those antiderivatives differ only by a constant.
    </p>

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-5-2-3.xml"/>
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <title>Summary</title>
    <p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <p>
            For a continuous function <m>f</m>,
            the integral function
            <m>A(x) = \int_1^x f(t) \, dt</m> defines an antiderivative of <m>f</m>.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li>
          <p>
            The Second Fundamental Theorem of Calculus is the formal,
            more general statement of the preceding fact:
            if <m>f</m> is a continuous function and <m>c</m> is any constant,
            then <m>A(x) = \int_c^x f(t) \, dt</m> is the unique antiderivative of <m>f</m> that satisfies <m>A(c) = 0</m>.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li>
          <p>
            Together,
            the First and Second FTC enable us to formally see how differentiation and integration are almost inverse processes through the observations that
            <me>
              \int_c^x \frac{d}{dt} \left[ f(t) \right] \, dt = f(x) - f(c)
            </me>
            and
            <me>
              \frac{d}{dx} \left[ \int_c^x f(t) \, dt \right] = f(x)
            </me>.
          </p>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <xi:include href="./exercises/ez-5-2.xml"/>
</section>
