<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<!-- Copyright 2012-2019                                                   -->
<!-- Matthew Boelkins                                                      -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- This file is part of Active Calculus.                                 -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document -->
<!-- under the terms of the Creative Commons BY-SA license.  The work      -->
<!-- may be used for free by any party so long as attribution is given to  -->
<!-- the author(s), the work and its derivatives are used in the spirit of -->
<!-- "share and share alike".  All trademarks are the registered marks of  -->
<!-- their respective owners.                                              -->
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<section xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec-2-2-sin-cos">
  <title>The sine and cosine functions</title>
  <objectives>
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>
          What is a graphical justification for why <m>\frac{d}{dx}[a^x] = a^x \ln(a)</m>?
        </p>
      </li>

      <li>
        <p>
          What do the graphs of <m>y = \sin(x)</m> and
          <m>y = \cos(x)</m> suggest as formulas for their respective derivatives?
        </p>
      </li>

      <li>
        <p>
          Once we know the derivatives of <m>\sin(x)</m> and <m>\cos(x)</m>,
          how do previous derivative rules work when these functions are involved?
        </p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </objectives>

  <subsection><title>Introduction</title>
    <p>
      Throughout <xref ref="C-2">Chapter</xref>,
      we will develop shortcut derivative rules to help us bypass the limit definition and quickly compute <m>f'(x)</m> from a formula for <m>f(x)</m>.
      In <xref ref="sec-2-1-elem-rules">Section</xref>,
      we stated the rule for power functions,
      <me>
        \text{if}~ f(x) = x^n,~ \text{then}~ f'(x) = nx^{n-1}
      </me>,
      and the rule for exponential functions,
      <me>
        \text{if}~ a ~ \text{is a positive real number and}~ f(x) = a^x,~
        \text{then}~ f'(x) = a^x \ln(a)
      </me>.
      Later in this section,
      we will use a graphical argument to conjecture derivative formulas for the sine and cosine functions.
    </p>

    <xi:include href="./previews/PA-2-2.xml"/>
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <title>The sine and cosine functions</title>
    <p>
      The sine and cosine functions are among the most important functions in all of mathematics.
      Sometimes called the <em>circular</em>
      functions due to their definition on the unit circle,
      these periodic functions play a key role in modeling repeating phenomena such as tidal elevations,
      the behavior of an oscillating mass attached to a spring,
      or the location of a point on a bicycle tire.
      Like polynomial and exponential functions,
      the sine and cosine functions are considered basic functions,
      ones that are often used in building more complicated functions.
      As such, we would like to know formulas for
      <m>\frac{d}{dx} [\sin(x)]</m> and <m>\frac{d}{dx} [\cos(x)]</m>,
      and the next two activities lead us to that end.
    </p>

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-2-2-1.xml"/>

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-2-2-2.xml"/>

    <p>
      The results of the two preceding activities suggest that the sine and cosine functions not only have beautiful connections such as the identities <m>\sin^2(x) + \cos^2(x) = 1</m> and
      <m>\cos(x - \frac{\pi}{2}) = \sin(x)</m>,
      but that they are even further linked through calculus,
      as the derivative of each involves the other.
      The following rules summarize the results of the activities<fn>
      These two rules may be formally proved using the limit definition of the derivative and the expansion identities for
      <m>\sin(x+h)</m> and <m>\cos(x+h)</m>.
      </fn>.
    </p>

    <assemblage xml:id="sine-cosine-fxns">
      <title>Sine and Cosine Functions</title>
      <p>
            <idx><h>derivative</h><h>cosine</h></idx>
            <idx><h>derivative</h><h>sine</h></idx>
        For all real numbers <m>x</m>,
        <me>
          \frac{d}{dx} [\sin(x)] = \cos(x) \ \ \text{and}  \ \ \frac{d}{dx} [\cos(x)] = -\sin(x)
        </me>.
      </p>
    </assemblage>

    <p>
      We have now added the sine and cosine functions to our library of basic functions whose derivatives we know.
      The constant multiple and sum rules still hold, of course,
      as well as all of the inherent meaning of the derivative.
    </p>

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-2-2-3.xml"/>
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <title>Summary</title>
    <p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <p>
            For an exponential function <m>f(x) = a^x</m> <m>(a \gt 1)</m>,
            the graph of <m>f'(x)</m> appears to be a scaled version of the original function.
            In particular, careful analysis of the graph of<m>f(x) = 2^x</m>,
            suggests that <m>\frac{d}{dx}[2^x] = 2^x \ln(2)</m>,
            which is a special case of the rule we stated in <xref ref="sec-2-1-elem-rules">Section</xref>.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li>
          <p>
            By carefully analyzing the graphs of
            <m>y = \sin(x)</m> and <m>y = \cos(x)</m>,
            and by using the limit definition of the derivative at select points,
            we found that <m>\frac{d}{dx} [\sin(x)] = \cos(x)</m> and <m>\frac{d}{dx} [\cos(x)] = -\sin(x)</m>.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li>
          <p>
            We note that all previously encountered derivative rules still hold,
            but now may also be applied to functions involving the sine and cosine.
            All of the established meaning of the derivative applies to these trigonometric functions as well.
          </p>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <xi:include href="./exercises/ez-2-2.xml"/>
</section>
