<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<!-- Copyright 2012-2019                                                   -->
<!-- Matthew Boelkins                                                      -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- This file is part of Active Calculus.                                 -->
<!--                                                                       -->
<!-- Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document -->
<!-- under the terms of the Creative Commons BY-SA license.  The work      -->
<!-- may be used for free by any party so long as attribution is given to  -->
<!-- the author(s), the work and its derivatives are used in the spirit of -->
<!-- "share and share alike".  All trademarks are the registered marks of  -->
<!-- their respective owners.                                              -->
<!-- **********************************************************************-->
<section xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:id="sec-5-6-num-int" oldpermid="hec">
  <title>Numerical Integration</title>
  <objectives permid="ycn">
    <ul permid="KqF">
      <li permid="WEX">
        <p permid="HvZ">
          How do we accurately evaluate a definite integral such as
          <m>\int_0^1 e^{-x^2} \, dx</m> when we cannot use the First Fundamental Theorem of Calculus because the integrand lacks an elementary algebraic antiderivative?
          Are there ways to generate accurate estimates without using extremely large values of <m>n</m> in Riemann sums?
        </p>
      </li>

      <li permid="CMg">
        <p permid="nDi">
          What is the Trapezoid Rule,
          and how is it related to left,
          right, and middle Riemann sums?
        </p>
      </li>

      <li permid="iTp">
        <p permid="TKr">
          How are the errors in the Trapezoid Rule and Midpoint Rule related,
          and how can they be used to develop an even more accurate rule?
        </p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </objectives>

  <introduction permid="ejw">
    <p permid="snb">
      When we first explored finding the net signed area bounded by a curve,
      we developed the concept of a Riemann sum as a helpful estimation tool and a key step in the definition of the definite integral.
      Recall that the left, right,
      and middle Riemann sums of a function <m>f</m> on an interval <m>[a,b]</m> are given by
      <mdn permid="Fln">
        <mrow xml:id="E-Left">L_n = f(x_0) \Delta x + f(x_1) \Delta x + \cdots + f(x_{n-1}) \Delta x \amp= \sum_{i = 0}^{n-1} f(x_i) \Delta x,</mrow>
        <mrow xml:id="E-Right">R_n = f(x_1) \Delta x + f(x_2) \Delta x + \cdots + f(x_{n}) \Delta x \amp= \sum_{i = 1}^{n} f(x_i) \Delta x,</mrow>
        <mrow xml:id="E-Mid">M_n = f(\overline{x}_1) \Delta x + f(\overline{x}_2) \Delta x + \cdots + f(\overline{x}_{n}) \Delta x \amp= \sum_{i = 1}^{n} f(\overline{x}_i) \Delta x</mrow>
      </mdn>,
      where <m>x_0 = a</m>, <m>x_i = a + i\Delta x</m>,
      <m>x_n = b</m>, and <m>\Delta x = \frac{b-a}{n}</m>.
      For the middle sum,
      we defined <m>\overline{x}_{i} = (x_{i-1} + x_i)/2</m>.
    </p>

    <p permid="Yuk">
      A Riemann sum is a sum of
      (possibly signed)
      areas of rectangles.
      The value of <m>n</m> determines the number of rectangles,
      and our choice of left endpoints, right endpoints,
      or midpoints determines the heights of the rectangles.
      We can see the similarities and differences among these three options in <xref ref="F-5-6-LRMsum">Figure</xref>,
      where we consider the function
      <m>f(x) = \frac{1}{20}(x-4)^3 + 7</m> on the interval <m>[1,8]</m>,
      and use 5 rectangles for each of the Riemann sums.
    </p>

    <figure xml:id="F-5-6-LRMsum" permid="QPL">
      <caption>Left, right, and middle Riemann sums for <m>y = f(x)</m> on <m>[1,8]</m> with 5 subintervals.</caption>
      <image width="100%" source="images/5_6_LRMsum" />
    </figure>

    <p permid="EBt">
      While it is a good exercise to compute a few Riemann sums by hand,
      just to ensure that we understand how they work and how varying the function,
      the number of subintervals,
      and the choice of endpoints or midpoints affects the result,
      using computing technology is the best way to determine <m>L_n</m>,
      <m>R_n</m>, and <m>M_n</m>.
      Any computer algebra system will offer this capability;
      as we saw in <xref ref="PA-4-3">Preview Activity</xref>,
      a straightforward option that is freely available online is <url href="https://gvsu.edu/s/a9" visual="gvsu.edu/s/a9">this applet</url>.
      Note that we can adjust the formula for <m>f(x)</m>,
      the window of <m>x</m>- and <m>y</m>-values of interest,
      the number of subintervals, and the method.
      (See <xref ref="PA-4-3">Preview Activity</xref>
      for any needed reminders on how the applet works.)
    </p>

    <p permid="kIC">
      In this section we explore several different alternatives for estimating definite integrals.
      Our main goal is to develop formulas to estimate definite integrals accurately without using a large numbers of rectangles.
    </p>

    <xi:include href="./previews/PA-5-6.xml" />
  </introduction>

  <subsection permid="Nll">
    <title>The Trapezoid Rule</title>
    <idx><h>trapezoid rule</h></idx>

    <p permid="wWU">
      So far, we have used the simplest possible quadrilaterals
      (that is, rectangles)
      to estimate areas.
      It is natural, however,
      to wonder if other familiar shapes might serve us even better.
    </p>

    <p permid="ded">
      An alternative to <m>L_n</m>, <m>R_n</m>,
      and <m>M_n</m> is called the <em>Trapezoid Rule</em>.
      Rather than using a rectangle to estimate the (signed) area bounded by
      <m>y = f(x)</m> on a small interval, we use a trapezoid.
      For example, in <xref ref="F-5-6-TRAP">Figure</xref>,
      we estimate the area under the curve using three subintervals and the trapezoids that result from connecting the corresponding points on the curve with straight lines.
    </p>

    <figure xml:id="F-5-6-TRAP" permid="NVf">
      <caption>Estimating <m>\int_a^b f(x) \  dx</m> using three subintervals and trapezoids, rather than rectangles, where <m>a = x_0</m> and <m>b = x_3</m>.</caption>
      <image width="73%" source="images/5_6_TRAP" />
    </figure>

    <p permid="Jlm">
      The biggest difference between the Trapezoid Rule and a Riemann sum is that on each subinterval,
      the Trapezoid Rule uses two function values, rather than one,
      to estimate the (signed) area bounded by the curve.
      For instance, to compute <m>D_1</m>,
      the area of the trapezoid on <m>[x_0, x_1]</m>,
      we observe that the left base has length <m>f(x_0)</m>,
      while the right base has length <m>f(x_1)</m>.
      The height of the trapezoid is <m>x_1 - x_0 = \Delta x = \frac{b-a}{3}</m>.
      The area of a trapezoid is the average of the bases times the height,
      so we have
      <me permid="lsw">
        D_1 = \frac{1}{2}(f(x_0) + f(x_1)) \cdot \Delta x
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p permid="psv">
      Using similar computations for <m>D_2</m> and <m>D_3</m>,
      we find that <m>T_3</m>,
      the trapezoidal approximation to <m>\int_a^b f(x) \, dx</m> is given by
      <md permid="RzF">
        <mrow>T_3 &amp;=  D_1 + D_2 + D_3</mrow>
        <mrow>&amp;= \frac{1}{2}(f(x_0) + f(x_1)) \cdot \Delta x + \frac{1}{2}(f(x_1) + f(x_2)) \cdot \Delta x + \frac{1}{2}(f(x_2) + f(x_3)) \cdot \Delta x</mrow>
      </md>.
    </p>

    <p permid="VzE">
      Because both left and right endpoints are being used,
      we recognize within the trapezoidal approximation the use of both left and right Riemann sums.
      Rearranging the expression for <m>T_3</m> by removing factors of
      <m>\frac{1}{2}</m> and <m>\Delta x </m>,
      grouping the left endpoint and right endpoint evaluations of <m>f</m>,
      we see that
      <men xml:id="E-Trap3" permid="xGO">
        T_3 =  \frac{1}{2} \left[ f(x_0) + f(x_1) + f(x_2) \right] \Delta x   +  \frac{1}{2} \left[ f(x_1) + f(x_2) + f(x_3) \right] \Delta x
      </men>.
    </p>

    <p permid="BGN">
      We now observe that two familiar sums have arisen.
      The left Riemann sum <m>L_3</m> is <m>L_3 = f(x_0) \Delta x + f(x_1) \Delta x + f(x_2) \Delta x</m>,
      and the right Riemann sum is <m>R_3 = f(x_1) \Delta x + f(x_2) \Delta x + f(x_3) \Delta x</m>.
      Substituting <m>L_3</m> and <m>R_3</m> for the corresponding expressions in <xref ref="E-Trap3">Equation</xref>,
      it follows that <m>T_3 = \frac{1}{2} \left[ L_3 + R_3 \right]</m>.
      We have thus seen a very important result:
      using trapezoids to estimate the (signed) area bounded by a curve is the same as averaging the estimates generated by using left and right endpoints.
    </p>

    <assemblage permid="RVe">
      <title>The Trapezoid Rule</title>
      <p permid="hNW">
        The trapezoidal approximation, <m>T_n</m>,
        of the definite integral <m>\int_a^b f(x) \, dx</m> using <m>n</m> subintervals is given by the rule
        <md permid="dNX">
          <mrow>T_n =\mathstrut \amp  \left[\frac{1}{2}(f(x_0) + f(x_1)) + \frac{1}{2}(f(x_1) + f(x_2))  + \cdots + \frac{1}{2}(f(x_{n-1}) + f(x_n)) \right] \Delta x.</mrow>
          <mrow>=\mathstrut \amp  \sum_{i=0}^{n-1} \frac{1}{2}(f(x_i) + f(x_{i+1}))  \Delta x</mrow>
        </md>.
        Moreover, <m>T_n = \frac{1}{2} \left[ L_n + R_n \right]</m>.
      </p>
    </assemblage>

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-5-6-1.xml" />
  </subsection>

  <subsection permid="tsu">
    <title>Comparing the Midpoint and Trapezoid Rules</title>
    <p permid="uco">
      We know from the definition of the definite integral
      that if we let <m>n</m> be large enough,
      we can make any of the approximations <m>L_n</m>,
      <m>R_n</m>,
      and <m>M_n</m> as close as we'd like
      (in theory)
      to the exact value of <m>\int_a^b f(x) \, dx</m>.
      Thus, it may be natural to wonder why we ever use any rule other than <m>L_n</m> or <m>R_n</m>
      (with a sufficiently large <m>n</m> value)
      to estimate a definite integral.
      One of the primary reasons is that as <m>n \to \infty</m>,
      <m>\Delta x = \frac{b-a}{n} \to 0</m>,
      and thus in a Riemann sum calculation with a large <m>n</m> value,
      we end up multiplying by a number that is very close to zero.
      Doing so often generates roundoff error,
      because representing numbers close to zero accurately is a persistent challenge for computers.
    </p>

    <p permid="ajx">
      Hence, we explore ways to estimate definite integrals to high levels of precision,
      but without using extremely large values of <m>n</m>.
      Paying close attention to patterns in errors,
      such as those observed in <xref ref="act-5-6-1">Activity</xref>,
      is one way to begin to see some alternate approaches.
    </p>

    <p permid="GqG">
      To begin, we compare the errors in the Midpoint and Trapezoid rules.
      First, consider a function that is concave up on a given interval,
      and picture approximating the area bounded on that interval by both the Midpoint and Trapezoid rules using a single subinterval.
    </p>

    <figure xml:id="F-5-6-MidVTrap" permid="jDj">
      <caption>Estimating <m>\int_a^b f(x) \  dx</m> using a single subinterval: at left, the trapezoid rule; in the middle, the midpoint rule; at right, a modified way to think about the midpoint rule.</caption>
      <image width="100%" source="images/5_6_MidVTrap" />
    </figure>

    <p permid="mxP">
      As seen in <xref ref="F-5-6-MidVTrap">Figure</xref>,
      it is evident that whenever the function is concave up on an interval,
      the Trapezoid Rule with one subinterval, <m>T_1</m>,
      will overestimate the exact value of the definite integral on that interval.
      From a careful analysis of the line that bounds the top of the rectangle for the Midpoint Rule
      (shown in magenta),
      we see that if we rotate this line segment until it is tangent to the curve at the midpoint of the interval
      (as shown at right in <xref ref="F-5-6-MidVTrap">Figure</xref>),
      the resulting trapezoid has the same area as <m>M_1</m>,
      and this value is less than the exact value of the definite integral.
      Thus, when the function is concave up on the interval,
      <m>M_1</m> underestimates the integral's true value.
    </p>

    <figure xml:id="F-5-6-MidTrapError" permid="PKs">
      <caption>Comparing the error in estimating <m>\int_a^b f(x) \  dx</m> using a single subinterval: in red, the error from the Trapezoid rule; in light red, the error from the Midpoint rule.</caption>
      <image width="47%" source="images/5_6_MidTrapError" />
    </figure>

    <p permid="SEY">
      These observations extend easily to the situation where the function's concavity remains consistent but we use larger values of <m>n</m> in the Midpoint and Trapezoid Rules.
      Hence, whenever <m>f</m> is concave up on <m>[a,b]</m>,
      <m>T_n</m> will overestimate the value of <m>\int_a^b f(x) \, dx</m>,
      while <m>M_n</m> will underestimate <m>\int_a^b f(x) \, dx</m>.
      The reverse observations are true in the situation where <m>f</m> is concave down.
    </p>

    <p permid="yMh">
      Next, we compare the size of the errors between <m>M_n</m> and <m>T_n</m>.
      Again, we focus on <m>M_1</m> and <m>T_1</m> on an interval where the concavity of <m>f</m> is consistent.
      In <xref ref="F-5-6-MidTrapError">Figure</xref>,
      where the error of the Trapezoid Rule is shaded in red,
      while the error of the Midpoint Rule is shaded lighter red,
      it is visually apparent that the error in the Trapezoid Rule is more significant.
      To see how much more significant,
      let's consider two examples and some particular computations.
    </p>

    <p permid="eTq">
      If we let <m>f(x) = 1-x^2</m> and consider <m>\int_0^1 f(x) \,dx</m>,
      we know by the First FTC that the exact value of the integral is
      <me permid="JVg">
        \int_0^1 (1-x^2) \, dx = x - \frac{x^3}{3} \bigg\vert_0^1 = \frac{2}{3}
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p permid="Laz">
      Using appropriate technology to compute <m>M_4</m>,
      <m>M_8</m>, <m>T_4</m>, and <m>T_8</m>,
      as well as the corresponding errors <m>E_{M,4}</m>, <m>E_{M,8}</m>,
      <m>E_{T,4}</m>, and <m>E_{T,8}</m>,
      as we did in <xref ref="act-5-6-1">Activity</xref>,
      we find the results summarized in <xref ref="T-5-6-Ex2">Table</xref>.
      We also include the approximations and their errors for the example
      <m>\int_1^2 \frac{1}{x^2} \, dx</m> from <xref ref="act-5-6-1">Activity</xref>.
    </p>

    <table xml:id="T-5-6-Ex2" permid="ixQ">
      <title>Calculations of <m>T_4</m>, <m>M_4</m>, <m>T_8</m>, and <m>M_8</m>, along with corresponding errors, for the definite integrals <m>\int_0^1 (1-x^2) \  dx</m> and <m>\int_1^2 \frac{1}{x^2} \  dx</m>.</title>
      <tabular top="minor" bottom="minor" permid="OEZ">
        <row>
          <cell>Rule</cell>
          <cell><m>\int_0^1 (1-x^2) \,dx = 0.\overline{6}</m></cell>
          <cell>error</cell>
          <cell><m>\int_1^2 \frac{1}{x^2} \, dx = 0.5</m></cell>
          <cell>error</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell><m>T_4</m></cell>
          <cell><m>0.65625</m></cell>
          <cell><m>-0.0104166667</m></cell>
          <cell><m>0.5089937642</m></cell>
          <cell><m>0.0089937642</m></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell><m>M_4</m></cell>
          <cell><m>0.671875</m></cell>
          <cell><m>0.0052083333</m></cell>
          <cell><m>0.4955479365</m></cell>
          <cell><m>-0.0044520635</m></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell><m>T_8</m></cell>
          <cell><m>0.6640625</m></cell>
          <cell><m>-0.0026041667</m></cell>
          <cell><m>0.5022708502</m></cell>
          <cell><m>0.0022708502</m></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell><m>M_8</m></cell>
          <cell><m>0.66796875</m></cell>
          <cell><m>0.0013020833</m></cell>
          <cell><m>0.4988674899</m></cell>
          <cell><m>-0.0011325101</m></cell>
        </row>
      </tabular>

    </table>

    <p oldpermid="rhI" permid="mJe">
      For a given function <m>f</m> and interval <m>[a,b]</m>,
      <m>E_{T,4} = T_4 - \int_a^b f(x) \,dx</m> calculates the difference between the approximation generated by the Trapezoid Rule with <m>n = 4</m> and the exact value of the definite integral.
      If we look at not only <m>E_{T,4}</m>,
      but also the other errors generated by using <m>T_n</m> and <m>M_n</m> with <m>n = 4</m> and <m>n = 8</m> in the two examples noted in <xref ref="T-5-6-Ex2">Table</xref>,
      we see an evident pattern.
      Not only is the sign of the error
      (which measures whether the rule generates an over- or under-estimate)
      tied to the rule used and the function's concavity,
      but the magnitude of the errors generated by <m>T_n</m> and <m>M_n</m> seems closely connected.
      In particular,
      the errors generated by the Midpoint Rule seem to be about half the size (in absolute value) of those generated by the Trapezoid Rule.
    </p>

    <p permid="XoR">
      That is, we can observe in both examples that
      <m>E_{M,4} \approx -\frac{1}{2} E_{T,4}</m> and <m>E_{M,8} \approx -\frac{1}{2}E_{T,8}</m>.
      This property of the Midpoint and Trapezoid Rules turns out to hold in general:
      for a function of consistent concavity,
      the error in the Midpoint Rule has the opposite sign and approximately half the magnitude of the error of the Trapezoid Rule.
      Written symbolically,
      <me permid="qcp">
        E_{M,n} \approx -\frac{1}{2} E_{T,n}
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p permid="Dwa">
      This important relationship suggests a way to combine the Midpoint and Trapezoid Rules to create an even more accurate approximation to a definite integral.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection permid="ZzD">
    <title>Simpson's Rule</title>
    <idx><h>Simpson's rule</h></idx>

    <p permid="vRB">
      When we first developed the Trapezoid Rule,
      we observed that it is an average of the Left and Right Riemann sums:
      <me permid="Wjy">
        T_n = \frac{1}{2}(L_n + R_n)
      </me>.
    </p>

    <p permid="bYK">
      If a function is always increasing or always decreasing on the interval <m>[a,b]</m>,
      one of <m>L_n</m> and <m>R_n</m> will over-estimate the true value of <m>\int_a^b f(x) \, dx</m>,
      while the other will under-estimate the integral.
      Thus,
      the errors that result from <m>L_n</m> and <m>R_n</m> will have opposite signs;
      so averaging <m>L_n</m> and <m>R_n</m> eliminates a considerable amount of the error present in the respective approximations.
      In a similar way,
      it makes sense to think about averaging <m>M_n</m> and <m>T_n</m> in order to generate a still more accurate approximation.
    </p>

    <p permid="IfT">
      We've just observed that <m>M_n</m> is typically about twice as accurate as <m>T_n</m>.
      So we use the weighted average
          <idx><h>weighted average</h></idx>
      <men xml:id="E-Simpson" permid="CqH">
        S_{2n} = \frac{2M_n + T_n}{3}
      </men>.
    </p>

    <p permid="onc">
      The rule for <m>S_{2n}</m> giving by <xref ref="E-Simpson">Equation</xref>
      is usually known as <em>Simpson's Rule</em>.<fn>
      Thomas Simpson was an 18th century mathematician;
      his idea was to extend the Trapezoid rule,
      but rather than using straight lines to build trapezoids,
      to use quadratic functions to build regions whose area was bounded by parabolas
      (whose areas he could find exactly).
      Simpson's Rule is often developed from the more sophisticated perspective of using interpolation by quadratic functions.
      </fn> Note that we use
      <q><m>S_{2n}</m></q> rather that <q><m>S_n</m></q>
      since the <m>n</m> points the Midpoint Rule uses are different from the <m>n</m> points the Trapezoid Rule uses,
      and thus Simpson's Rule is using <m>2n</m> points at which to evaluate the function.
      We build upon the results in <xref ref="T-5-6-Ex2">Table</xref>
      to see the approximations generated by Simpson's Rule.
      In particular, in <xref ref="T-5-6-Ex3">Table</xref>,
      we include all of the results in <xref ref="T-5-6-Ex2">Table</xref>,
      but include additional results for
      <m>S_8 = \frac{2M_4 + T_4}{3}</m> and <m>S_{16} = \frac{2M_8 + T_8}{3}</m>.
    </p>

    <table xml:id="T-5-6-Ex3" permid="uMi">
      <title><xref ref="T-5-6-Ex2">Table</xref> updated to include <m>S_8</m>, <m>S_{16}</m>, and the corresponding errors.</title>
      <tabular top="minor" bottom="minor" permid="aTr">
        <row>
          <cell>Rule</cell>
          <cell><m>\int_0^1 (1-x^2) \,dx = 0.\overline{6}</m></cell>
          <cell>error</cell>
          <cell><m>\int_1^2 \frac{1}{x^2} \, dx = 0.5</m></cell>
          <cell>error</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell><m>T_4</m></cell>
          <cell><m>0.65625</m></cell>
          <cell><m>-0.0104166667</m></cell>
          <cell><m>0.5089937642</m></cell>
          <cell><m>0.0089937642</m></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell><m>M_4</m></cell>
          <cell><m>0.671875</m></cell>
          <cell><m>0.0052083333</m></cell>
          <cell><m>0.4955479365</m></cell>
          <cell><m>-0.0044520635</m></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell><m>S_8</m></cell>
          <cell><m>0.6666666667</m></cell>
          <cell><m>0</m></cell>
          <cell><m>0.5000298792</m></cell>
          <cell><m>0.0000298792</m></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell><m>T_8</m></cell>
          <cell><m>0.6640625</m></cell>
          <cell><m>-0.0026041667</m></cell>
          <cell><m>0.5022708502</m></cell>
          <cell><m>0.0022708502</m></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell><m>M_8</m></cell>
          <cell><m>0.66796875</m></cell>
          <cell><m>0.0013020833</m></cell>
          <cell><m>0.4988674899</m></cell>
          <cell><m>-0.0011325101</m></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell><m>S_{16}</m></cell>
          <cell><m>0.6666666667</m></cell>
          <cell><m>0</m></cell>
          <cell><m>0.5000019434</m></cell>
          <cell><m>0.0000019434</m></cell>
        </row>
      </tabular>

    </table>

    <p permid="Uul">
      The results seen in <xref ref="T-5-6-Ex3">Table</xref> are striking.
      If we consider the <m>S_{16}</m> approximation of <m>\int_1^2 \frac{1}{x^2} \, dx</m>,
      the error is only <m>E_{S,16} = 0.0000019434</m>.
      By contrast, <m>L_8 = 0.5491458502</m>,
      so the error of that estimate is <m>E_{L,8} = 0.0491458502</m>.
      Moreover, we observe that generating the approximations for Simpson's Rule is almost no additional work:
      once we have <m>L_n</m>,
      <m>R_n</m>, and <m>M_n</m> for a given value of <m>n</m>,
      it is a simple exercise to generate <m>T_n</m>,
      and from there to calculate <m>S_{2n}</m>.
      Finally, note that the error in the Simpson's Rule approximations of
      <m>\int_0^1 (1-x^2) \, dx</m> is zero!<fn>
      Similar to how the Midpoint and Trapezoid approximations are exact for linear functions, Simpson's Rule approximations are exact for quadratic and cubic functions.
      See additional discussion on this issue later in the section and in the exercises.
      </fn></p>

    <p permid="ABu">
      These rules are not only useful for approximating definite integrals such as <m>\int_0^1 e^{-x^2} \, dx</m>,
      for which we cannot find an elementary antiderivative of <m>e^{-x^2}</m>,
      but also for approximating definite integrals when we are given a function through a table of data.
    </p>

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-5-6-2.xml" />
  </subsection>

  <subsection permid="FGM">
    <title>Overall observations regarding <m>L_n</m>, <m>R_n</m>, <m>T_n</m>, <m>M_n</m>, and <m>S_{2n}</m>.</title>
    <p permid="gID">
      As we conclude our discussion of numerical approximation of definite integrals,
      it is important to summarize general trends in how the various rules over- or under-estimate the true value of a definite integral,
      and by how much.
      To revisit some past observations and see some new ones,
      we consider the following activity.
    </p>

    <xi:include href="./activities/act-5-6-3.xml" />

    <p permid="MPM">
      The results seen in <xref ref="act-5-6-3">Activity</xref> generalize nicely.
      For instance,
      if <m>f</m> is decreasing on <m>[a,b]</m>,
      <m>L_n</m> will over-estimate the exact value of <m>\int_a^b f(x) \,dx</m>,
      and if <m>f</m> is concave down on <m>[a,b]</m>,
      <m>M_n</m> will over-estimate the exact value of the integral.
      An excellent exercise is to write a collection of scenarios of possible function behavior,
      and then categorize whether each of <m>L_n</m>, <m>R_n</m>,
      <m>T_n</m>, and <m>M_n</m> is an over- or under-estimate.
    </p>

    <p permid="sWV">
      Finally, we make two important notes about Simpson's Rule.
      When T.<nbsp />Simpson first developed this rule,
      his idea was to replace the function <m>f</m> on a given interval with a quadratic function that shared three values with the function <m>f</m>.
      In so doing,
      he guaranteed that this new approximation rule would be exact for the definite integral of any quadratic polynomial.
      In one of the pleasant surprises of numerical analysis,
      it turns out that even though it was designed to be exact for quadratic polynomials, Simpson's Rule is exact for any cubic polynomial:
      that is, if we are interested in an integral such as <m>\int_2^5 (5x^3 - 2x^2 + 7x - 4)\, dx</m>,
      <m>S_{2n}</m> will always be exact,
      regardless of the value of <m>n</m>.
      This is just one more piece of evidence that shows how effective Simpson's Rule is as an approximation tool for estimating definite integrals.<fn>
      One reason that Simpson's Rule is so effective is that <m>S_{2n}</m> benefits from using <m>2n+1</m> points of data.
      Because it combines <m>M_n</m>,
      which uses <m>n</m> midpoints, and <m>T_n</m>,
      which uses the <m>n+1</m> endpoints of the chosen subintervals,
      <m>S_{2n}</m> takes advantage of the maximum amount of information we have when we know function values at the endpoints and midpoints of <m>n</m> subintervals.
      </fn></p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection permid="lNV">
    <title>Summary</title>
    <p permid="Zee">
      <ul permid="qxO">
        <li permid="Pay">
          <p permid="zRA">
            For a definite integral such as
            <m>\int_0^1 e^{-x^2} \, dx</m> when we cannot use the First Fundamental Theorem of Calculus because the integrand lacks an elementary algebraic antiderivative,
            we can estimate the integral's value by using a sequence of Riemann sum approximations.
            Typically, we start by computing <m>L_n</m>, <m>R_n</m>,
            and <m>M_n</m> for one or more chosen values of <m>n</m>.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="vhH">
          <p permid="fYJ">
            The Trapezoid Rule, which estimates
            <m>\int_a^b f(x) \, dx</m> by using trapezoids,
            rather than rectangles,
            can also be viewed as the average of Left and Right Riemann sums.
            That is, <m>T_n = \frac{1}{2}(L_n + R_n)</m>.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li permid="boQ">
          <p permid="MfS">
            The Midpoint Rule is typically twice as accurate as the Trapezoid Rule,
            and the signs of the respective errors of these rules are opposites.
            Hence,
            by taking the weighted average <m>S_{2n} = \frac{2M_n + T_n}{3}</m>,
            we can build a much more accurate approximation to
            <m>\int_a^b f(x) \, dx</m> by using approximations we have already computed.
            The rule for <m>S_{2n}</m> is known as Simpson's Rule,
            which can also be developed by approximating a given continuous function with pieces of quadratic polynomials.
          </p>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <xi:include href="./exercises/ez-5-6.xml" />
</section>

